Preface

The most pleasing literary labour of my life has been to translate “The Lusiads.” One of my highest aims has been to produce a translation which shall associate my name, not unpleasantly, with that of “my master, Camões.”

Those who favour me by reading this version are spared the long recital of why, how, and when Portugal’s Maro became to me the perfection of a traveller’s study. The first and chiefest charm was, doubtless, that of the Man. A wayfarer and voyager from his youth; a soldier, somewhat turbulent withal, wounded and blamed for his wounds; a moralist, a humourist, a satirist, and, consequently, no favourite with King Demos; a reverent and religious spirit after his own fashion (somewhat “Renaissance,” poetic, and Pagan), by no means after the fashion of others; an outspoken, truth-telling, lucre-despising writer; a public servant whose motto was—strange to say—Honour, not Honours; a doughty Sword and yet doughtier Pen; a type of the chivalrous age; a patriot of the purest water, so jealous of his Country’s good fame that nothing would satisfy him but to see the world bow before her perfections; a genius, the first and foremost of his day, who died in the direst poverty and distress; such in merest outline was the Man, and such was the Life which won the fondest and liveliest sympathies of the translator.

Poetas por poetas sejam lidos;
Sejam só por poetas explicadas
Suas obras divinas;

(Still by the Poets be the Poets read
Only be render’d by the Poet’s tongue
Their works divine);

writes Manuel Corrêa. Mickle expresses the sentiment with more brevity and equal point: None but a poet can translate a poet; and Coleridge assigns to a poet the property of explaining a poet. Let me add that none but a traveller can do justice to a traveller. And it so happens that most of my wanderings have unconsciously formed a running and realistic commentary upon The Lusiads. I have not only visited almost every place named in the Epos of Commerce, in many I have spent months and even years. The Arch-poet of Portugal paints from the life, he has also the insight which we call introvision; he sees with exact eyes where others are purblind or blind. Only they who have personally studied the originals of his pictures can appreciate their perfect combination of fidelity and realism with Fancy and Idealism. Here it is that the traveller-translator may do good service with his specialty.

Again, like Boccaccio, Camões reflects the Lux ex Oriente. There is a perfume of the East in everything he writes of the East: we find in his song much of its havock and all its splendour. Oriental-like, he delights in the Pathetic Fallacy; to lavish upon inanimates the attributes of animate sensation. Here again, the student of things Eastern, the “practical Orientalist,” may be useful by drawing attention to points which escape the European, however learned.

There are many translators of Camões yet to come. We are an ephemeral race, each one struggling to trample down his elder brother, like the Simoniacal Popes in the Malebolge-pit. My first excuse for adding to the half-dozen translations in the field, must be my long studies, geographical and anthropological: I can at least spare future writers the pains and penalties of saddling the exactest of poets with bad ethnology and worse topography. These may be small matters, but in local colouring every touch tells.

My chief qualifications for the task, however, are a thorough appreciation of the Poem and a hearty admiration for the Poet whom I learned to love in proportion as I learned to know him. His Lusiads has been described as une lecture saine et fortifiante. I would say far more. The Singer’s gracious and noble thoughts are reviving as the champagne-air of the mountain-top. His verse has the true heroic ring of such old ballads as:—

S’en assaut viens, devant ta lance,
En mine, en échelle, en tous lieux,
En prouesse les bons avance,
Ta dame t’en aimera mieux.

And with this love and sympathy of mine mingles not a little gratitude. During how many hopeless days and sleepless nights Camões was my companion, my consoler, my friend;—on board raft and canoe; sailer and steamer; on the camel and the mule; under the tent and the jungle-tree; upon the fire-peak and the snow-peak; on the Prairie, the Campo, the Steppe, the Desert!

Where no conversable being can be found within a march of months; and when the hot blood of youth courses through the brain, Ennui and Nostalgia are readily bred, while both are fatal to the Explorer’s full success. And, preferring to all softer lines the hard life of Discovery-travel:—

Where things that own not man’s dominion dwell,
Where foot of mortal man hath never been;—

a career which combines cultivation and education with that resistless charm, that poetry-passion of the Unknown; whose joy of mere motion lightens all sorrows and disappointments; which aids, by commune with Nature, the proper study of Mankind; which enlarges the mental view as the hill-head broadens the horizon; which made Julian a saint, Khizr a prophet, and Odin a god: this Reiselust, I say, being my ruling passion, compelled me to seek a talisman against homesickness and the nervous troubles which learned men call Phrenalgia and Autophobia.

I found this talisman in Camões.

And, if it be true that by virtue of his perfect affection and veneration for Homer, whom he loved as a second self, Chapman was enabled to reflect a something of the old Greek’s magic force and fire, I also may be permitted to hope that complete sympathy with my Poet will enable me to present the public with a copy not unworthy of Camões’ immortal work.

After all, to speak without undue modesty, my most cogent reason for printing this translation of my Master is, simply because I prefer it to all that have appeared. Others will think otherwise; and there is a Judge from whose sentence lies no present appeal. I have spared no labour on the work; I have satisfied myself if not Malebouche; and I repeat my motto: poco spero, nulla chiedo. If a concurrence of adverse trifles prevent my being appreciated now, the day will come, haply somewhat late, when men will praise what they now pass by.

Richard Francis Burton

Cairo, May 1, 1880.

Canto II

Instigated by the Demon, the King of Mombasah aimeth at destroying the Navigators: He plotteth treason against them under the fiction of friendship: Venus appeareth to Jupiter, and intercedeth for the Portugueze: He promiseth her to favour them and prophetically relateth some feats which they shall perform in the East: Mercury discloseth himself to the Gama in a dream, and warneth him to shun the dangers of Mombasah: They weigh anchor and reach Melinde, whose King receiveth the Captain with favour and hospitality.

Mombasah’s King untimely end hath laid (1–17)
For famous Gama by his fell deceit:
Descending seawards, Venus saves th’ Armade, (18–32)
and fares on high her sovran Sire to greet, (33–43)
She learns our future lot by Jove’s good aid: (44–55)
appeareth Mercury to Lusus’ fleet, (56–71)
It makes Melindé, where a potent Chief (72–End)
within his harbour lendeth glad relief.

1

’Twas now the period when the Planet bright,
whose race distinguisheth the hours of day,
did at his longed-for, tardy goal alight,
veiling from human eyne his heav’enly ray;
and of his Ocean-home, deep hid from sight,
the God of Night-tide oped the portal-way;
when the false crafty folk came flocking round
the ships, whose anchors scarce had bit the ground.

2

’Mid them a villain, who had undertane
the task of deadly damage, spake aloud:—
“O val’orous Captain, who hast cut the reign
of Neptune, and his salty plain hast plow’d,
the King who governeth this island, fain
to greet thy coming, is so pleased and proud,
he wisheth nothing save to be thy host,
to see thee, and supply what need ye most.

3

“And, as he burneth, with extreme desire,
so famed a pers’onage to behold and greet,
he prays suspicion may no fear inspire;
but cross the bar-line, thou and all thy Fleet;
And, sith by voyage long men greatly tire,
thy gallant crew by travel-toil is beat,
he bids thee welcome to refit on land
as, cèrtes, Nature must such rest command.

4

“And if thou wendest seeking merchandise
got in the golden womb of the Levant,
Cinnamon, cloves, and biting spiceries,
health-dealing drug, or rare and excellent plant;
or, if thou lust for sparkling stones of price,
the Ruby fine, the rigid Diamant,
hence shall thou bear such full, abundant store,
that e’en thy Fancy shall affect no more.”

5

Unto the Herald straight our Chief replieth,
grateful acknowledging the Royal hest;
and saith, that seeing Sol now seawards hieth
he may not enter as becomes a guest:
But, when returning light shall show where lieth
the way sans danger, with a fearless breast,
the Royal orders he will list fulfil,
a Lord so gracious hath claim higher still.

6

He questions further, an the land contain
christenèd Peoples, as the Pilot sware:
The cunning Herald who ne’er speaks in vain
voucheth that Christian men dwell mostly there.
Thus doth he banish from our Captain’s brain
the cautious fantasies of doubt and fear:
Wherefore the Gama straightways ’gan to place
Faith in that faithless unbeliever-race.[23]

7

And, as condemnèd felons he had brought,
convìct of mortal crime and shameful deed,
who might in sim’ilar cases danger-fraught
be ventured where the common weal had need;
a twain of wily, well-tried wits he sought,
bade them the Moorman’s craft and trick’eries heed,
go spy the City’s power, and seek to see
whether desirèd Christians there may be.

8

Fair gifts he gave them for the Royal hand,
to quit the goodly will the greeting show’d,
by him held sure and firm and clear and bland,
whereas ’twas cleanly of a cont’rary mode.
Now all the rout perfidious and nefand,
quitting the Squadron o’er the waters row’d:
With gladsome, joyous gestures, all deceit,
The pair of shipmates on the shore they greet.

9

And when in presence of the King convey’d,
the gifts they gave, and message did present,
far less they witness’d, as ’bout town they stray’d,
than what they wanted on their work intent;
the shrewd sagacious Moors pretences made
to veil from sight what they to see were sent;
for where reigns Malice there we ever find
the fear of Malice in a neighbour’s mind.

10

But He,[24] for ever fair, for ever young
in form and feature, born of mothers twain
by wondrous birth-rite; and whose wilful tongue
would work the Navigators’ ban and bane—
dwelt in a house the City-folk among,
of form and vestment human; who did feign
to be a Christian priest, and here had raisèd
a sumptuous altar where he prayed and praisèd.

11

There had he limnèd, figuring aright
the Holy Ghost’s high heavenly portraiture;
hover’d a Dove, in snowy plume bedight,
o’er the sole Phoenix, Mary, Virgin pure:
The Saintly Company was shown to sight,
the Dozen, in that sore discomfiture,
as when, taught only by the Tongues that burnt
with lambent fire, man’s varied tongues they learnt.

12

Thither conducted either Comrade went,
where hateful Bacchus stood in lies array’d;
and rose their spirits, while their knees were bent
before the God who sways the worlds He made.
The perfumed incense by Panchaia sent,
fuming its richest scent, o’ th’ altar laid
Thyóne’s Son; and now they view, forsooth,
the god of Lies adore the God of Truth.

13

Here was receiv’ed, for kindly rest at night,
with ev’ery mode of good and trusty greeting,
the twain of Christians, who misween’d the rite,
th’ unholy show of holy counterfeiting.
But soon as Sol returning rained his light
on sombre Earth, and in one instant fleeting
forth from the ruddy-dyed horizon came
the Spouse Tithonian with her front aflame:

14

Return the Moormen bearing from the land
the Royal licence, with the Christian pair,
that disembarkèd by our Chief’s command,
for whom the King feign’ed honest friendship fair:
The Portingall, assured no plot was plan’d,
and seeing scanty fear of scathe or snare
when Christian peoples in the place abode,
to stem the salty river straightway stood.

15

Advisèd him the scouts dispatcht ashore
that holy clerk and altars met their sight;
and how receivèd them the friendly Moor
while Night’s cloud-shadowèd mantle cloaked the light;
Nay, that both Lord and Liege no feeling bore,
save what in kindness took a dear delight,
for, certès, nothing told of doubt or fear,
where proofs of friendship showèd sure and clear.

16

Whereon the noble Gama hied to greet
gladly the Moors that up the bulwarks plied;
for lightly trusteth sprite without deceit;
and gallant souls in goodly show confide.
The crafty people on the Flagship meet,
mooring their light canoes along her side:
Merrily trooped they all, because they wot
the wisht-for prizes have become their lot.

17

The cautious war-men gather on the land
arms and ’munitions; that whene’er th’ Armade
ride at her anchors near the riv’erine strand
the work of boarding may be readier made:
With deepest treachery the traitors plan’d
for those of Lusus such an ambuscade,
that reckless of the coming doom they pay
the blood-debt dating from Mozámbic Bay.

18

Weighed are the biting anchors, rising slow,
while ’customed capstan-songs and shouts resound;
only the foresails to the gale they throw
as for the buoyèd bar the Ships are bound:
But Erycína fair, from ev’ry foe
aye glad to guard and guide her Race renown’d,
seen the black ambush big with deadly bane,
flies from the welkin shaft-swift to the Main.

19

She musters Nereus’ maidens fair and blonde,
with all the meiny of the sea-blue race;
the Water-princes her commandment own’d,
for the salt Ocean was her natal place:
Then, told the reason why she sought the lond,
with her whole bevy forth she set apace,
to stay the Squadron ere it reach the bourne
whence ne’er a Traveller may to life return.

20

On, on they hurry, scatt’ring high the spray,
and lash with silvern trains the spumy White:
Doto’s soft bosom breasts the briny way
with hotter pressure than her wonted plight.
Springs Nisé, while Neríne seeks the fray
clearing the crystal wavelets nimble light:
The bending billows open wide a path,
fearing to rouse the hurrying Nereids’ wrath.

21

Borne on a Triton’s shoulders rides in state
with fiery gesture, Dionaea fair;
nor feels the bearer that delicious weight,
superb his cargo of such charms to bear:
Now draw they nearer where stiff winds dilate
the bellicose Armada’s sailing gear:
They part, and sudden with their troops surround
the lighter vessels in the vayward bound.

22

Girt by her nymphs the Goddess lays her breast
against the Flagship’s prow, and others close
the harbour-entrance; such their sudden gest
the breeze through bellied canvas vainly blows:
With tender bosom to tough timber prest
she drives the sturdy ship that sternward goes:
Her circling Nereids raise and urge afar
the threatened victim from the hostile bar.

23

E’en as to nesty homes the prov’ident Ants,
their heavy portion’d burdens haling slow,
drill their small legions, hostile combatants,
’gainst hostile Winter’s war of frost and snow:
There are their travails given to their wants,
there puny bodies mighty spirits show:
Not otherwise the Nymphs from fatal end
labour the Portughuezes to defend.

24

Their force prevails; astern the Flagship falleth,
’spite all aboard her raising fearful shout;
boiling with rage the Crew each yardarm hauleth
to port and starboard putting helm about:
Apoop the cunning Master vainly bawleth,
seeing that right toforn upon his route,
uprears a sea-girt rock its awful head,
and present shipwreck fills his soul with dread.

25

But as loud call and clamour ’gan uprise
from the rude sailor toiling hard and keen;
the Moors are frighted by th’ unusèd cries,
as though they sighted Battle’s horrid scene.
None know the reason of such hot surprise;
none know in sim’ilar press whereon to lean;
they hold their treach’erous felon tricks are known,
and present tortures must their crime atone.

26

Lo! with a panick fear themselves they flung
in the swift-sailing barklets which they brought:
These high uplifted on the billows hung,
those deep in water diving safety sought:
Sudden from starboard and from port they sprung,
by dread of visionary sights distraught;
for all would rather tempt the cruel tide,
for none in mercies of their foes confide.

27

Of such a fashion in the sylvan Mere
the Frogs, a brood of Lycian blood whilòme,
when fall of coming foot perchance they hear,
while all incautious left their wat’ery home,
wake marish-echoes hopping here and there
to ’scape the perils threat’ening death and doom;
and, all ensconcèd in the well-known deep
nought but their small black heads ’bove water peep:

28

So fly the Moors; the Loadsman who alone
the Ships in deadly imm’inent risk had led,
deeming his hateful plans to all beknown,
plunged in the bitter depths and swimming fled.
But as her course had missed the steadfast stone,
where every hope of darling life were dead,
eftsoons our Amm’irall doth her anchor throw,
and, near her, furling sail, the rest come to.

29

Observant Gama, seen this sudden sight
of Moorish strangeness, and surprised to view
his Pilot flying with accusing flight,
divines the plottings of that bestial crew:
And when ne hindrance showèd, ne the might
of tides that onwards bore, or winds that blew,
yet that his Flagship forged ahead no more,
the Marvel hailing thus he ’gan implore:—

30

“Oh Chance, strange, passing strange, that gave no sign!
Oh wondrous Godsend shown so clear, so plain!
Oh fellest treason baffled inopine!
Oh hostile Paynims, false, perfidious strain!
Who of such desp’erate devilish design
by mortal wisdom could escape the bane,
unless there throned in Heav’en the Sovran Guard
to weak humanity strong aid award?

31

“Right well hath provèd Providence on high,
the scanty safety by these Ports purvey’d:
Right well appearance showeth every eye,
how all our confidence hath been betray’d:
But since Man’s wit and wisdom vainly try
to sound these feints and foils so deeply laid,
O Thou, Almighty Guard! to guard him deign
who sans Thine aid himself would guard in vain!

32

“And if Thy holy ruth so condescend
to save this People peregrine and poor,
who on Thy grace and goodness sole depend,
to force salvation from the false fell Moor;
vouchsafe, O Lord, our weary course shall end
at some fair Harbour, shelter’d and secure;
or show the distant shores we pine to see,
since all this sailing is for serving Thee.”

33

The piteous prayer smote the loving ears
of Dionaea fair; her heart was painèd;
she left her Nymphs, all bathed in yearning tears,
who by her sudden flight perplext remainèd:
Now she had thrid the lum’inous planet-spheres,
now the third Heaven’s gateway she had gainèd;
on, onward still to the sixth sphere, the throne
where high All-Father sits and reigns alone.

34

And, as her way affronting, forth she hied,
her ev’ry gesture such a grace expirèd,
Stars, Skies and Aether’s circumambient tide,
and all that saw her with love-fire were firèd.
Those eyne wherein Dan Cupid aye doth nide,
such vital spirits in all life inspirèd;
the frigid Poles with torrid ardours burnèd,
and spheres of Arctic frost to flame were turnèd.[25]

35

And with more love to move her Sovereign
Sire, who aye lov’d her with a constant will,
herself she shows as to the Trojan swain
she showed of old on Ida’s bosky hill.
If her the Hunter who the form of man
lost, seeing Dian in the glassy rill,
had seen, he ne’er had died by rav’ening hound,
erst slain by a sorer and a surer wound.

36

Wander’d the crispy threads of wavy gold
adown a bosom shaming virgin snow:
Her milk-hued breasts with ev’ry movement roll’d
where Love lay sporting but did nowhere show:
Flames with far-flashing fire the Zone’s white fold
wherewith the Boy gar’d ev’ry heart to glow:
while round those columns’ polisht curves were climbing
Desires, like ivy parent-trunk entwining.

37

A filmy Cendal[26] winds around her waist,
which del’icate sense conceals by modest veiling;
and yet not all conceal’d, nor all confest,
the veil, red-blushing lilies oft revealing:
With warmer fondness still to ’flame his breast
she woos his sight with secret charms assailing:
Now all Olympus shakes with jealous jars,
rage burneth Vulcan, Love inflameth Mars.

38

The while her angel-semblance showeth blended
with smiles a sadness in the sweetest way;
like some fair Ladye by rude swain offended
incautious rough while playing am’orous play;
who laughs and laughing pouts with wrath pretended
passing withouten pause from grave to gay;
thus she, the Goddess who no rival heedeth,
softer than sad before her Father pleadeth.

39

“Aye had I deemèd, mighty Father mine,
in whatsoe’er my loving breast preferrèd,
to find thee kind and affable and benign,
e’en though of hostile heart the hate were stirrèd:
But as I see thine ire to me incline,
ire undeserv’ed—to thee I ne’er have errèd—
let Bacchus triumph with his wicked will;
while in his weal I sit and wail mine ill.

40

“This Folk, these Sons of me, for whom I pour
the tear that trickleth bootless ’fore thy sight,
whose woe, since wish’d them well, I work the more
when my good wishes but thy wrath excite:
For them I weep, for them thine aid implore,
and thus, in fine, with adverse fate I fight:
But now, because my love ill-fortune bears,
I will to will them ill and weal be theirs.

41

“Yet thus to perish by that wild-beast race,
for I have been”[27] * * * Whereon, all lovely flows
the burning tear-drop beading down her face,
as pearled with rory dew fresh shines the Rose:
Silent awhile, as though her plea for grace
the portals of her teeth list not disclose
she had pursued; but ere a word she said
the potent Thund’erer further plaint forbade:

42

And, moved to pity by such gentle powers,
pow’ers made to move the heart of Tyger dure,
with beaming smile, as when the sky that lowers
waxeth serene, and clears the lift obscure;
he dries his Daughter’s welling tears, and showers
warm kisses on her cheeks and neck snow-pure;
in mode that had the place been lere and lone
a pair of Cupids had Olympus known.

43

And, face approaching to the face he prizèd,
whereat the sobbing tears the faster flow;
e’en as some yeanling by the nurse chastisèd
weepeth caresst with louder feint of woe:
To soothe her troubled bosom he devisèd
the future fortunes of her sons to show,
unripping thus from Fate’s impregnate womb
He opes the mysteries of the things to come:—

44

“Thou fairest Daughter mine! throw far thy fear
lest to thy Lusians happen harm indign;
nor deem my spirit holdeth aught so dear,
as the sad waters of these sov’reign eyne:
Thou shalt behold, my Daughter, hear me swear,
the Greek and Roman dimm’d of all his shine,
by Gestes illustrious this thy Hero-race
Shall dare and do in Eastern dwelling-place.

45

“If glib Ulysses e’er to flee was fated
a life-long slav’ery on Ogygia-shore;
and if Antenor’s fortune penetrated
Illyric bays, Timavus’ fount t’ explore;
e’en if thy pious Aeneas navigated
where seas round Scylla and Charybdis roar;
thy nobler scions higher grade shall win,
shall add new worlds to worlds of older men.

46

“Valvartes and cities and the tow’ering wall
built by their valour, Daughter, thou shalt see:
Shalt see the Turk, deem’ed bravest brave of all,
from their dread prowess forcèd aye to flee:
Shalt see of Inde the free-born monarchs fall
and own their mightier King’s supremacy:
And when, in fine, they wield the full command
shall dawn a Higher Law[28] for every land.

47

“Him shalt thou see, who now in hurrièd flight
fares distant Indus through such fears to find,
make vasty Neptune tremble with affright,
and crisp his wavy waste sans breath of wind.
Oh Chance ne’er seen! Oh wonder-teeming Sight!
this Quake of Water with plat calm combin’d!
Oh valiant race, with loftiest thought inbred,
whom Earth’s four El’ements must regard with dread![29]

48

“This Land, that water hath to them denied,
shalt see affording surest Hythe, where spent
by their long voyaging, shall rest and ride
Argosies bound from utmost Occident.
In fine, this seaboard all, that futile tried
death-snare to weave, shall pay obedient
toll, tithe, and tribute, knowing vain it were
to beard the Lusian Lyon in his lair.

49

“Shalt see King Erythras’ far-famèd Main
permute his nat’ural red to Fear’s pale dye:
eke shalt thou see the haughty Hormuz-reign
twice taken, prostrate in their presence lie:
There shalt thou see the furious Moorman slain
pierced by his own deflected archery;[30]
till all ken clearly who thy Sons oppose
by their own deed become their deadliest foes.

50

“Shalt see of Diu[31] th’ inexpugnable wall,
two sieges braving, while thy sons defend;
there shall their val’orous worth be shown to all
with feats of arms that every feat transcend:
Envy shalt see in Mars majestical
of Lusian fierceness none shall dare offend:
There shall they sight the Moor with voice supreme
before high Heaven false Mahound blaspheme.

51

“Thou shalt see Góa from the Muslim tane,
and in near future raised to queenly place,
Ladye of Orient land sublimely vain
of triumphs wrested by thy conqu’ering Race.
There, with superb, high, haughtiest disdain
the Gentoo louting low to idols base,
they bit and bridle, mastering every land
that ’gainst thy Lusians raiseth head or hand.

52

“Thou shalt behold the Fortalice hold out
of Cananor with scanty garnison:
Calecut thou shalt see endure sad rout,
that erst so populous and puissant town;
shalt in Cochin[32] see one approv’d so stout,
who such an arr’ogance of the sword hath shown,
no harp of mortal sang a similar story,
digne of e’erlasting name, eternal glory.

53

“Ne’er with such Mars-taught art and furious flame,
was Leucas seen in civil wars to glow,
when to his Actium-fight Augustus came
and laid th’ injurious Roman captain low;
whom, deft Aurora’s reign and race to tame,
far-famèd Nyle and Bactrus’ Scythic foe,
despoilèd, ’spite victorious spoils and rare,
that fair Egyptian not so chaste as fair;[33]

54

“As thou shalt see when Ocean boileth o’er
with fires enkindled by thy Lusians’ bate,
who captive make the Idol-man and Moor,
and triumph high o’er many a subject state:
Till, won rich Aurea-Chersonésus’-shore
far as far China they shall navigate,
and each remotest isle of Orient tide
and every Ocean in their rule shall bide.

55

“Tis thus, O Daughter mine! thy children’s lot
higher than human vigour to display,
nowhere shall Brav’ery burn and blaze so hot
from Ganges’ bank to Gaditanian bay;
nor from the Boreal billows to the gut
where first an injured Lusian brake the way;[34]
e’en though their progress o’er the world t’ oppose
the Dead of Ages from their tombs arose.”

56

This said, he sendeth Maia’s son divine
to visit lowly earth, and there to seek
some harbour’s peaceful shelter, with design
that all the Fleet shall ride sans risk of wreck:
And, lest in false Mombasah-land indign
more of delay the valiant Captain make,
’tis Jove’s command that be in vision shone
a restful region free from restless fone.

57

Now th’ airy space the Cyllenéan span’d,
descending earth with feath’ery feet to tread;
his hand was armèd with the fatal Wand,
which sheds on weary eyne sweet drowsihed;
wherewith he called the sad-eyed shadowy band
from Hades, and obedient breezes sped:
The wingèd basnet on his head he bore;
and thus he sought the Melindanian shore.

58

Fame is his mate who mote aloud proclaim
the Lusitanian’s weight and rarest worth;
for mortal breast is won by noble name,
that makes the bearer loved of all on earth.
Thus winning stranger-hearts the Herald came,
and to the mighty bruit gave timely birth:
Anon Desire Melindé burns to see
what mode of men the val’orous People be.

59

Thence to Mombasah takes the God his course,
where the strange vessels rode in fear afar,
to bid the seamen leave, while none the worse,
those lands suspected and that treacherous bar:
For scant availeth human fraud or force
against Infernals waging treach’erous war:
Scant ’vaileth heart and art and judgment staid
when human wisdom lacketh heavenly aid.

60

Already Night had past her middle way,
and all the starry host with th’ alien light
rained on the breadth of Earth their radiance gay;
and now was Sleep tired man’s supreme delight.
Th’ illustrious Captain weary, wayworn, lay,
with careful watching through the cares of night,
a short repose for anxious eyne he snatchèd:
The men on duty at their quarters watchèd.

61

When in a vision Maia’s son was seen
and heard to say: “Fly, Lusitanian! fly
that wicked Monarch’s snares, that only mean
to draw you forwards where ye surely die:
Fly, for breathes fair the breeze and smiles serene
Aether, while stormless sleep the seas and sky;
in other part another King more benign
sure shelter offereth unto thee and thine!

62

“Here nought thou findest but the barb’rous rite
the guest-rite dear to cruel Diomed,
ill-host that made each miserable wight
the wonted forage of his stabled steed:
Those altars which Busiris, infame sprite,
taught with the stranger’s wailing life to bleed,
here certès wait thee an thou longer dwell:
Fly, then, this folk perfidious, fierce, and fell!

63

“Steer straight, along this outstretch’d sea-board run,
another land more leal shalt thou find;
there near the Belt where th’ ever-blazing sun
to Day and Night hath equal space assign’d:[35]
There to thy Squadron honour gladly done,
a King, with many a friendly service kind,
the surest shelter shall for thee provide,
and for your India skilful trusty guide.”

64

Mercury thus; and rousèd from his dreams
the Captain rising in a stark dismay,
while pierced the palpable Obscure bright streams
of sudden light and splendid holy ray:
Then, seen forthwith that him it best beseems
in land so vile to make the shortest stay,
he bade his Master, urged by spirit new,
to spread the canvas in what breeze there blew.

65

“Hoist sail!” he said, “hoist high in lib’ral air,
for God commands, and Heav’n affects its friends;
from yon clear seats was sent a messengèr
only to speed our steps and shape our ends.”
Meanwhile the sailors to set sail prepare;
all work and either watch its anchor tends;
the weighty irons with willing shouts are weighèd,
and sin’ewy strength, the seaman’s pride, displayèd.

66

Now at what time their anchors high uprose,
lurking in Night’s murk shadow rose the Moor,
stealthy to cut the cables of his foes,
that all might perish on the rocky shore:
But watched with lynx-like glances, clear and close,
the Portingalls prepared for ev’ry stowre:
Finding his victims wakeful th’ enemy fled
by wings of terror, not by paddle, sped.

67

But now the narrow sharp-cut Prores renew,
cleaving the humid argent plain, their road;
blandly the north and eastern Trade-wind blew
with gentle movement, as in joyous mood:
Past perils in their talk review’d the Crew,
for with a fond delay Thought loves to brood
on dang’rous chances, when to death-in-life
Life comes so near she scarcely ’scapes the strife.

68

One circle ended Phoebus all aglow,
and on a second entered, when appearèd
in the far offing, sailing sure and slow,
two hulls by gently-breathing Zephyrs steerèd:
And, as they must be manned by Moorish foe
our Squadron veering soon her prizes nearèd:
This one that fearèd fearful ills to brave
ran straight ashore her crew thereon to save.

69

No sim’lar cunning from such chances led
her consort, captive of the Lusian hand,
which, ne by rig’rous Mavors’ rage had bled,
nor felt what furies Vulcan doth command.
But weakly, master’d by a craven dread,
the feeble forces which the barquelet man’d
resistance offer’d none; which haply shown,
from such resisting greater ills had known.

70

And as the Gama felt him much incline’d
to seek a Guide for India-land long sought,
he thought a Helmsman ’mid the Moors to find,
yet naught to him succeeded as he thought;
none mote give tidings of the lay of Inde,
under what tract of heav’n it might be brought:
But all declare a harbour lies hard by
Melinde, ready Pilots to supply.

71

Her King’s benevolence the Moormen praise,
conditions lib’ral, breast no guile that knew;
magnificent, grandiose and gentle ways
with parts that won respect and honour true.
All this to heart for fact our Captain lays,
since to his vision came such view to shew
the dream-sent Cyllenéan; thus he sped
whither the vision and the Moorman led.

72

’Twas the glad season when the God of Day
into Europa’s rav’isher ’gan return;
when warmèd either point his genial ray
and Flora scatter’d Amalthéa’s horn:
The hasty Sun, that girds the heavenly way,
brought round the mem’ry of that blessèd morn,
when He, who ruleth all by Will Divine,
upon Creation stampt His seal and sign:[36]

73

At such a time the Squadron neared the part,
where first Melindé’s goodly shore was seen,
in awnings drest and prankt with gallant art,
to show that none the Holy Day misween:
Flutter the flags, the streaming Estandart
gleams from afar with gorgeous purple sheen;
tom-toms and timbrels mingle martial jar:
Thus past they forwards with the pomp of war.

74

Men crowd and jostle on Melindé’s strand
hasting to sight the stranger’s glad Armade;
a folk more truthful far, humane, and bland
than any met on shores their course had made.
Now rides the Lusian Fleet anent the land:
Her pond’rous anchors now the depths invade:
Forthwith a captured Moor they send to greet
the King and mani’fest whence had come the Fleet.

75

The King who well that noble lineage knew,
which to the Portingalls such worth imparts,
prizeth their harb’ring at his Hythe, as due
the praise to Braves so prompt in martial arts:
And, with the spirit ever pure and true
that ’nobleth gen’rous souls and gallant hearts,
he prays by proxy all forthwith may deign
to land and use, as best they choose, his reign.

76

Frank offers these, and made in Honour bright,
simple the words, undoubted, unprepar’d,
wherewith the Monarch greets each noble Knight,
who o’er such seas and lands so far hath fared.
And eke he sendeth muttons fleecy white
with many a cramm’d domesticate poulard,
and tropick fruitage which the markets fill:
Yet his good gifts are giv’n with better will.

77

A glad and eager ear our Captain lent
to him who spake his Sovran’s speech benign;
straightway of royal gifts return he sent
stow’d in his Squadron for such fair design:
Purple Escarlat,[37] cloth of crimson tint,
the branchy Coral, highly prized and fine,
which in deep Water soft and tender grown,
in Air doth harden to a precious stone.

78

Eke sends he one well known for courtly wit,
who with the King may pact of peace conclude;
and prayeth pardon that he could not quit
his ships at once, and leave the Fleet aflood.
His trusty Truchman[38] on the land alit,
and, as before the Monarch’s face he stood,
spake thus in style which only Pallas taught
when praise and prayer firm persuasion wrought:—

79

“O King sublime! to whom Olympus pure
of His high justice gave the gift and boon
to curb and conquer peoples dour and dure,
to win their love, nor less their fear to own;
as safe asylum, haven most secure,
to ev’ry Oriental nation known,
thee have we come to seek, in thee to find
the surest med’icine of the Wanderer’s mind.

80

“No Pyrates we, who fare on ports to prey,
and purse-proud cities that in war be weak;
thieves, who with fire and steel the peoples slay,
their robber-greed on neighbour-goods to wreak:
From haughty Europe to the realms of Day
we sail, and Earth’s remotest verge we seek
of Inde, the great, the rich, for thus ordaineth
the mighty Monarch who our country reigneth.

81

“What brood so harsh as this was ever bred?
what barb’arous custom and what usage ban’d
that can not only men from ports forbid
but grudge the shelter of their desert sand?
What of ill Will hold they our hearts have hid,
that of a folk so few in fear they stand?
That traps for us they spread and ready snares
and work their worst whereby we die unwares?

82

“But Thou, wherein full surely we confide
to find, O King benign! an honest man,
and hope such certain aid to see supplied,
as gave Alcino’us the lost Ithacan,
to this thy Haven sure we stem the tide
with the Divine Interpreter in van:
For as He sendeth us to thee ’tis clear
thy heart must e’en be rare, humane, sincere.

83

“And deem not thou, O King! that dreads to land
our famous Captain thee to serve and see,
for aught he sees of base or underhand,
or aught suspects of false and feign’ed in thee:
But know he acteth by the high command—
a law of all obeyed implicitly—
his King’s own hest, forbidding him t’explore,
and from his Squadron land at port or shore.

84

“And, since of subjects King may thus require,
for of the Head should members heed the sway,
thou, kingly officed, never shalt desire
the liege his lord’s command to disobey;
but the high ben’efits, and those gifts still higher
by thee bestow’d, he prom’iseth to repay
with all that done by him or his can be
long as the rolling rivers seek the Sea.”

85

Thus he; when all conjoint their voices raisèd
while each to each his separate thoughts convey’d,
by the high stomach of the Race amazèd,
who through such seas and skies their way had made.
Th’ illustrious King for loyalty bepraisèd
the Portingalls, the while his spirit weigh’d
how high his value, strong his orders are,
whose Royal word is heard in land so far.

86

And, with a smiling mien and pleasèd face,
he hailed the Herald, proff’ering high esteem:—
“All black suspicions from your bosoms chase,
nor let your souls with frigid terror teem;
such be your gallant worth, your works of grace,
the World your deeds shall aye most glorious deem;
and whoso holdeth right to do you wrong
ne truth ne noble thoughts to him belong.

87

“That all you warmen may not instant land
observing ’customèd pre-eminence,
though sorely grievèd by your King’s command,
yet much we prize so much obedience:
Yet, as your orders our desire withstand;
nor we consent to see such excellence
of heart, such loyalty of soul, belied,
that our good wishes sole be gratified.

88

“But, as to-morrow’s Sun on earth shall shine,
all our Flotilla shall make holiday;
to seek your sturdy Fleet is our design
we have so longed to see full many a day:
And if your sea-tost vessels bear the sign
of angry tempests, and their tedious way,
here they shall find in friendly form and guise
pilots, munitions, vittaile and supplies.”

89

He spake; and ’neath the sea-rim sank to rest
Latona’s son, when home the Herald hied,
with the fair message to the Fleet addrest,
in a light canoe that fast outran the tide.
Now joy and gladness fillèd ev’ery breast,
all had the perfect cure at length descried—
Discov’ery of the Land, long wisht-for sight;
and thus they festival’d with glee the night.

90

Aboard is foyson of those artful rays,
whose splendours mock the trem’ulous hairy star:
Now every bombardier his boast displays,
till Ocean’s thunder answers earth and air.
The Cyclops’ art is shown in various ways,
in fire-stuffed shells, and burning bombs of war:
Others with voices which invade the skies,
make brazen notes from blaring trumps arise.

91

Echoes a loud reply the ready shore,
with buzzing fireworks forming giddy gyre;
whirl burning wheels that far in Aether soar;
sulphurous dust deep-hid explodes in fire:
Heav’en-high resounds the multitudinous roar;
the soft blue waters don Flame’s red attire;
nor blazeth land the less: ’Tis thus friends greet
their friends as foemen who in battle meet.

92

Again the restless Spheres revolving sped,
to olden drudg’ry dooming man anew:
Again did Memnon’s Mother radiance shed,
and from the sluggard’s eyne soft sleep withdrew:
The latest shadows slowly melting fled,
on earthly flow’rets weeping frigid dew;
when the Melindan King took boat that he
might view the Squad that swam the Blackmoor sea.

93

Boiling about him, swarming round the Bay,
dense crowds glad gather’d and enjoy’d the sight:
Caftans of finest purple glisten gay;
glance splendid robes with silken tissue dight:
In lieu of warrior lance, and harsegaye[39]
and bow whose burnisht cusps mock Luna’s light;
aloft the revellers bear the palmy bough,
the fittest crown that decks the conqueror’s brow.

94

A spacious stately barge, o’ercanopied
with dainty silks, of divers teinture stainèd
beareth Melinde’s King, accompanied
by lords and captains of the land he reignèd.
Rich clad he cometh with what pomp and pride,
his country customs and his taste ordainèd;
a precious Turbant winds around his head
of cotton wrought with gold and silken thread.

95

Caftan of costly texture Damascene—
the Tyrian colour honour’d there of eld;—
Torque round his collar, shining golden sheen,
whose wealth of work its wealth of ore excel’d:
Glitters and gleams with radiance diamantine
Dag-targe of costly price by girdle held:
And show, in fine, upon his sandal-shoon
velvets with seed-pearl and gold-spangle strewn.

96

With silken sunshade, high and round of guise
fast to its handle bound, a gilded spear,
a Minister the solar ray defies
lest hurt of baleful beam the high King bear:
High in the poop his strange glad music hies,
of asp’erous noise, most horr’ible to the ear,
of archèd trumpets writhed in curious round,
roaring a rough, rude, unconcerted sound.

97

Nor with less garnishment our Lusitanian
swift-sailing galleys from the Squadron bore,
to meet and greet the noble Melindanian,
begirt by goodly company galore.
The Gamma cometh dight in dress Hispanian;
but of French work the doublet was he wore,
Satin which Adrian Venice works and stains
crimson, a colour which such prize obtains.

98

Buttons of gold his loopèd sleeves confine,
where solar glancings dazzle gazing eyes:
Hosen of soldier fashion purfled shine
with the rich metal Fortune oft denies:
Points of the same the slashes deftly join,
gored in his doublet, with right del’icate ties:
Gold-hilted sword in mode of Italy:
Plume in his bonnet worn a little wry.

99

I’ the suite and escort of the Captain show’d
of the dye murex—Tyre’s surpassing tint—
the various shades that joy’d men’s eyne, and mode
of dress devis’d with fashion different:
Such was th’ enamel, and as bright it glow’d
with cunning colours in quaint mixture blent,
as though her rutilant bow had rear’d in air
the Maid of Thaumas, fairest of the fair.

100

Sonorous trumpets manly breasts incite
gladding the heart with martial music gay:
Churnèd the Moorish keels blue waters white
and awnings sprent with dews of pearly spray:
The horrid-sounding bombards thunder fright
while smoky hangings veil the splendid day;
roar the hot volleys hurtling sounds so loud,
fain close with hands their ears the Moorish crowd.

101

And now the King our Captain’s galley sought,
who strainèd in his arms the welcome guest:
He with the courtesy which Reason taught,
his host (who was of Royal rank) addrest.
Noted th’ admiring Moor, with marvel fraught,
his visitor’s ev’ery mode, and look, and gest,
as one regarding with a huge esteem
Folk who so far in quest of India came.

102

And to him proffers in his phrase high-flown
whatever goods his realm and haven boast;
the while commanding him to hold his own
what store might haply serve his turn the most:
Eke he assures him Fame had made well-known
the Lusian name ere Lusians reached his coast:
for long ’twas rumour’d that in realms afar
it had with peoples of his law waged war.

103

How Africk cont’inent’s farthest shores resound,
he told him, with great deeds the warmen did;
whose long campaigns the Conquerors had crown’d
lords of the lands where dwelt the Hesperid.[40]
With long harangue he taught the crowd around
the least deserts the Lusians meritèd,
and yet the most that Fame was fain to teach;
when thus Da Gama to the King made speech:—

104

“O thou! who sole hast seen with pit’iful eye,
benignant King! our Lusitanian race,
which in such mis’ery dire hath dared defy
Fate, and the furies of mad seas to face;
may yon Divine eternity on high,
that ruleth man, revolving skyey space,
since gifts so goodly givest thou, I pray
the Heav’ens repay thee what we never may.

105

“Of all Apollo bronzèd hath thou sole,
peaceful didst greet us from th’ abysmal sea:
In thee from Aeolus’ winds that moan and howl,
we find good, truthful, glad security.
Long as its Stars leads forth the vasty Pole,
long as the Sun shall light the days to be,
where’er I haply live, with fame and glory
shall live thy praises in my People’s story.”

106

He spake, and straight the barges ’gin to row
whither the Moorman would review the Fleet;
rounding the vessels, one by one, they go
that ev’ery not’able thing his glance may meet:
But Vulcan skywards voll’eying horr’ible lowe
with dire artill’ery hastes the guest to greet,
while trumpets loud canorous accents blend;
with shawms the Moorish hosts their answer send.

107

When due attention to the sights had lent
the gen’erous Muslim, fill’ed with thrilling wonder,
and hearing, eke, th’ unwonted instrument
that told its dreadful might in fiery thunder;
he bade the light Batèl wherein he went
at anchor quiet ride the Flagship under,
that with the doughty Gama he might hold
converse of matters erst by Rumour told.

108

The Moor in varied di’alogue took delight,
and now he prayed the vis’itor would expound
each war renowned and famous feat of fight
fought with the races that adore Mahound:
Now of the peoples he would gain a sight
that hold our ultimate Hispanian ground:
Then of the nations who with us confine;
then of the mighty voyage o’er the brine.

109

“But first, O valiant Captain! first relate,”
quoth he, “with all the diligence thou can,
what lands and climes compose your natal state,
and where your home, recount with regular plan;
nor less your ancient lineage long and great
and how your Kingdom’s lofty rule began,
with all your early deeds of derring-do;
e’en now, tho’ know’ng them not, their worth we know.

110

“And, prithee, further say how o’er the Main
long on this voyage through fierce seas you stray’d,
seeing the barb’arous ways of alien strain,
which our rude Africk-land to you display’d:
Begin! for now the team with golden rein
draws near, and drags the new Sun’s car, inlaid
with marquetry, from cold Aurora’s skies:
Sleep wind and water, smooth the wavelet lies.

111

“And as th’ Occasion such a fitness showeth,
so is our wish your wondrous tale to hear;
who dwells among us but by rumour knoweth
the Lusitanian’s labour singular?
Deem not so far from us removèd gloweth
resplendent Sol, that need thy judgment fear
to find Melinde nurse so rude a breed,
which can ne prize ne praise a noble deed.

112

“Vainly the haughty olden Giants vied
by war to win Olympus clear and pure:
Pirith and Theseus mad with ign’orance tried
of Pluto’s realm to burst the dread Obscure;
If in the world such works hath workèd pride,
not less ’tis labour excellent and dure,
bold as it was to brave both Heav’en and Hell,
for man o’er raging Nereus to prevail.

113

“With fire consumèd Dian’s sacred fane—
that master-piece of subtle Ctesiphon—
Heróstratus, who by such deed would gain
of world-wide Fame the high immortal boon;
If greed of foolish praise and glory vain
to actions so perverse may urge men on,
more reason ’tis to crown with endless fame
Deeds that deserve, like Gods, a deathless name.”

Canto III

The talk of Vasco da Gama with the King of Melinde, wherein he describeth Europe, and recounteth the origin of the kingdom of Portugal, its kings (including the King Dom Fernando) and its principal achievements: The notable feat of Egás Moníz: The Queen of Castile, Dona Maria, visiteth Portugal to crave aid for the Battle of the Salado: The loves and luckless fate of Dona Ignéz de Castro: Some events which befell the King Dom Fernando.

Populous Europe passeth in review; | (6–23)
Egás Moníz is praised for famous feat; | (35–41)
What Kings and wars our Lusitania knew; | (24–34)
Afonso sees the Christ on Cross elate; | (42–46)
Agnes de Castro’s breast of snowy hue | (118–135)
With innocent blood empurpleth popular hate:
Fernando’s vile neglect is shown to shame, | (138–143)
And the high pow’ers that youth and beauty claim.

1

Now, my Calliope! to teach incline
what speech great Gama for the King did frame:
Inspire immortal song, grant voice divine
unto this mortal who so loves thy name.
Thus may the God whose gift was Medicine,
to whom thou barest Orpheus, lovely Dame!
never for Daphne, Clytia, Leucothöe
due love deny thee or inconstant grow he.

2

Satisfy, Nymph! desires that in me teem,
to sing the merits of thy Lusians brave;
so worlds shall see and say that Tagus-stream
rolls Aganippe’s liquor. Leave, I crave,
leave flow’ry Pindus-head; e’en now I deem
Apollo bathes me in that sovran wave;
else must I hold it, that thy gentle sprite,
fears thy dear Orpheus fade through me from sight.

3

All stood with open ears in long array
to hear what mighty Gama mote unfold;
when, past in thoughtful mood a brief delay,
began he thus with brow high-raised and bold:—
“Thou biddest me, O King! to say my say
anent our grand genealogy of old:
Thou bidd’st me not relate an alien story;
thou bidd’st me laud my brother Lusians’ glory.

4

“That one praise others’ exploits and renown
is honour’d custom which we all desire;
yet fear I ’tis unfit to praise mine own;
lest praise, like this suspect, no trust inspire;
nor may I hope to make all matters known
for Time however long were short: yet, sire!
as thou commandest all is owed to thee;
maugre my will I speak and brief will be.

5

“Nay, more, what most obligeth me, in fine,
is that no leasing in my tale may dwell;
for of such Feats whatever boast be mine,
when most is told, remaineth much to tell:
But that due order wait on the design,
e’en as desirest thou to learn full well,
the wide-spread Cont’inent first I’ll briefly trace,
then the fierce bloody wars that waged my Race.

6

“Atwixt the Zone, where Cancer holds command—
the lucent Sun’s septentrional mete—
and that whose frigid horrors freeze the land
as burns the middle Belt with fervid heat,
lies haughty Europe: On her goodly strand,
facing Arcturus and the Ponent, beat
the briny billows of Atlantis plain,
while free t’wards Auster flows the Midland-main.

7

“That part where lovely Dawn is born and bred,
neighboureth Asia: But the curvèd river,[41]
from far and frore Rhipaean ranges shed,
to feed Maeotis-lake with waves that shiver,
departs them, and the Sea-strait fierce and dread,
that owned the vict’ory of the Greek deceiver,
where now the seaman sees along the shore
triumphant Troja’s mem’ories and—no more.

8

“There farther still the Boreal Pole below,
Hyperboréan mountain-walls appear,
and the wild hills where Aeolus loves to blow,
while of his winds the names they proudly bear:
Here such cold comfort doth Apollo show,
so weak his light and warmth to shine and cheer,
that snows eternal gleam upon the mountains,
freezeth the sea, and ever freeze the fountains.

9

“Here of the Scythic hordes vast numbers be,
in olden day a mighty warrior band,
who fought for honours of antiquity
with the then owners of the Nylus-land:
But how remote their claims from verity,
(for human judgments oft misunderstand),
let him who seeks what higher lore reveal’d
ask the red clay that clothes Damascus-field.[42]

10

“Now in these wild and wayward parts be told
Cold Lapland’s name, uncultivate Norwày,
Escandinavia’s isle, whose scions bold
boast triumphs Italy shall ne’er gainsay.
Here, while ne frost, ne wintry rigours hold
in hand the waters, seafolk ply the way,
over the arm of rough Sarmatic Main
the Swede, the Brusian,[43] and the shiv’ering Dane.

11

“Between the sea and Tanaïs-stream we count
strange races, Ruthens,[44] Moscows, and Livonians—
Sarmátae all of old—and on the Mount
Hercynian,[45] Marcomanni, now Polonians.
Holding the empire Almayne paramount
dwell Saxons, and Bohemians, and Pannonians;
and other tribes, wherethrough their currents frore
Rhine, Danube, Amasis,[46] and Albis pour.

12

“ ’Twixt distant Ister and the famous Strait,
where hapless Helle left her name and life,
the Thracians wone, a folk of brave estate,
Mars’ well-loved country, chosen home of strife:
There Rhódope and Haemus rue the weight
of cursèd Othman’s rule with horror rife;
Byzance they hold beneath their yoke indign
great injury working to great Constantine!

13

“Hard by their side the Macedonians rest,
whose soil is water’ed by cold Axius’ wave:[47]
Eke ye, of ev’ery choicest realm the best,
Lands of the free, the wise, the good, the brave,
that here did breed and bear the facund breast,
and to the world its wit and wisdom gave,
wherewith thou, noble Greece! hast reach’ed the stars,
no less by arts exalt than arms and wars.

14

“The Dalmats follow; and upon the Bay
where rose Antenor’s walls[48] in while of yore,
superb Venetia builds on wat’ery way,
Adria’s Queen that erst was lowly poor.
Hence seawards runs a land-arm made to sway
forceful the sons of many a stranger shore;
an arm of might, whose Race hath conquer’d time
nor less by spirit than by sword sublime.

15

“Girdeth her shores the kingdom Neptunine,
while Nature’s bulwarks fence her landward side;
her middle width departeth Apennine,
by Mars, her saint and patron, glorified:
But when the Porter rose to rank divine,
she lost her prowess, and her bellic pride:
Humbled she lies with antique puissance spent:
So Man’s humil’ity may his God content!

16

“Gallia can there be seen, whose name hath flown
where Caesar’s triumphs to the world are told;
by Séquana[49] ’tis watered and the Rhone,
by Rhine’s deep current and Garumna[50] cold:
Here rise the ranges from Pyréne known,
the Nymph ensepulchre’d in days of old,
whence, legends say, the conflagrated woods
rolled golden streams, and flowèd silvern floods.

17

“Lo! here her presence showeth noble Spain,
of Europe’s body corporal the head;
o’er whose home-rule, and glorious foreign reign,
the fatal Wheel so many a whirl hath made:
Yet ne’er her Past or force or fraud shall stain,
nor restless Fortune shall her name degrade;
no bonds her bellic offspring bind so tight
but it shall burst them with its force of sprite.

18

“There, facing Tingitania’s shore, she seemeth
to block and bar the Med’iterranean wave,
where the known Strait its name ennobled deemeth
by the last labour of the Theban Brave.
Big with the burden of her tribes she teemeth,
circled by whelming waves that rage and rave;
all noble races of such valiant breast,
that each may justly boast itself the best.

19

“Hers the Tarragonese who, famed in war,
made aye-perturbed Parthenopé obey;
the twain Asturias, and the haught Navarre
twin Christian bulwarks on the Muslim way:
Hers the Gallego canny, and the rare
Castilian, whom his star raised high to sway
Spain as her saviour, and his seign’iory feel
Baetis, Leon, Granáda, and Castile.

20

“See the head-crowning coronet is she,
of general Europe, Lusitania’s reign,
where endeth land and where beginneth sea,
and Phoebus sinks to rest upon the main.
Willed her the Heavens with all-just decree
by wars to mar th’ ignoble Mauritan,
to cast him from herself: nor there consent
he rule in peace the Fiery Continent.

21

“This is my happy land, my home, my pride;
where, if the Heav’ens but grant the pray’er I pray
for glad return and every risk defied,
there may my life-light fail and fade away.
This was the Lusitania, name applied
by Lusus or by Lysa, sons, they say,
of ancient Bacchus, or his boon compeers,
eke the first dwellers of her eldest years.

22

“Here sprang the Shepherd,[51] in whose name we see
forecast of virile might, of virtuous meed;
whose fame no force shall ever hold in fee,
since fame of mighty Rome ne’er did the deed.
This, by light Heaven’s volatile decree,
that ancient Scyther, who devours his seed,
made puissant pow’er in many a part to claim,
assuming regal rank; and thus it came:—

23

“A King there was in Spain, Afonso hight,
who waged such warfare with the Saracen,
that by his ’sanguined arms, and arts, and might,
he spoiled the lands and lives of many men.
When from Hercùlean Calpè winged her flight
his fame to Caucasus Mount and Caspian glen,
many a Knight, who noblesse coveteth,
comes off’ering service to such King and Death.

24

“And with intrinsic love inflamèd more
for the True Faith, than honours popular,
they troopèd gath’ering from each distant shore,
leaving their dear-loved homes and lands afar.
When with high feats of force against the Moor
they proved of sing’ular worth in Holy War,
willèd Afonso that their mighty deeds
commens’urate gifts command and equal meeds.

25

“ ’Mid them Henrique, second son, men say,
of a Hungarian King, well-known and tried,
by sort won Portugal which, in his day,
ne prizèd was ne had fit cause for pride:
His strong affection stronger to display
the Spanish King decreed a princely bride,
his only child, Theresa, to the count;
and with her made him Seigneur Paramount.

26

“This doughty Vassal from that servile horde,
Hagar the handmaid’s seed, great vict’ories won;
reft the broad lands adjacent with his sword
and did whatever Brav’ery bade be done:
Him, for his exploits exc’ellent to reward,
God gave in shortest space a gallant son,
whose arm to ’noble and enfame was fain
the warlike name of Lusitania’s reign.

27

“Once more at home this conqu’ering Henry stood
who sacred Hierosol’yma had relievèd,
his eyes had fed on Jordan’s holy flood,
which the Dear Body of Lord God had lavèd;
when Godfrey[52] left no foe to be subdued,
and all Judaea conquered was and savèd,
many that in his wars had done devoir
to their own lordships took the way once more.

28

“But when this stout and gallant Hun attainèd
Life’s fatal period, age and travail-spent,
he gave, by Death’s necessity constrainèd,
his sprite to Him who had that spirit lent:
A son of tender years alone remainèd,
to whom the Sire bequeath’d his ’bodiment;
with bravest braves the youth was formed to cope,
for from such sire such son the world may hope.

29

“Yet old Report, I know not what its weight,
(for on such antique tale no man relies),[53]
saith that the Mother, tane in tow the state,
a second nuptial bed did not despise:
Her orphan son to disinher’ited fate
she doomed, declaring hers the dignities,
not his, with seigniory o’er all the land,
her spousal dowry by her sire’s command.

30

“Now Prince Afonso (who such style had tane
in pious mem’ory of his Grandsire’s name)
seeing no part and portion in his reign
all pilled and plunder’d by the Spouse and Dame,
by dour and doughty Mars inflamed amain,
privily plots his heritage to claim:
He weighs the causes in his own conceit
till firm Resolve its fit effect shall greet.

31

“Of Guimara’ens the field already flow’d
with floods of civil warfare’s bloody tide,
where she, who little of the Mother show’d,
to her own bowels love and land denied.
Fronting the child in fight the parent stood;
nor saw her depth of sin that soul of pride
against her God, against maternal love:
Her sensual passion rose all pow’er above.

32

“O magical Medea! O Progne dire!
if your own babes in vengeance dared ye kill
for alien crimes, and injuries of the sire,
look ye, Teresa’s deed was darker still.
Foul greed of gain, incontinent desire,
were the main causes of such bitter ill:
Scylla her agèd sire for one did slay,
for both Teresa did her son betray.

33

“Right soon that noble Prince clear vict’ory won
from his harsh Mother and her Fere indign;
in briefest time the land obeyed the son,
though first to fight him did the folk incline.
But reft of reason and by rage undone
he bound the Mother in the biting chain:
Eftsoons avenged her griefs the hand of God:
Such veneration is to parents owe’d.

34

“Lo! the superb Castilian ’gins prepare
his pow’er to ’venge Teresa’s injuries,
against the Lusian land in men so rare,
whereon ne toil ne trouble heavy lies.
Their breasts the cruel battle grandly dare,
aid the good cause angelic Potencies;
unrecking might unequal still they strive,
nay, more, their dreadful foe to flight they drive.[54]

35

“Passeth no tedious time, before the great
Prince a dure Siege in Guimaraens dree’d
by passing pow’er, for to ’mend his state,
came the fell en’emy, full of grief and greed:
But when committed life to direful Fate,
Egas, the faithful guardian, he was free’d,
who had in any other way been lost,
all unpreparèd ’gainst such ’whelming host.

36

“But when the loyal Vassal well hath known
how weak his Monarch’s arm to front such fight,
sans order wending to the Spanish fone,
his Sovran’s homage he doth pledge and plight.
Straight from the horrid siege th’ invader flown
trusteth the word and honour of the Knight,
Egas Moniz: But now the noble breast
of the brave Youth disdaineth strange behest.

37

“Already came the plighted time and tide,
when the Castilian Don stood dight to see,
before his pow’er the Prince bend low his pride,
yielding the promisèd obediency.
Egás who views his knightly word belied,
while still Castile believes him true to be,
sweet life resolveth to the winds to throw,
nor live with foulest taint of faithless vow.

38

“He with his children and his wife departeth
to keep his promise with a faith immense;
unshod and strippèd,[55] while their plight imparteth
far more of pity than of vengeance:
‘If, mighty Monarch! still thy spirit smarteth
to wreak revenge on my rash confidence,’
quoth he, ‘behold! I come with life to save
my pledge, my knightly Honour’s word I gave.’

39

“ ‘I bring, thou seest here, lives innocent,
of wife, of sinless children dight to die;
if breasts of gen’erous mould and excellent
accept such weaklings’ woeful destiny.
Thou se’est these hands, this tongue inconsequent,
hereon alone the fierce exper’iment try
of torments, death, and doom that pass in full
Sinis or e’en Perillus’ brazen bull.’

40

“As shrifted wight the hangman stands before,
in life still draining bitter draught of death,
lays throat on block, and of all hope forlore,
expects the blighting blow with bated breath:
So, in the Prince’s presence angry sore,
Egás stood firm to keep his plighted faith:
When the King, marv’elling at such wondrous truth,
feels anger melt and merge in Royal ruth.

41

“Oh the great Portingall-fidelity
of Vassal self-devote to doom so dread!
What did the Persian more for loyalty
whose gallant hand his face and nostrils shred?
When great Darius mourned so grievously
that he a thousand times deep-sighing said,
far he prefer’d his Zóp’yrus sound again,
than lord of twenty Babylons to reign.

42

“But Prince Afonso now prepared his band
of happy Lusians proud to front the foes,
those haughty Moors that held the glorious land
yon side where clear delicious Tagus flows:
Now on Ourique[56] field was pitched and plan’d
the Royal ’Campment fierce and bellicose,
facing the hostile host of Sarrasin
though there so many, here so few there bin.

43

“Confident, yet would he in nought confide,
save in his God that holds of Heav’en the throne;
so few baptizèd stood their King beside,
there were an hundred Moors for every one:
Judge any sober judgment, and decide
’twas deed of rashness or by brav’ery done
to fall on forces whose exceeding might
a cent’ury showèd to a single Knight.

44

“Order five Moorish Kings the hostile host
of whom Ismár,[57] so called, command doth claim;
all of long Warfare large experience boast,
wherein may mortals win immortal fame:
And gallant dames the Knights they love the most
’company, like that brave and beauteous Dame,
who to beleaguer’d Troy such aidance gave
with woman-troops that drained Thermòdon’s wave.

45

“The coolth serene, and early morning’s pride,
now paled the sparkling stars about the Pole,
when Mary’s Son appearing crucified
in vision, strengthened King Afonso’s soul.
But he, adoring such appearance, cried
fired with a frenzied faith beyond control:
‘To th’ Infidel, O Lord! to th’ Infidel:[58]
Not, Lord, to me who know Thy pow’er so well.’

46

“Such gracious marvel in such manner sent
’flamèd the Lusians’ spirits fierce and high,
towards their nat’ural King, that excellent
Prince, unto whom love-boon none could deny:
Aligned to front the foeman prepotent,
they shouted res’onant slogan to the sky,
and fierce the ’larum rose, ‘Real, real,
for high Afonso, King of Portugal!’

47

“As to the fight by calls defied and cries,
some fierce Molossan on the wooded height,
attacks the rampant Bull, who most relies
on strength of tem’erous horn to force the fight:
Now nips the ear, then at the side he flies
barking, with more of nimbleness than might,
till ripped at last the gullet of his foe
he lays the mighty bulk of monster low:

48

“So the new King, inflamed with zeal devout
for God nor less for faithful Lieges’ sake,
assails by cunning skill the barb’arous rout
with Braves the fronting phalanx eath to break:
Whereat the ban-dogs ‘Allah! Allah!’ shout,
and fly to arms; our raging warriors shake
the lance and bow; resound the trumpet tones;
the music thunders; Echo moans and groans.

49

“E’en as the prairie-fire enkindled on
sun-parchèd steppe (as winn’oweth upper air
sibilant Boreas), by the blasts swift blown
o’er bush and arid brake rains flame and flare:
The shepherd lads and lasses, idly strown
in rest and gentle slumber, waked by blare
of crackling conflagration blazing higher,
hamlet-wards force their flocks to fly the fire:

50

“Th’ astonied Moorman in such startled guise,
snatcheth his weapon hast’ily and sans heed;
yet he awaits the fight, nor ever flies,
nay, spurs his battle-ginnet to its speed.
Meet him as rash and swift his enemies
whose piercing lances gar his bosom bleed:
These fall half-slain, while others flee that can
convoking aidance of their Alcoran.

51

“There may be viewèd ’counters madly rash,
onsets no Serra’s sturdy strength could stand,
while charging here and there the chargers dash—
the gifts of Neptune smiting gravid Land:—
Buffets they deal, and blows that bash and smash,
burneth and blazeth Warfare’s blasting brand,
but he of Lusus coat, mail, plate of steel,
hacks, hews, breaks, batters, rives and rends piecemeal.

52

“Men’s heads like bullets dance the bloody plain,
ownerless arms and legs insens’ible lie,
and quiv’ering entrails tell of mortal pain,
and faces fade and life’s fair colours fly.
Lost is that impious host, whose heapèd slain
roll o’er the green’ery rills of crimson dye;
whereby the grasses lose their white and green
and nought but glow of crimson gore is seen.

53

“But now the Lusian victor held the field
his trophies gath’ering, and his gorgeous prey:
The crusht Hispanian Moor was forced to yield
while on the plain three days the great King lay.[59]
And now he chargeth on his virgin shield,
what still assures this well-won Vict’ory.
five noble inescutcheons azure-hued,
signing the Moorish Five his sword subdued.

54

“He paints with bezants five each ’scutcheon,
the thirty silvers wherewith God was sold,
and various tinctures make His mem’ory known,
whose grace and favour did his cause uphold.
Painted on every cinque a cinque is shown;
and, that the thirty may be fully told,
counteth for two the one that central lies
of the five azures painted crossy-wise.

55

“Some time has passèd, since this gain had past
of goodly battail, when the high King hies
to take Leiría, lately tane and last
conquest that boast our conquer’d enemies.
Herewith Arronches castled strong and fast
is jointly gainèd with the noble prize
Scalabicastro,[60] whose fair fields amene
thou, crystal Tagus! bathest all serene.

56

“Unto this conquered roll of towns his might
eke addeth Mafra won in shortest space,
and in the Mountains which the Moon hath hight
he clasps frore Cintra to his hard embrace;
Cintra, whose Naiads love to hide their light
by hidden founts and fly the honey’d lace,
which Love hath woven ’mid the hills where flow
the waters flaming with a living lowe.

57

“And thou, O noble Lisbon! thou encrown’d
Princess elect of Cities capital,
rear’d by the facund Rover-King renown’d,
whose wiles laid low Dardania’s burning wall:
Thou, whose commands oblige the Sea’s Profound,
wast taught to bear the Lusitanian’s thrall,
aided by potent navies at what time
they came crusading from the Boreal clime.[61]

58

“Beyond Germanic Albis and the Rhene,
and from Britannia’s misty margin sent,
to waste and slay the people Sarracene,
many had sailed on holy thoughts intent.
Now gained the Tagus-mouth, our stream amene
to great Afonso’s royal camp they went,
whose lofty fame did thence the Heav’ens invade
and siege to Ulysséa’s walls they laid.

59

“Five sequent times her front had Luna veilèd,
five times her lovely face in full had shown,
when oped her gate the City, which availèd
no Force ’gainst ’sieging forces round her thrown.
Right bloody was th’ assault and fierce th’ assailèd,
e’en as their stubborn purpose bound them down;
asp’erous the Victor, ready all to dare,
the Vanquisht, victims of a dire despair.

60

“Thus won she yielded and, in fine, she lay
prostrate that City which, in days of old,
the mighty meiny never would obey
of frigid Scythia’s hordes immanely bold:
Who could so far extend their savage sway,
till Ebro saw ’t, and Tagus trembling roll’d;
and some o’er Baetis-land, in short, so swept
that was the region Vandalía ’clept.

61

“What might of city could perchance endure
prowess which proud Lisbóa might not bear?
Who mote resist the powers dure and dour
of men, whose Fame from earth invadeth air?
Now yield obedience all Estremadure,
Obidos, Torres Vedras, Alemquer,
where softly plash the music-murmuring waves,
’mid rocks and reefs whose feet the torrent laves.

62

“Eke ye, Transtagan lands! ye justly vain
of flavous Ceres’ bien and bonny boon,
yielded to might above the might of men
the walls and castles by his valour won:
Thou, too, Moor-yeoman! hopest hope insane,
those riant regions long as lord to own;
for Elvas, Moura, Serpa, well-known sites,
with Alcacer-do-Sal must yield their rights.

63

“The noble City and sure seat behold,
held by Sertorius, rebel famed whilòme;
where now the nitid silv’ery waters cold,
brought from afar to bless the land and home,
o’erflow the royal arches hundredfold,
whose noble sequence streaks the dark-blue dome;
not less succumb’d she to her bold pursuer,
to Giraldó, entitled ‘Knight Sans Peur.’[62]

64

“Fast towards Beja city, vengeful prest,
to slake his wrath for spoilt Trancoso’s wrong,[63]
Afonso, who despiseth gentle rest
and would brief human life by Fame prolong.
Feebly resisteth him and his behest
the City, falling to his arms ere long,
and nought of life within her walls but feel
the raging victor’s edge of merciless steel.

65

“With these Palmella yielded to the war,
piscous Cezimbra, eke, her finny spoils;
then, aided onwards by his fortunate star,
the King a pow’erful force of foemen foils:
Felt it the City, saw ’t her Lord afar,
who to support and aid her spares no toils,
along the hill-skirt marching all unware
of rash encounter lackt he heed and care.

66

“The King of Bad’ajoz was a Muslim bold,
with horse four thousand, fierce and furious Knights,
and countless Peons, armed and dight with gold,
whose polisht surface glanceth lustrous light.
But as a savage Bull on lonely wold,
whom jealous rage in hot May-month incites,
sighting a stranger, mad with love and wrath
the brute blind lover chargeth down the path:

67

“So doth Afonso, sudden seen the foes
that urge their forward march securely brave,
strike, slay, and scatter, raining doughty blows;
flies the Moor King, who recks but self to save:
Naught save a panick fear his spirit knows;
his foll’owers eke to follow only crave;
while ours, who struck a stroke so sore, so fell,
were sixty horsemen told in fullest tale.

68

“Victory swift pursuing, rest disdaineth
the great untiring King; he must’ereth all
the lieges of his land, whom nought restraineth
from ever seeking stranger realms to ’thrall.
He wends to ’leaguer Bad’ajoz, where he gaineth
his soul’s desire, and battleth at her fall
with force so fierce, and art and heart so true
his deeds made others fain to dare and do.

69

“But the high Godhead, who when man offends,
so long deservèd penalties delays,
waiting at times to see him make amends,
or for deep myst’ery hid from man’s dull gaze;
if He our valiant King till now defends
from dangers, facèd fast as foes can raise;
lends aid no longer, when for vengeance cries
the Mother’s curses who in prison lies;

70

“For in the City which he compast round,
encompast by the Leoneze was he,
because his conquests trespasst on their ground,
which of Leon and not of Port’ugale be.
Here was his stubborn will right costly found,
as happeth oft in human history,
an iron maims his legs, as rage-inflamèd
to fight he flies and falls a captive maimèd.

71

“O famous Pompey! feel thy Wraith no pain
to see the fate of noble feats like thine;
nor mourn if all-just Nemesis ordain
thy bays be torn by sire-in-law indign;
though Phasis frore and parcht Syéné-plain
whose perpendic’ular shadows ne’er decline,
Bootes’ ice-bergs, and Equator-fires,
confess the terrors which thy name inspires;

72

“Tho’ rich Arabia, and the brood ferocious
Heniochs, with Colchis-region known of yore
for Golden Fleece; and though the Cappadoces
and Júdeans who One only God adore;
tho’ soft Sophénes,[64] and the race atrocious,
Cilician, with Armenia whence outpour
the twain of mighty streams, whose farthest fount
hides in a higher and a holier Mount;[65]

73

“And though, in fine, from far Atlantic tide
E’en to the Taurus, Scythia’s tow’ering wall,
all saw thee conquer; fearless still abide
if none save Emath-field beheld thee fall:
Thou shalt behold Afonso’s ovant pride,
lie subjugate, that subjugated all.
Such fate Celestial Counsel long foresaw
thine from a sire, his from a son-in-law.

74

“Returned the King sublime, in fine, with sprite
by the just doom of Judge divine chastisèd,
and when of Santarem in pride of might
the Saracen a bootless siege devisèd;
and when of Vincent, martyr benedight,
the precious Corse by Christian people prizèd,
from Sacrum Promontorium[66] was conveyed
and reverent-wise in Ulysséa laid:

75

“Faster to push the projects still in hand,
the toil-spent Father sent his stout young son,
bidding him pass to Alemtejo’s land,
with warlike gear and soldiers many a one.
Sancho, a sov’ereign wielder of the brand,
straight forward passing, gore-red gars to run
the stream[67] whose waters feed Seville and flood,
dyed by the brutish Moormen’s barb’rous blood.

76

“With hunger whetted by this new success,
now resteth not the Youth till sight his eyes
another slaughter, sore as this, oppress
the barb’rous host that circling Beja lies:
Not long the Prince whom fortune loves to bless,
waits the fair end where leads his dear emprize.
But now the routed Moors to vengeance cleave,
their only hope such losses to retrieve.

77

“They crowd the mighty Mount whereof Meduse
robbèd his body who the skies upbore:
They flock in thousands from Cape Ampeluse
and from Tangier, Antaeus’ seat of yore.
Abyla’s[68] dweller offereth scant excuse;
who with his weapon hasteth him the more,
when heard the Moorish clarions shrilly-tonèd,
and all the reign high Juba whilom ownèd.

78

“The Mir-almuminin,[69] who led the throng,
from the Dark Cont’inent past to Portugal:
Thirteen Moor kings he led, high, haught, and strong,
to his Imperial sceptre subject all:
Thus wreaking forceful every tyrant Wrong,
wherever easy Wrong mote sate his gall,
Sancho in Santarem he flies t’ invest,
yet his was hardly of success the best.

79

“Gives asp’erous battle, fighting fury-fraught
the hateful Moor a thousand feints designing;
ne horrid catapult avails him aught,
ne forceful batt’ering-ram, ne hidden mining:
Afonso’s son, conserving force and thought,
and firm resolve with warlike skill combining,
foreseeth all with prudent heart and art,
and stern resistance brings to every part.

80

“But now the Vet’ran—doomed by years to ease
and gentle rest, from life of toil and teen,
be’ing in the city,[70] down whose pastured leas
Mondego’s wavelets kiss the hem of green;—
when learnt how close his son beleaguer’d is
in Santarem by Moormen blind with spleen,
close from the City flies the fone to meet,
age-idlesse spurning with fast eager feet.

81

“He heads his army, tried in war and known,
his son to succour; and his well-led host
shows wonted Port’ingall-fury all their own,
till in brief time the Moor is broke and lost.
The Battle-plain—whose blood-stained front is strown
with steely coats, and caps of varied cost,
horse, charger, harness, rich and worthy prize—
heaped with their owners’ mangled corpses lies.

82

“Forth fares the remnant of the Paynimry
from Lusitania, hurled in headlong flight:
But Mir-almuminin may never flee,
for ere he flee his life hath fled the light.
To Him whose arm vouchsafed such Victory
in praise and stintless prayer our hosts unite:
Chances so passing strange make clear to ken
God’s arm smites sorer than all arms of men.

83

“Such crown of conquest still bedeckt the brow
of old Afonso, Lord of lofty fame;
when he, in fine, who ever foiled his foe,
was foiled by ancient Time’s unyielding claim:
Past the death-sickness o’er his pallid brow
its frigid hand, and wrung his feeble frame;
and thus the debt on mortal shoulders laid
his years to gloomy Libitína paid.

84

“His loss the lofty Promontories mourn,
and from the wavy rivers floods of grief
with lakelets overspread the fieldèd corn,
and trickling tears are sorrow’s sole relief:
But ring so loud o’er Earth’s extremest bourne
the fame and exploits of our great lost chief,
that evermore shall Echo for his reign
‘Afonso! Afonso!’ cry, and cry in vain.

85

“Sancho, his lusty son, the worthy heir
of his great Father’s valour, force and might,
as did his early doings clear declare,
when Baetis[71] fled ensanguin’d from the fight,
and from Andalusía forced to fare
the barb’arous King and peoples Ishmaelite;
and more, when they who vainly Beja girt
of his shrewd blows themselves had borne the hurt:

86

“After he had been raised to Royal hest,
and held for years a few his father’s land,
he wends the city Sylves to invest,
plowèd whose plain the barb’arous peasant’s hand:
With allies val’orous was his daring blest
the sturdy Germans, whose Armada man’d
by furnisht host was flying o’er the wave,
the lost Judaea to regain and save.

87

“To join in holy enterprise they went
Red Frederick, who did first to move begin
his mighty armament and succour sent
to ward the town where Christ had died for men;
When Guy, whose Croisers were by thirst bespent,
yielded his sword to gallant Saladin
there, where the Muslim host was well supplied
with wat’ery store to those of Guy denied.[72]

88

“But that majestical Armade that came
by dint of storm-wind o’er the Lisbon bar,
would aid our Sancho the foul foe to tame,
all being bounden for the Holy War:
As to his Father, happed to him the same;
and Lisbon fell to fortunes similar;
aided by Germans, Sylves town he takes
and the fierce dweller slays or subject makes.

89

“And if so many trophies from Mahound
his valour snatchèd, eke denies his pride
the Leoneze in peace to till their ground,
whom Mart with martial usage loved to guide:
Till on the bended neck his yoke he bound
of haughty Túi and all its country-side;
where many a city felt the dreaded blow
which with thine arms thou, Sancho! broughtest low.

90

“But ’mid his many palms this Prince waylaid
the stroke of tem’erous Death; his heir prefer’d
was that esteemèd son whom all obey’d,
second Afonso, of our Kings the third.
He reigning, Alcacér-do-Sal was made
ours, snatcht for ever from the Moorish herd;
that erst was taken by the Moor beset,
and now parforce he pays of Death the Debt.

91

“Afonso dying, straight to him succeedeth
a second Sancho, easy-going soul,
who in his weakling idlesse so exceedeth,
the rulèd rule their ruler and their tool:
He lost the Reign, for which another pleadeth,
by private preference deprived of rule;
since, govern’d only by his minions’ will
he made him partner in their works of ill.

92

“Yet ne’er was Sancho, no, such profl’igate pest
as was that Nero wedded with a boy,
who in foul incest showing horrid zest
his mother Agrippina dared enjoy;
Ne’er with strange cruel arts did he molest
the liege, nor gar’d the torch his town destroy;
he was no waster, no Heliogabálus,[73]
no woman-king like soft Sardanapálus.

93

“Ne’er was his tyr’annised people so chastisèd
as wretched Sicill by her tyrant bane;
ne like the despot Phálaris, he devisèd
novel inventions for inhuman pain:
But his high-hearted realm, which ever prizèd
lords of the highest hopes and sovran strain,
would ne’er whole-soulèd such a King obey,
who showed not fittest for the kingly sway.

94

“Hence came the gov’ernance of the reign to right
the County Bolognese; and he arose
at length to kingship, when from life took flight
his brother Sancho sunk in soft repose.
This, whom the ‘Brave Afonso’ subjects hight,
when fenced his kingdom from internal foes,
strives to dilate it; what his Sire possest
is worlds too narrow for so big a breast.

95

“Of both Algarves, given to his hand
in gift of bridal dowry, greater part
his arm recovers, and outdrives the band
of Moors ill-treated now by hostile Mart.
He freed and made the Mistress of her Land
our Lusitania, such his bellic art;
till final ruin whelmed the mighty hordes
where’er Earth ownèd Lusus’ subjects lords.

96

“See, next that Diniz comes in whom is seen
the ‘brave Afonso’s’ offspring true and digne;
whereby the mighty boast obscurèd been,
the vaunt of lib’eral Alexander’s line:
Beneath his sceptre blooms the land serene
(already compast golden Peace divine)
with constitution, customs, laws and rights,
a tranquil country’s best and brightest lights.

97

“The first was he who made Coimbra own
Pallas-Minerva’s gen’erous exercise;
he called the Muses’ choir from Helicon
to tread the lea that by Mondego lies:
Whate’er of good whilere hath Athens done,
here proud Apollo keepeth ev’ery prize:
Here gives he garlands wove with golden ray,
with perfumed Nard and ever-verdant Bay.

98

“Brave towns and cities reared his hand anew,
stout fortalice, and strongly-castled mure,
while his well-nigh reformèd kingdom grew
with stalwart towers and lofty walls secure:
But when dure Atropos cut short the clew,
and shore the thin-spun thread of life mature,
arose, to filial duty nidering
the fourth Afonso, yet a brave good King.

99

“This proud Castile’s bravades with equal pride
despised, of soul and breast serenely grand;
for aye the Lusitanian’s sprite defied
fear of the strongest, though the smaller band:
But when the Mauritanian races hied
to win and wear Hesperia’s winsome land,
and marchèd boldly to debel Castile
superb Afonso went to work her weal.

100

“Ne’er did Semiramis such myriads see
who o’er the wide Hydaspick prairie trod;
nor Attila—who daunteth Italy
with dreadful boast, self-titled ‘Scourge of God,’—
hurried such Gothick hosts to victory,
as the wild Saracens’ stupendous crowd,
with all th’ excessive might Granáda yields
that flockt to battle on Tartessus’ fields.

101

“When saw Castilia’s monarch, high and haught,
such force inexpugnable fain of strife,
dreading lest all Hispania come to naught,
once lost ere this,[74] far more than loss of life;
aid of our Lusian chivalry he sought
and sent the summons by his dearest wife,
his spouse who sends her, and the joy and pride
of the fond Father to whose realm she hied.

102

“Enter’d Maria, fairest of the fair,
her Father’s palace-halls of tow’ering height;
lovely her gest though joy was crusht by care
that brimmed her beauteous eyes with tears that blight:
and waved her glorious wealth of golden hair
o’er neck and shoulders iv’ory-smooth and white:
Before her gladly-greeting Sire she stood,
and told her mission in this melting mood:—

103

“ ‘Whatever various races Earth hath borne,[75]
the fierce strange peoples of all Africk-land
leadeth Marocco’s mighty Monarch, sworn
our noble Spain to conquer and command:
Power like this ne’er met beneath the Morn
since bitter Ocean learnt to bathe the strand:
They bring such fierceness and a rage so dread
the Living shake and quake the buried Dead.

104

“ ‘He to whose arms thou gavest me to wife,
his land defending when such foes invade,
offers himself, o’erfeeble for the strife,
to the hard mercies of the Moorish blade;
if, Sire! thou deign not aid that all-dear life,
me shalt thou see from out the kingdom fade,
widowèd, wretched, doomed to lot obscure,
sans realm, sans husband, e’en sans life secure.

105

“ ‘Wherefore, O King! of whom for purest fear,
Mulucha’s[76] currents in their course congeal;
cast from thee dull delay, rise, swift appear
a second Saviour to our sad Castile:
If this thy count’enance, beaming love so dear,
set on a Father’s fond proud heart its seal,
haste, Father! succour, an thou hasten not,
haply he faileth who thy succour sought.’

106

“Not otherwise fear-filled Maria spake
her Sire, than Venus when, in saddest strain,
she pled to great All-Father for the sake
of her Aeneas tossing on the Main;
and in Jove’s breast could such compassion ’wake,
his dreadful thunders from his hand fall vain:
The clement Godhead all to her concedeth
and mourneth only that no more she needeth.

107

“But now the squadded warriors muster dense
on Eborensian plains with fierce array;
glint in the sun-glare harness, sword, spear, lance,
and richly furnisht destriers prance and neigh:
The banner’d trumpets with a blast advance,
rousing men’s bosoms from the gentle sway
of holy Peace to dire refulgent arms,
and down the dales reverb’erate War’s alarms.[77]

108

“Majestic marcheth, girt by all his powers,
th’ insignia of his Royal state among,
valiant Afonso, and his tall form towers
by neck and shoulders taller than the throng;
his gest alone embraves the heart that cowers,
in his stout presence wax the weaklings strong:
Thus to Castilia’s realm he leads his band,
with his fair daughter, Ladye of the Land.

109

“In fine when met the Kings, Afonsos twain,[78]
upon Tarifa’s field, they stand to front
that swarming host of stone-blind heathen men,
for whom are small the meadows and the mount.
No sprite there liveth of so tough a grain,
but feels its faith and trust of small account,
did it not clearly see and fully know,
Christ by His servants’ arms shall smite the foe.

110

“The seed of Hagar laughing, as it were,
to view the Christian pow’er so weak, so mean;
begins the lands, as though their own, to share
ere won, among the conqu’ering Hagarene;
such forgèd title and false style they bear
claiming the famous name of Saracene:
Thus with false reck’oning would they strip and spoil
calling it theirs, that noble alien soil.

111

“E’en so the barb’arous Giant huge and gaunt,
with cause to royal Saul so dread appearing
when seen the swordless Shepherd stand afront,
armed but with pebbles and with heart unfearing;
launchèd his sneer of pride and arr’ogant taunt
at the weak youngling’s humble raiment jeering,
who, whirled the sling, soon read the lesson well,
how much shall Faith all human force excel:

112

“Thus do the Moormen, traitor-souls, despise
our Christian forces, nor can understand
how Heav’en’s high fortress wonted aid affies,
which e’en horrific Hell may not withstand:
On this and on his skill Castile relies,
falls on Marocco’s King, strikes hand to hand:
The Portingall, who holds all danger light,
makes the Granádan kingdom fear his might.

113

“Behold! the brandisht blade and lance at rest,
rang loud on coat and crest, a wild onsèt!
They cried, as each his several law confest,
these ‘Sanct’ Thiago!’ and those ‘Mahomet!’
The cries of wounded men the skies opprest,
whose flowing blood in ugly puddles met,
where other half-slain wretches drowning lay,
who dragged their shatter’d limbs from out the fray.

114

“With such prevailing force the Lusian fought
the Gránadil, that in the shortest space
an utter ruin of his host was wrought;
ne fence, ne steely plate our strokes could face:
With such triumphant Vict’ory cheaply bought
unsatisfied, the Strong Arm[79] flies apace,
and timely aids Castilia’s toiling pow’er,
still mixt in doubtful conflict with the Moor.

115

“Now brightly burning Sol had housed his wain
in Thetis’ bower, and his slanting ray
sank westward, bearing Hesper in his train,
to close that rare and most memorious day:
When of the Moors those valiant Sovrans twain
the dense and dreadful squadrons swept away,
with such fell slaughter as ne’er told of Man
the page of Story since the world began.

116

“Ne’er could strong Marius e’en the quarter show,
of lives here victim’d by victorious Fate;
when to the river, red with gory glow,
he sent his thirsty Braves their drouth to sate:
Ne yet the Carthaginian, asp’erous foe
to Roman pow’er and cradled in her hate,
when slain so many Knights of noble Rome,
of their gold rings he sent three bushels home.

117

“And if sole thou so many souls to flit
couldst force, and seek Cocytus’ reign of night,
when thou the Holy City didst acquit
of the base Júdean, firm in olden rite;
’twas that Jehovah’s vengeance thus saw fit,
O noble Titus! not thine arm of might;
for thus inspirèd men had prophesied,
and thus by Jesu’s lips ’twas certified.

118

“Accomplishèd his act of arms victorious,
home to his Lusian realm Afonso sped,
to gain from Peace-tide triumphs great and glorious,
as those he gained in wars and battles dread;[80]
when the sad chance, on History’s page memorious,
which can unsepulchre the sheeted dead,
befell that ill-starr’d miserable Dame
who, foully slain, a thronèd Queen became.

119

“Thou, only thou, pure Love, whose cruel might
obligeth human hearts to weal and woe,
thou, only thou, didst wreak such foul despight,
as though she were some foul perfidious foe.
Thy burning thirst, fierce Love, they say aright,
may not be quencht by saddest tears that flow;
nay, more, thy sprite of harsh tyrannick mood
would see thine altars bathed with human blood.

120

“He placed thee, fair Ignèz! in soft retreat,
culling the first-fruits of thy sweet young years,
in that delicious Dream, that dear Deceit,
whose long endurance Fortune hates and fears:
Hard by Mondego’s yearned-for meads thy seat,
where linger, flowing still, those lovely tears,
until each hill-born tree and shrub confest
the name of Him deep writ within thy breast.[81]

121

“There, in thy Prince awoke responsive-wise
dear thoughts of thee which soul-deep ever lay;
which brought thy beauteous form before his eyes,
whene’er those eyne of thine were far away:
Night fled in falsest, sweetest fantasies,
in fleeting, flying reveries sped the Day;
and all, in fine, he saw or cared to see
were memories of his love, his joys, his thee.

122

“Of many a dainty dame and damosel
the coveted nuptial couches he rejecteth;
for nought can e’er, pure Love! thy care dispel,
when one enchanting shape thy heart subjecteth.
These whims of passion to despair compel
the Sire, whose old man’s wisdom aye respecteth,
his subjects murmuring at his son’s delay
to bless the nation with a bridal day.

123

“To wrench Ignèz from life he doth design,
better his captured son from her to wrench;
deeming that only blood of death indign
the living lowe of such true Love can quench.
What Fury willed it that the steel so fine,
which from the mighty weight would never flinch
of the dread Moorman, should be drawn in hate
to work that hapless delicate Ladye’s fate?

124

“The horr’ible Hangmen hurried her before
the King, now moved to spare her innocence;
but still her cruel murther urged the more,
the People swayed by fierce and false pretence.
She with her pleadings pitiful and sore,
that told her sorrows and her care immense
for her Prince-spouse and babes, whom more to leave
than her own death the mother’s heart did grieve:

125

“And heav’enwards to the clear and chryst’alline skies,
raising her eyne with piteous tears bestainèd;
her eyne, because her hands with cruel ties
one of the wicked Ministers[82] constrainèd:
And gazing on her babes in wistful guise,
whose pretty forms she loved with love unfeignèd,
whose orphan’d lot the Mother filled with dread,
unto their cruel grandsire thus she said—

126

“ ‘If the brute-creatures, which from natal day
on cruel ways by Nature’s will were bent;
or feral birds whose only thought is prey,
upon aerial rapine all intent;
if men such salvage be’ings have seen display
to little children loving sentiment,
e’en as to Ninus’ mother did befall,
and to the twain who rear’d the Roman wall:

127

“ ‘O thou, who bear’st of man the gest and breast,
(an it be manlike thus to draw the sword
on a weak girl, because her love imprest
his heart, who took her heart and love in ward);
respect for these her babes preserve, at least!
since it may not her òbscure death retard:
Moved be thy pitying soul for them and me,
although my faultless fault unmoved thou see!

128

“ ‘And if thou know’est to deal in direful fight
the doom of brand and blade to Moorish host,
know also thou to deal of life the light
to one who ne’er deserved her life be lost:
But an thou wouldst mine inn’ocence thus requite,
place me for aye on sad exilèd coast,
in Scythian sleet, on seething Libyan shore,
with life-long tears to linger evermore.

129

“ ‘Place me where beasts with fiercest rage abound—
Lyons and Tygers—there, ah! let me find
if in their hearts of flint be pity found,
denied to me by heart of humankind.
There with intrinsic love and will so fond
for him whose love is death, there will I tend
these tender pledges whom thou see’st; and so
shall the sad mother cool her burning woe.’

130

“Inclin’ed to pardon her the King benign,
moved by this sad lament to melting mood;
but the rude People and Fate’s dure design
(that willed it thus) refused the pardon sued:
They draw their swords of steely temper fine,
they who proclaim as just such deed of blood:
Against a ladye, caitiff, felon wights!
how showed ye here, brute beasts or noble knights?

131

“Thus on Polyxena, that beauteous maid,
last solace of her mother’s age and care,
when doom’d to die by fierce Achilles’ shade,
the cruel Pyrrhus hasted brand to bare:
But she (a patient lamb by death waylaid),
with the calm glances which serene the air,
casts on her mother, mad with grief, her eyes
and silent waits that awesome sacrifice.

132

“Thus dealt with fair Ignèz the murth’erous crew,
in th’ alabastrine neck that did sustain
the charms whereby could Love the love subdue
of him, who crown’d her after death his Queen;
bathing their blades; the flow’ers of snowy hue,
which often water’ed by her eyne had been,
are blood-dyed; and they burn with blinding hate,
reckless of tortures stor’d for them by Fate.

133

“Well mightest shorn of rays, O Sun! appear
to fiends like these on day so dark and dire;
as when Thyestes ate the meats that were
his seed, whom Atreus slew to spite their sire.
And you, O hollow Valleys! doomed to hear
her latest cry from stiffening lips expire—
her Pedro’s name—did catch that mournful sound,
whose echoes bore it far and far around!

134

“E’en as a Daisy sheen, that hath been shorn
in time untimely, floret fresh and fair,
and by untender hand of maiden torn
to deck the chaplet for her wreathèd hair;
gone is its odour and its colours mourn;
so pale and faded lay that Ladye there;
dried are the roses of her check, and fled
the white live colour, with her dear life dead.

135

“Mondego’s daughter-Nymphs the death obscure
wept many a year, with wails of woe exceeding;
and for long mem’ry changed to fountain pure,
the floods of grief their eyes were ever feeding:
The name they gave it, which doth still endure,
revived Ignèz, whose murthered love lies bleeding,
see yon fresh fountain flowing ’mid the flowers,
tears are its waters, and its name “Amores!”[83]

136

“Time ran not long, ere Pedro saw the day
of vengeance dawn for wounds that ever bled;
who, when he took in hand the kingly sway,
eke took the murth’erers who his rage had fled:
Them a most cruel Pedro did betray;
for both, if human life the foemen dread,
made concert savage and dure pact, unjust as
Lepidus made with Anth’ony and Augustus.

137

“This in his judgments rig’orous and severe,
plunder, advoutries, murtherers supprest:
To stay with cruel grasp Crime’s dark career,
bred sole assurèd solace in his breast:
A Justiciary, not by love but fear,
he guarded Cities from haught tyrant-pest;
their doom more robbers dree’d by his decrees
than Theseus slew, or vagueing Hercules.

138

“Pedro, the harshly just, begets the bland,
(see what exceptions lurk in Nature’s laws!)
remiss, and all-regardless prince, Fernand,
who ran his realm in danger’s open jaws:
For soon against the weak, defenceless land
came the Castilian, who came nigh to cause
the very ruin of the Lusian reign;
for feeble Kings enfeeble strongest strain.

139

“Or ’twas the wages Sin deserves of Heaven,
that filchèd Léonor from marriage bed,
by false, misunderstood opinions driven
another’s wife, a leman-bride to wed;
Or ’twas because his easy bosom given
to vice and vileness, and by both misled,
waxèd effeminate weak; which may be true,[84]
for low-placed loves the highest hearts subdue.

140

“Of such offences ever paid the pain
many, whom God allowed or willèd He;
those who fared forth to force the fair Helèn;
Appius and Tarquin, eke, such end did see:
Say, why should David of the saintly strain
so blame himself? What felled th’ illustrious tree
of Benjamin? Full well the truth design a
Pharaoh for Sara, Sichem for a Dinah.

141

“But if so weakeneth forceful human breast
illicit Love, which spurns the golden mean,
well in Alcmené’s son we find the test
as Omphalé disguis’ed to hero-quean.
Anthony’s fame a shade of shame confest,
to Cleopatra bound by love too keen;
nor less thou, Punick victor! wast betray’d
by low allegiance to some Puglian maid.

142

“Yet say who, peradventure, shall secure
his soul from Cupid armed with artful snare
’mid the live roses, human snow so pure,
the gold and alabaster crystal-clare?
who ’scapeth Beauty’s wiles and per’egrine lure,
the true Medusa-face so awful fair,
which man’s imprison’d, witch-bound heart can turn
no, not to stone, but flames that fiercely burn?

143

“Who se’eth a firm-fixt glance, a gesture bland,
soft promises of angel-excellence,
the soul transforming aye by charmed command;
say, who from pow’er like this can find defence?
Pardie, he scantly blameth King Fernand
who pays, as he did, Love’s experience:
But human Judgment would, if fancy-free,
adjudge his laches even worse to be.

Canto IV

Da Gama pursueth his discourse with the King of Melinde, and relateth the wars between Portugal and Castile, touching the succession to the throne, after the death of the king, D. Fernando: Military feats of the Constable, D. Nuno Alvares Pereira: Battle and victory of Aljubarrota: Diligent attempts to discover India by land, in the days of the king D. Joam II: How the king D. Manoel gained this end by resolving upon the present voyage: Preparations for it: Embarkation and farewells of the navigators upon the Belem beach.

Joam acclaimèd to be Pedro’s heir, (1–5)
Léonor craveth aidance of Castile: (6–13)
Withstandeth Nuno, warrior sans fear, (14–22)
They fight; and conquest crowns the Lusian’s weal: (23–47)
Who first went forth the Morning-land to spere (60–66)
And through the tumid flood his way to feel;
And how to Gama fell the great emprize, (77–End)
To gar our Port’ugal’s glory higher rise.

1

“After the horrors of the stormy Night,
with gloom, and lightning-gleams, and hiss of wind,
breaks lovely Morning’s pure and blessèd light,
with hope of haven and sure rest to find:
Sol banisheth the dark obscure from sight,
laying the terror of man’s timid mind:
Thus to the doughty kingdom it befell,
when King Fernando bade this world farewell.

2

“For, if so many with such hopes were firèd
for one whose potent arm their harms could pay
on those, that wrought their wrongs with soul untirèd,
nerved by Fernando’s heedless, feeble way;
in shortest time it happed as they desirèd,
when ever-glorious John arose to sway,
the only heir that did from Pedro spring,
and (though a bastard) every inch a King.

3

“That such accession came from Heaven divine
proved ’special marvels, God His truth proclaiming,
when Ev’ora city saw the choicest sign,
a babe of age unspeech’d the ruler naming;
and, but to show the Heav’en’s supreme design,
she raised her cradled limbs and voice, exclaiming—
‘Portugal! Port’ugal!’ high uplifting hand,
‘for the new king, Dom John, who rules the land.’

4

“Changèd in sprite were all within the Reign,
old hatreds firing hearts with novel flame;
absolute cruelties none cared restrain
popular Fury dealt to whence it came:
Soon are the friends and kith and kinsmen slain
of the adult’erous County and the Dame,
with whom incont’inent love and lust unblest,
the wappen’d widow showèd manifest.

5

“But he, dishonour’d and with cause, at last
by cold white weapon falls before her eyes,
and with him many to destruction past;
for flame so kindled all consuming flies:
This, like Astyanax, is headlong cast
from the tall steeple (’spite his dignities);
whom orders, altar, honours, nought avail;
those through the highways torn and stript they trail.

6

“Now long Oblivion veils the deeds accurst
of mortal fierceness, such as Rome beheld,
done by fierce Marius, or the bloody thirst
of Sylla, when parforce his foe expel’d.
Thus Léonor, who mortal vengeance nurst
for her dead County gars, with fury swell’d,
Castilia’s force on Lusitania fall,
calling her daughter heir of Portugal.

7

“Beatrice was the daughter, interwed
with the Castilian, who for kingship greedeth,
putative offspring of Fernando’s bed,
if evil Fame so much to her concedeth.
Hearing the voice, Castile high raiseth head,
and saith this daughter to her sire succeedeth;
for warfare must’ereth she her warrior bands
from various regions and from various lands.

8

“They flock from all the Province, by one Brigo[85]
(if such man ever was) yclept of yore;
and lands by Ferd’inand won, and Cid Rodrigo
from the tyrannick gov’ernance of the Moor.
Little in fear of warlike feat doth he go
who with hard plowshare cleaving lordeth o’er
the champaign Leonèze, and boasts to be
the blight and bane of Moorish chivalry.

9

“In Valour’s ancient fame the Vandal host,
confident still and stubborn, ’gan appear
from all Andalusía’s head and boast,
laved by thy crystal wave, Guadalquivir!
the noble Island[86] eke, whilere the post
of Tyrian strangers, to the war drew near,
bringing insignia by renown well known,
Hercules’ Pillars on their pennons shown.

10

“Eke come they trooping from Toledo’s reign,
City of noble, ancient or’igin, span’d
by Tagus circling with his sweet glad vein,
that bursts and pours from Conca’s[87] mountain-land.
You also, you, all craven fear disdain
sordid Gallegos! hard and canny band,
for stern resistance fast to arms ye flew,
warding their doughty blows whose weight ye knew.

11

“Eke War’s black Furies hurried to the fight
the fierce Biscayan folk, who clean despise
all polisht reasons, and ne wrong ne slight
of stranger races bear in patient guise.
Asturias-land and that Guipusc’oan hight,
proud of the mine which iron ore supplies,
with it their haughty sworders armed and made
ready their rightful lords i’ the war to aid.

12

“John in whose bosom Peril only grows
the strength Jew Sampson borrow’d of his hair,
though all he hath be few to fight his foes,
yet bids his few for battle-gage prepare:
And, not that counsel fails when danger shows,
with his chief lords he counsels on th’ affair,
but drift of inner thoughts he seeks and finds;
for ’mid the many there be many minds.

13

“Nor lack their reas’onings who would disconcert
opinions firmly fixt in pop’ular will,
whose weal of ancient valour is convèrt
to an unusèd and disloyal ill:
Men in whose hearts Fear, gelid and inert,
reigneth, which faith and truth were wont to fill:
Deny they King and Country; and, if tried,
they had (as Peter did) their God denied.

14

“But ne’er did such denial-sin appear
in noble Nuno Alv’ares, nay, instead—
although his brothers show’d default so clear—
he fiercely chid the fickle hearts misled;
and to the lieges steeped in doubt and fear,
with phrase more forceful than fine-drawn he said,
too fere for facund, as he bared his glave,
threating Earth, seas, and sphere with ban and brave:—

15

“ ‘What! ’mid the noble sons of Portugale
that nills to strike for freedom beats a heart?
What! in this province which the nations all
crowned War’s princess in ev’ery earthly part
breathes, who his aid denies, such nid’ering thrall?
renaying faith and love, and force and art
of Portingall; and, be whate’er the cause,
would see his country keep the stranger’s laws?

16

“ ‘What! flows not still within your veins the blood
of the brave soldiers who ’neath banners borne
by great Henriques[88] fierce with hero-mood,
this valiant race in war did ever scorn?
When tane so many banners, and withstood
so many foemen, who such losses mourn,
that seven noble Yarls were forced to yield
their swords besides the spoils that strewed the field?

17

“ ‘Say you, by whom were alway trodden down
these, now who seem to tread adown on you;
for Diniz and his son of high renown,
save by your sires’ and grandsires’ derring-do?
Then if by sin or sore neglect o’erthrown
so could your olden force Fernand undo,
to you fresh forces this new King shall bring;
an it be sooth that Subjects change with King.

18

“ ‘Such King ye have, that an ye courage have
equal his kingly heart ye raised to reign,
all en’emies shall ye rout so be ye brave,
much more the routed, eath to rout again:
But an such noble thought no more may save
your souls from pen’etrant Fear to bosom tane,
the craven hands of seely terrors tie,
this stranger’s yoke I, only I, defy.

19

“ ‘I with my vassals only, and my brand
(this said, his dreadful blade he bared mid-way)
against the high and hostile force will stand,
that threats a kingdom strange to stranger sway:
By virtue of my Liege, my mourning Land,
of Loyalty denied by you this day
I’ll conquer all, not only these my foes,
but whatsoever durst my King oppose.’

20

“E’en as the Youths who ’scaping Cannae-field—
its only remnants—to Canusium fled
despairing, and well-nigh disposed to yield,
and hail the Carthaginian vict’ory-led,
the young Cornelius to their faith appeal’d,
and took his comrades’ oath upon his blade
the Roman arms t’ uphold as long as life
hold, or hath pow’er to ’scape the mortal strife:

21

“Forceth the Folk enforcèd in such wise
Nuno, and when his final words they hear,
th’ ice-cold and sullen humour sudden flies,
that curdled spirits with a coward fear:
To mount the beast Neptunian all arise,
charging and tossing high the lance and spear;
they run and shout with open-mouthèd glee—
‘Long live the famous King who sets us free!’

22

“O’ the pop’ular classes not a few approve
the War their natal land and home sustains:
These fare to furbish armours, and remove
injurious rust, of Peace the biting stains;
they quilt their morions, plates for breast they prove;
each arms himself e’en as his fancy fain ’s;
while those on coats with thousand colours bright,
the signs and symbols of their loves indite.

23

“With all this lustrous Company enrol’d
from fresh Abrantès sallies John the Brave,
Abrantès, fed by many a fountain cold
of Tagus rolling sweet abundant wave.
The vanguard-knights commands that warrior bold
by Nature fittest made command to have
of th’ Oriental hordes withouten count,
wherewith Sir Xerxes crost the Hellespont:

24

“I say Don Nuno, who appearèd here
the proudest scourger of that prideful Spain,
as was in olden days the Hun so fere,
curse of the Frankish, of Italian men.
Followed another far-famed cavalier
who led the dexter phalanx Lusitane,
apt to dispose them, prompt to lead his fellows,
Mem Rodrigues they call de Vasconcéllos.

25

“While of the Knights in corresponding flank
Antám Vasqués d’Almáda hath command,
to Avranches’ Earldom rose anon his rank,
who holds the Lusian host’s sinistral hand.
Nor far the banner from men’s notice shrank
in rear, where Cinques by Castles[89] bordered stand
with John the King, who shows a front so dread
E’en Mars must learn to hide his ’minished head.

26

“Linèd the rempart[90] groups of trembling fair,
whom hopes and fears alternate heat and freeze,
mothers and sisters, wives and brides in pray’er,
with fasts and pilgrim-vows the Heav’ens to please.
And now the Squadrons wont the war to dare,
affront the serrièd hosts of enemies,
who meet this onset with a mighty shout;
while all are whelmed in dreadful direful doubt.

27

“Messenger-trumpets to the cries reply,
and sibilant fife, and drum, and atambor;
while Ancients wave their flags, and banners fly
with many-colour’d legends ’broidered o’er.
’Twas fruity August when the days be dry,
and Ceres heaps the peasant’s threshing-floor,
August, when Sol Astraea’s mansion reigneth;[91]
and the sweet must of grapes Lyaeus straineth.

28

“Sudden Castilia’s trump the signal gave
horribly fearful, sounding tem’erous dread:
Heard it the Hill Artábrus;[92] and his wave
Guadiana rollèd backwards as he fled:
O’er Douro and Transtagan lands it drave;
Tagus sore agitated seaward sped;
while mothers trembling at the terr’ible storm
embraced with tighter arm each tiny form.

29

“How many faces there wan waxt and white,
whose fainting hearts the friendly life-blood cheerèd!
For in dire danger Fear hath more of might—
the fear of danger—than the danger fearèd:
If not, it seemeth so; when rage of fight
man’s sprite to quell or kill the foe hath stirrèd,
it makes him all unheed how high the cost
were loss of limb, or dear life rashly lost.

30

“Battle’s uncertain work begins; and move
right wings on either part to take the plain;
these fighting to defend the land they love,
those eggèd on by hope that land to gain:
Soon great Pereira, who would foremost prove
the knightly valour of his noble strain;
charges and shocks, and strews the field till sown
with those who covet what is not their own.

31

“Now in the dust-blurred air with strident sound
bolts, arrows, darts and man’ifold missiles fly;
beneath the destrier’s horny hoof the ground
quaketh in terror, and the dales reply;
shiver the lances; thundereth around
the frequent crash of fellèd armoury;
foes on the little force redoubling fall
of Nuno fierce, who makes great numbers small.

32

“See! there his brethren meet him in the fray:
(Fierce chance and cruel case!) But dreads he nought;
right little were it brother-foe to slay,
who against King and Country trait’orous fought:
Amid these ren’egades not a few that day
war in the foremost squadrons fury-fraught
against their brethren and their kin (sad Fate!)
as in great Julius’ warfare with the Great.[93]

33

“O thou, Sertorius! O great Coriolane!
Catiline! all ye hosts of bygone age,
who ’gainst your Fatherland with hearts profane
ragèd with rav’ening parricidal rage;
if where Sumánus holds his dismal reign
most dreadful torments must your sin assuage,
tell him, that e’en our Portugal sometimes
suckled some traitors guilty of your crimes.

34

“Here doth the foremost of our lines give way,
so many foemen have its force opprest:
There standeth Nuno, brave as Ly’on at bay,
where Africk Ceita rears her hilly crest;
who sees the ’circling troop of cavalry,
over the Tetu’an plain to chase addrest;
and raging as they couch the deadly spear
seems somewhat stirred, but hides all craven fear:

35

“With sidelong glance he sights them, but his spleen
ferine forbids the King of Beasts to show
a craven back; nay, rather on the screen
of plumping lances leaps he as they grow.
So stands our Knight, who stains and soils the green
with alien gore-streams: On that field lie low
some of his own; howe’er with valour dowerèd
hearts lose their virtue by such odds o’erpowerèd.

36

“John felt the danger and the dure affront
of Nuno; straight like Captain wise and ware,
he rushed afield, viewed all, and in the brunt
with words and works taught men fresh deeds to dare.
As nursing Ly’oness, fere and fierce of front,
who, left for chase her whelps secure in lair,
findeth while for’aging for their wonted food
Massylian[94] hind hath dared to rob her brood:

37

“Runs, frantick raging, while her roar and moan
make the Seven-Brother Mountains[95] shake and rave.
So John with other chosen troop hath flown
foeward his dexter wing t’ enforce and save:
‘Oh strong Companions! Souls of high renown!
Cavaliers braver than what men hold brave,
strike for your country! now all earthly chance,
all hope of Liberty is on your lance!’

38

“ ‘Behold me here, your Comrade and your King,
who ’mid the spear and harness, bolt and bow,
foremost I charge and first myself I fling;
smite, ye true Portughuese, deal yet one blow!’
Thus spake that great-soul’d Warrior, brandishing
four times his lance before the final throw;
and, thrusting forceful, by that single thrust
lanceth such wounds that many bite the dust.

39

“For, see, his soldiers brent with ardour new,
honoured repentance, honourable fire,
who shall display most courage staid and true,
and dare the dangers dealt by Mars his ire
contend: The steel that catcheth flamey hue,
aims first at plate, then at the breast aims higher;
thus, wounds they give and wounds they take again;
and, dealing Death, in Death they feel no pain.

40

“Many are sent to sight the Stygian wave,
into whose bodies entered iron Death:
Here dieth Sanct’ Iágo’s Master brave,
who fought with fiercest sprite till latest breath;
another Master dire of Calatrave,
horrid in cruel havock, perisheth:
Eke the Pereiras foully renegate
die God denying and denouncing Fate.

41

“Of the vile, nameless Vulgar many bleed;
flitting with Gentles to the Gulf profound;
where hungers, rav’ening with eternal greed,
for passing human Shades the three-head Hound:
And humbling more that haughty, arr’ogant breed,
and better taming enemies furibund,
Castilia’s Gonfanon sublime must fall
beneath the forceful foot of Portugall.

42

“Here[96] wildest Battle hath its cruel’est will,
with deaths and shouts, and slash and gory shower;
the multitud’inous Braves, who’re killed and kill,
rob of their proper hues the bloom and flower:
At length they fly! they die! now waxeth still
War’s note, while lance and spear have lost their power:
Castilia’s King the fate of pride must own,
seeing his purpose changed, his host o’erthrown.

43

“The field he leaveth to the Conqueror,
too glad his life had not been left in fight:
Follow him all who can; and panick sore
lends them not feet, but feather’d wings for flight:
Their breasts are fillèd with a wild doloùr,
for Deaths, for Treasure waste in wanton plight;
for woe, disgust, and foul dishonour’s soil
to see the Victor rev’elling in their spoil.

44

“Some fly with furious curses, and blaspheme
him who the World with Warfare made accurst;
others that cov’etous breast all culp’able deem
for Greed enquicken’d by his selfish thirst.
That, alien wealth to win, with sore extreme
he plunged his hapless folk in woes the worst;
leaving so many wives and mothers, lorn
of sons and spouses, evermore to mourn.

45

“Campèd our conqu’ering John the ’customed days
on foughten field, in glory of the brave;
then with vowed pilgrimage, gift, pray’er, and praise,
he gave Him graces who such vict’ory gave.
But Nuno, willing not by peaceful ways
on human memory his name to ’grave,
but by his sovran feats of war, commands
his men pass over to Transtágan lands.

46

“His gallant project favoureth Destiny,
making effect commensurate with cause;
the Lands that bordered by the Vandals lie
yielding their treasures bow before his laws:
Now Baetic banners which Seville o’erfly,
and flags of various princes, without pause,
all trail foot-trampled; naught their force availeth
whate’er the forceful Portingall assaileth.[97]

47

“By these and other Victories opprest,
Castilia’s lieges long deplored their woes;
when Peace by all desired and gentle Rest,
to grant their vanquisht fone the Victors chose;
then seemed it good to His almighty hest
that the contending Sovrans should espouse
two royal Damsels born of English race,
Princesses famed for honour, form, and grace.

48

“Nills the brave bosom, used to bloody broil,
the lack of foeman who his force shall dree;
and thus, Earth holding none to slay and spoil,
he carries conquest o’er the unconquer’d Sea.
First of our Kings is he who left the soil
patrial, teaching Africk’s Paynimry,
by dint of arms, how much in word and deed
the Laws of Christ Mafamed’s laws exceed.

49

“See! thousand swimming Birds the silv’ery plain
of Thetis cleave, and spurn her fume and fret,
with bellied wings to seize the wind they strain,
where his extremest mete Alcides set:
Mount Abyla, and dight with tow’er and fane
Ceita, they seize, ignoble Mahomet
they oust: and thus our gen’eral Spain secure
from Julian-craft,[98] disloyal and impure.

50

“Death granted not to Portugal’s desire
Hero so happy long should wear the crown;
but soon th’ angelick Host and heav’enly Choir
a home in highest Heaven made his own:
To ward his Lusia, and to raise her higher,
He who withdrew him left the goodly boon—
building our country on her broadest base—
of noble Infants a right royal Race.

51

“Noways so happy was Duarte’s fate,
what while he rose the royal rank to fill:
Thus troublous Time doth ever alternate
pleasure with pain, and temper good with ill.
What man hath lived through life in joyous state,
who firmness finds in Fortune’s fickle will?
Yet to this Kingdom and this King she deignèd
spare the vicissitudes her laws ordainèd.

52

“Captive he saw his brother, hight Fernand,
the Saint aspiring high with purpose brave,
who as a hostage in the Sara’cen’s hand,
betrayed himself his ’leaguer’d host to save.
He lived for purest faith to Fatherland
the life of noble Ladye sold a slave,
lest bought with price of Ceita’s potent town
to public welfare be preferred his own.

53

“Codrus, lest foemen conquer, freely chose
to yield his life and, conqu’ering self, to die;
Regulus, lest his land in aught should lose,
lost for all time all hopes of liberty;
this, that Hispania might in peace repose,
chose lifelong thrall, eterne captivity:
Codrus nor Curtius with man’s awe for meed,
nor loyal Decii ever dared such deed.

54

“Afonso, now his kingdom’s only heir—
a name of Vict’ory on our Spanish strand—
who, the haught fierceness of the Moor’s frontier
to lowest mis’ery tamed with mighty hand,
pardie, had been a peerless cavalier
had he not lusted after Ebro-land:
But still shall Africk say, ’twere hopeless feat
on battle-plain such terr’ible King to beat.

55

“This could pluck Golden Apples from the bough,
which only he in Tiryns born could pluck:
He yoked the salvage Moor, and even now
the salvage Moorman’s neck must bear his yoke.
Still palms and greeny bays begird his brow
won from the barb’arous raging hosts that flock,
Alcacèr’s fortèd town with arms to guard,
Tangier the pop’ulous, and Arzille the hard.

56

“All these by gallant deeds, in fine, were gainèd,
and low lay ev’ery diamantine wall
anent the Portingalls, now taught and trainèd
to throw the Pow’er that lists to try a fall:
Such extreme marvels by strong arms attainèd—
right worthy el’oquent scripture one and all—
the gallant Cavaliers, whose Gestes of glory
added a lustre to our Lusian story.

57

“But soon, ambition-madded, goaded on
by Passion of Dominion bitter-sweet,
he falls on Ferdinand of Aragon,[99]
Castile’s haught kingdom hoping to defeat.
The swarming hostile crowds their armour don,
the proud and various races troop and meet,
from Cadiz fast to tow’ering Pyrenee,
who bow to Ferdinand the neck and knee.

58

“Scornèd an idler in the realm to rest
the youthful John; who taketh early heed
to aid his greedy father with his best,
and sooth, came th’ aidance at the hour of need.
Issued from bloody battle’s terr’ible test
with brow unmoved, serene in word and deed
maugre defeat, the Sire, that man of blood,
while ’twixt the rivals Vict’ory doubtful stood:

59

“For-that of valiant princely vein his son,
a gentle, stalwart, right magnan’imous Knight,
when to th’ opponents he such harm had done,
one whole day campèd on the field of fight.
Thus from Octavian[100] was the vict’ory won,
while Anthony, his mate, was Victor hight,
when they the murth’erers who the Caesar slew,
upon Philippi-field the deed made rue.

60

“But as thro’ gathered shades of Night eterne
Afonso sped to realms of endless joy,
the Prince who rose to rule our realm in turn
was John the Second and the thirteenth Roy.
This, never-dying Glory’s meed to earn,
higher than ventured mortal man to fly,
ventured; who sought those bounds of ruddy Morn,
which I go seeking, this my voyage-bourne.

61

“Envoys commiss’ioneth he, who passing o’er
Hispania, Gaul, and honoured Italy,
took ship in haven of th’ illustrious shore
where erst inhumèd lay Parthenopè;
Naples, whose Dest’iny was decreed of yore,
the var’ious stranger’s slave and thrall to be,
and rise in honour when her years are full
by sovereign Hispania’s noble rule.

62

“They cleave the bright blue waves of Sic’ulan deeps;
by sandy marge of Rhodos-isle they go;
and thence debark they where the cliffy steeps
are still enfam’d for Magnus here lain low:[101]
To Memphis wend they, and the land that reaps
crops which fat Nylus’ flood doth overflow;
and climb ’yond Egypt to those Aethiop heights
where men conserve Christ’s high and holy rites.

63

“And eke they pass the waters Erythréan,
where past the shipless peoples Israelite;
remain arear the ranges Nabathéan,
which by the name of Ishmael’s seed are hight:
Those odoriferous incense-coasts Sabaean,
dainty Adonis’ Mother’s dear delight,
they round, and all of Happy Ar’aby known,
leaving the Waste of Sand and Reign of Stone.

64

“They push where still preserveth Persic Strait,
confusèd Babel’s darkling memory;
there, where the Tygre blendeth with Euphràte,
which from their head-streams hold their heads so high.
Thence fare they his pure stream to find, whose fate
’twill be to deal such length of history,
Indus, and cross that breadth of Ocean-bed
where daring Trajan never darèd tread.

65

“Strange tribes they saw, and through wild peoples past
Gedrosian, and Carmanian, and of Inde;
seeing the various custom, various caste,
which ev’ery Region beareth in her kind.
But from such asp’erous ways, such voyage vast
man finds not facile safe return to find:
In fine, there died they and to natal shore,
to home, sweet home, returned they nevermore.[102]

66

“Reserved, meseemeth, Heav’en’s clear-sighting will
for Man’oel, worthy of such goodly meed,
this arduous task, and stirred him onward still
to stirring action and illustrious deed:
Man’oel, who rose the throne of John to fill,
and to his high resolves did eke succeed,
forthwith when taken of his realm the charge,
took up the conquest of the Ocean large:

67

“The same, as one obliged by a noble Thought,
the debt of Honour left as ’heritance
by predecessors, (who in life aye fought
their own dear land’s best interests to advance)
ne’er for a moment failèd of his fraught—
Obligement;—at what hour Day’s radiance
pales, and the nitid Stars on high that rise,
with falling courses woo man’s sleep-worn eyes;

68

“Already being on bed of gold recline’d
where Fancy worketh with prophetick strain;
revolving matters in his restless mind,
the bounden duties of his race and reign;
Sleep, soft restorer, comes his eyne to bind,
while thought and mem’ory both unbound remain;
for, as his weary lids sweet slumber sealeth,
Morpheus in varied forms himself revealeth.

69

“Here seems the King so high to soar away,
that touched his head the nearest primal Sphere,[103]
where worlds of vision ’neath his glances lay,
nations of vasty numbers, strange and fere:
and there right near the birthplace of the Day,
unto his outstretched eyne began appear,
from distant, olden, cloud-compelling mountains
flowing, a twain of high, deep, limpid fountains.

70

“Birds of the feral kind, and kine, and flocks,
’bode in the shadows of the shaggy wood:
A thousand herbs and trees with gnarled stocks,
barring the paths of passing mortals stood.
Adverse had ever been those mountain-rocks
to human intercourse, and clearly show’d,
never since Adam sinned against our days,
brake foot of man this breadth of bosky maze.

71

“From out the Fountains seemed he to behold
for him inclining, with long hasty stride,
two Men, who showèd old and very old,
of aspect rustick yet with lordly pride:
Adown their twistèd pointed locks slow roll’d
gouts which their bodies bathed on ev’ery side;
the skin of earthy texture, dark and dull;
the beard hirsute, unshorn, but long and full.

72

“These hoary Fathers round their foreheads bore
tree-boughs, with unknown shrub and herb entwine’d;
and one a worn and wearied aspect wore,
as though from regions lying far behind:
And thus his waters which did slower pour
seemèd adown the further side to wind:
E’en thus Alpheus from Arcádia fled
to Syracuse and Arethusa’s bed.

73

“This, who with graver gait and gesture came,
thus from a distance to the Monarch crieth:
‘O thou! whose sceptre and whose crown shall claim,
of Earth a mighty part that guarded lieth;
we twain, who fly through mouths of men by Fame,
we, whose untamèd neck man’s yoke defieth,
warn thee, O King! ’tis time to send commands,
and raise large tribute from our natal lands.

74

“ ‘Illustrious Gange am I, whose farthest fount
in realms celestial, heav’enly heights, I trace:
And yon stands Indus, King, who on the mount
which thou regardest, hath of birth his place.
Thou shalt hard warfare wage on our account;
but, still insisting ev’ery fear to face,
with ne’er seen conquests, and sans soil or stain,
the tribes thou viewest thou shalt curb and rein.’

75

“No more that holy noble River said;
both in a moment fade and disappear:
Awaketh Manoel in novel dread,
and big o’erchargèd thoughts ybred of fear.
Meanwhile his glitt’ering mantle Phoebus spread
upon the sombre somn’olent hemisphere;
Dawn comes and o’er the gloomy welkin showers
blushings of modest rose, and fiery flowers.

76

“The King in counsel calls his lords to meet,
and of the vision’d figures news imparts;
the holy Elder’s words he doth repeat,
which with a mighty marvel heaves their hearts.
All straight resolve t’ equip a sturdy fleet,
that men, well skilled in navigator-arts,
should cut the stubborn Main and forth should fare
in search of novel climes and novel air.

77

“I, who right little deemed, forsooth, to find
myself attaining hopes my Sprite desirèd;
yet mighty matters of such cunning kind
my heart presaging promised and inspirèd;
e’en now ken not, or how or why design’d,
or for what happy chance in me admirèd,
that famous Monarch chose me, gave to me
of this grave, gracious enterprise the key.

78

“And with fair offer coucht in courteous phrase—
lordly command obliging more than laws—
he said: ‘In exploits dure and daring ways
who woo most perils win the most applause:
Riskt life enfameth man with highest praise
or lost in Honour’s, not in honours’, cause;
And, when to blighting Fear it never bends,
short it may be, yet more its length extends.

79

“ ‘Thee from a chosen host have chosen I
the dangers claimed by thee to undergo:
’Tis heavy travail, hard, heroick, high;
which love of me shall lighten, well I trow.’
I could not suffer more:—‘Great King!’ I cry,
‘to face the steel-clad host, sword, lance, fire, snow,
for thee were thing so slight, my sole annoy
is to see trivial life so vain a toy.

80

“ ‘Imagine ev’ery wildest aventure,
such as Eurystheus for Alcídes plan’d:
Cleone’s Lyon, Harpies foul and dour,
and Boar of Erymanth and Hydra ban’d;
in fine to seek those empty shades obscure
where Styx surrounds of Dis the dire Dead-land;
the greatest danger and the deadliest brunt,
for thee, O King! this soul, this flesh would front.’

81

“His thanks and costly gifts on me bestows
the King, whose reason lauds my ready will;
for Valour fed on praises lives and grows,
Praise is the noble Spirit’s spur and spell.
At once to share my fortunes doth propose,
whom friendship and fraternal love compel,
nor less resolved to win him name and fame, a
dear trusty brother namèd Paul da Gama.

82

“Eke Nicholas Coelho volunteers,
trainèd to toilsome tasks and sufferings long;
both are in valour and in counsel peers,
in arms experienced, and in battle strong.
Now choicest hands in Youthtide’s gen’erous years,
lusting for Bravery’s meed around me throng;
doughty, high-mettled, as doth best become
advent’urous manhood that would tempt such doom.

83

“All these by Man’oel’s hand remun’erate were,
that Love through Duty might the more increase;
and with high words each heart was fired to bear
adventures, peradventure, sans surcease.
Thus did the Minyae for their feat prepare—
to gain the glories of the Golden Fleece—
orac’ulous Argo-ship, that dared the first
through Euxine waves her vent’urous way to burst.

84

“Now in famed Ulysséa’s haven man’d,
with raptures worthy of the great design
(where his sweet liquor and his snowy sand
our Tagus blendeth with Neptunian brine),
ride the ships ready. Here my strong young band
by fear unbridled glad in labour join;
for those of Mars and Neptune,[104] one and all,
the world would wander did I only call.

85

“Fast by the foreshore comes the soldiery
in various colours prankt with various art;
nor less enforced by inner force are they
to seek and see Earth’s unexplorèd part.
Round the good Navy gentle breezes play
and blithely waves each airy estandart:
They[105] swear, far-gazing on the breadth of brine,
’mid stars Olympick Argo-like to shine.

86

“When all prepared according to this sort
with what of wants such lengthy way demandeth,
our souls we did prepare for Death’s disport
who before seaman’s eyne for ever standeth:
To the Most Highest, throned in Heaven’s court
which He sustains, whose glance this globe commandeth,
that He, our guard and guide, His aidance lend,
we prayed, and see our incept to its end.

87

“Thus we departed from the saintly Shrine[106]
built on the margent of the briny wave,
named, for all mem’ory, from the Land Divine,
where God incarnèd came the world to save.
King! I assure thee when this mind of mine
rememb’ereth how ’twas ours those shores to leave,
filled are my sprite and heart with doubts and fears,
and eyes can hardly stay their trickling tears.

88

“The City-people on that saddest day
(these for their bosom-friends, and those for kin,
and others but spectators) thronged the way
sad and down-hearted at the dreary scene:
We, winding through the virtuous array
a thousand monks and priests of rev’erend mien,
praying, in solemn pageant, to the Lord,
afoot set forth the ready barques to board.

89

“On such long dubious courses sent to steer,
us deemed the people den’izens of the tomb;
the wailing women shed the piteous tear,
and sadly sighed the men to sight our doom:
Wives, sisters, mothers (most their hearts must fear
whose love is foremost) added to the gloom
Despair; and shudder’d with a freezing fright
lest we, their loved ones, aye be lost to sight.

90

“This, following, saith: ‘O son! I ever held
coolth of my sorrows and the sweet relief
of mine already weary way-worn eld
so soon to sink in glooms of need and grief;
why leave me thus to want and woe compel’d?
Why fly my love, fond child? whose days so brief
shall set in darkness, and in briny grave
shalt feed the fishes of the greedy wave.

91

“That, with loosed locks: ‘O douce and dearest spouse,
lacking whose love Love willeth not I live;
why risk, when daring Ocean’s wrath to rouse,
thy life, my life which is not thine to give?
How canst forget our fond fair marriage-vows?
Why face the waves a homeless fugitive?
Our love, our vain content shall nought avail
thrown to the breezes as they blow the sail?’

92

“With such and sim’ilar words that spake the tongue
of love and human nature’s yearning woe,
followed our seaward path both old and young,
life’s two extremes by Time made weak and slow.
Sad Echo wailèd the near wolds among,
as though hard hills were movèd grief to show;
And tears the snowy shore suchwise bedew’d,
drops rivall’d sands in equal multitude.

93

“Of us the Company, ne’er raising eye
on wife or mother, marcht in such a state,
we feared our hearts fall faint, and fain we fly
our fixt resolves, repenting all too late:
Thus I determined straight aboard to hie,
sans ‘Fare-thee-wells’ by custom consecrate;
which, though they be dear love’s own lovely way,
redouble grief to those who go or stay.

94

“But now an agèd Sire of reverend mien,[107]
upon the foreshore throngèd by the crowd,
with eyne fast fixt upon our forms was seen,
and discontented thrice his brow he bow’d:
His deep-toned accents raising somewhat keen,
that we from shipboard hear him speak aloud,
with lore by long experience only grown,
thus from his time-taught breast he made his moan:—

95

“ ‘Oh craving of Command! Oh vain Desire!
of vainest van’ity man miscalleth Fame!
Oh fraud’ulent gust, so easy fanned to fire
by breath of vulgar, aping Honour’s name!
What just and dreadful judgment deals thine ire,
to seely souls who overlove thy claim!
What deaths, what direful risks, what agonies
wherewith thou guerd’onest them, thy fitting prize!

96

“ ‘Thou dour disturber of man’s sprite and life,
fount of backsliding and adultery,
sagacious waster, and consummate thief
of subjects, kingdoms, treasure, empery:
They hail thee noble, and they hail thee chief,
though digne of all indignities thou be;
they call thee Fame and Glory sovereign,
words, words, the heart of silly herd to gain!

97

“ ‘What new disaster dost thou here design?
What horror for our realm and race invent?
What unheard dangers or what deaths condign,
veiled by some name that soundeth excellent?
What bribe of gorgeous reign, and golden mine,
whose ready offer is so rarely meant?
What Fame hast promised them? what pride of story?
What palms? what triumphs? what victorious glory?

98

“ ‘But oh! race ’gendered by his sin insane,
whom disobedience of the high command,
not only chasèd from the heav’enly reign,
and doomed to distant and exilèd land;
but, eke, from other state too blest for men
where Peace with Innocence fared hand in hand,
that olden golden Age, his victims hurl’d
into an iron and an armèd world:

99

“ ‘Since by this gustful Van’ity led astray,
lighter thou makest man’s light fantasy;
since his brute fierceness and his lust of prey
bear honoured names of Strength and Valiancy;
since thou wilt price and prize, in wildest way,
despisal of man’s life, which aye should be
esteemed of mortals, nay, held doubly dear,
when He who gave it, gave it up with fear:

100

“ ‘Neighbours thee not the hateful Ishmaelite,
with whom abundant strife shalt ever hold?
Follows he not th’ Arabian’s law unright,
an thou wouldst fight to fill of Christ the fold?
A thousand cities, regions infinite,
are they not his, an cov’etest earth and gold?
Is he not strong in warfare, high in name,
if Honour be, not greed of gain, thine aim?

101

“ ‘Dost leave the foeman breeding at thy gate
who wendest foreign far-off fone to seek;
whereby this antique realm lies desolate;
whose strength, o’erstretchèd, waxeth ruinous weak?
Seekest thou dark and dubious chance of fate,
who hearest Fame with honey’d accents speak,
lauding thy lot, and hailing thee seignior
of Inde, Perse, Arab and Aethiopia-shore?

102

“ ‘Oh, curst the Mortal, who the first was found
teaching the tree to wear the flowing sheet!
worthy th’ eternal pains of the Profound,
if just that justest law I hold and greet.
Ne’er may man’s judgment lofty and renown’d,
nor genius rare, nor harp sonorous sweet,
requite such gift with mem’ory, honour, fame;
perish thy glory, perish e’en thy name!

103

“ ‘Iápetus’ daring Son from Heaven brought
the fire he added human breast to bless;
fire, that inflamed to wars a world distraught,
with death and eke disgrace: (ah, sad distress!)
How better far for us and ours hadst wrought
Prometheus! and with loss of life the less;
had thy famed Statue never felt the fire
of great designs that ’gender great desire!

104

“ ‘Ne’er had the Stripling, miserably brave,
’tempted his Sire’s high car, nor empty Air
the mighty Mason and his boy, who gave
names which the Sea-gulf and the River bear.
No fierce emprize and fell, by land and wave,
through fire, steel, water, wind, frost, heat, to fare,
wherein the human race loves not to range.
Sorrowful sort! condition strangest strange!’

Canto V

Vasco da Gama pursueth the recital of his voyage, and describeth to the King of Melinde his departure from Lisbon; the divers lands whereat they touched, and the peoples whom they saw as far as the Cape of Good Hope: The chance of Fernam Velloso: The tale of the giant Adamastor: Continuation of the voyage to Melinde, where the discourse endeth; peace and true friendship being established between the Gama and that King.

The famèd Gama tells the forceful King (1–30)
His long-drawn voyage, and uncertain road;
What couthless nations in hot Africk spring,
And, eke, Fernam Velloso’s hardihood: (31–36)
How Adamastor, Giant menacing (37–60)
They saw, who claimed to be of Terra’s brood;
And other things that happened till was found (61–end)
Haven of rest, with comfort safe and sound.

1

“Such words that agèd Sire of honoured mien
still was exclaiming, as we spread the wing
to catch the sea-breath gentle and serene,
and from the well-known Port went sorrowing:
After the manner of far-faring men,
when loosed the sail we garred the welkin ring
crying ‘Boon Voyage!’ whereupon the breeze
made every trunk glide off with ’customed ease.

2

“ ’Twas in the season when th’ Eternal Light
entered the Beast that workt Nemaea’s woe;[108]
and rolled our Earth, consumed by Time’s long flight,
in her sixth epoch, feeble, cold and slow:
Now, in the wonted way, had met her sight
the suns that fourteen hundred courses show,
with seven and ninety more, wherein she ran,
as o’er the seas th’ Armada’s course began.

3

“Slow, ever slower, banisht from our eyne,
vanisht our native hills astern remaining:
Remained dear Tagus, and the breezy line
of Cintran peaks, long, long, our gaze detaining:
Remainèd eke in that dear country mine
our hearts with pangs of mem’ory ever paining:
Till, when all veilèd sank in darkling air,
naught but the welkin and the wave was there.

4

“Thus fared we opening those wastes of tide,
no generation openèd before;
sighting new islands and new airs we hied,
which gen’erous Henry had the heart t’ explore:
Past Mauritanian hills and homes we plied,
the realm Antaeus ruled in times of yore,
leaving to larboard; on our dexter hand
lay nothing surer than suspected land.[109]

5

“Hard by the great Madeiran Isle we past,
whose wealth of woodland won her chryssome name;
where first our people did their fortunes cast,
for name more famous than for classick fame:
But not the least, although ’twas found the last,
the smiles of Venus shall this Island claim:
Nay, an ’twere hers, scant cause it had to fear a
Cnidos or Cyprus, Paphos or Cythéra.

6

“We left Massylia’s seaboard, sterile waste,
where Azenéguan[110] herds their cattle feed;
a folk that never soft sweet waters taste,
nor doth the meadow-math suffice their need;
a land no luscious fruit’ery ever graced,
where birds spoil iron in their maws of greed,
a soil where nought save horrid Want abounds,
parting the Berber’s from the Blackmoor’s grounds.

7

“We past the limit where, his southing done,
Sol guides his chariot t’oward his northern goal;
where lie the Races whence Clyméné’s son
the clear bright colour of the daylight stole;
Here laving strangest peoples loves to run
black Sanagá in tropick summer cool;
where th’ Arsenarium Cape its name hath lost,
yclept Cape Verd by us that keep the coast.

8

“Now past Canaria’s archipelago—
‘Fortunate Isles’ of olden mariners these—
the waves that play around the Maids we plow
of agèd Hesper, hight Hesperides:[111]
Lands ever new, whose wonders greater grow
upon the sight, uprose our eyne to please:
Then with a prosp’rous wind we took the port,
to take provision of the wonted sort.

9

“Now at his Island was the harbour tane,
that warrior Sanct ‘Iago’s name did take;
a Saint who often holp the sons of Spain
brave slaught’ering of the Moorish man to make.
Hence while a favouring Boreas fanned the Main,
once more we sped to cut the vasty lake
of briny Ocean, while beneath the wave
settled the shore that sweet refreshment gave.

10

“Compast our courses thence the greater part
of Africk, eastward left her continent:
The province Joloff which, disposed athwart,
departs in tribes the Negro ’habitant;
mighty Mandinga-land by whose good art
the rich and lucid ore for us is sent,
which curvèd Gámbia’s wealth of waters drinketh
ere in Atlantis’ breadth his current sinketh:

11

“We past the Dorcades,[112] those isles assign’d
of the Weird Sisters erst the home to be,
who born of several vision reft and blind,
made single eye-ball serve for all the three:
Thou, only thou, whose crispy locks entwin’d
frore Neptune fired’st in his realm, the sea,
than ev’ery foulest monster fouler still
the burning sand with viper-brood didst fill.

12

“In fine with pointed Prow t’oward Austral shore[113]
across the vastest Guinea Gulf we stray’d,
leaving the rugged Range where Lyons roar
and Cape of Palmas called from palmy shade:
The Rio Grande,[114] where the thund’erous Bore
roars on our noted coasts, we left and made
that goodly Island named from him who tried
to thrust his finger in the God-man’s side.[115]

13

“There the broad shores of Congo kingdom show,
whilom by us convert to faith of Christ,
where long Zaïré’s deep clear waters flow,
River by men of old unseen, unwist:
And now in fine the wide-spread seas I plow,
far from Callisto’s well-known Pole, and list
to pass the torrid heats beneath the Line,
which doth the centre of our Sphere define.

14

“And now our vision had afront descried,
there in the new half-heav’en a meteor new,
unseen by other men, who or denied,
or held it doubtful, an ’twere false or true:
We saw the Firm’ament’s darker, duller side,
aye scant of stellar light where stars be few,
and the fixt Pole where man may not agree
if other land begin, or end the sea.

15

“Thus passing forward we the regions gain,
where twice Apollo’s yearly passage lies,
twin winters making, and of summers twain,
while he from Pole to Pole alternate flies:
Through calms and storms, caprices of the Main,
of angry Aeolus sea-sent tyrannies,
we saw the Bears, despite of Juno, lave
their tardy bodies in the boreal wave.

16

“To tell the many dangers of the deep,
sea-changes landsman never apprehendeth,
sudden Tornados, storms the seas that sweep,
Levens, whose fire the depths of air accendeth;
black nights when Heav’en in rain-flood seems to weep,
and Thunders bellowing till the welkin rendeth,
were but lost labour, and would do me wrong,
e’en were I dower’d with an iron tongue.

17

“Portents I witness’d, which rude mariners
by long experience wont their lore to try,
vouch for veracious, while each one avers
things must be truthful when they meet his eye:
These the sound judgment of the Sage prefers;—
or taught by Science or pure Wits to ’spy
the hidden secrets which in Nature brood—
to judge misfacts, or facts mis-understood.

18

“I saw, and clearly saw, the living Light,[116]
which sailor-people hold their Patron-saint,
in times of trouble and the winds’ rude fight,
and sable orcan when man’s heart is faint.
Nor less to one and all ’twas exquisite
marvel, surpassing power of wonderment,
to see the sea-based clouds, with bulky shaft,
upheaving Ocean’s depth with sucking draught.

19

“Certès I saw it (nor can I presume
my sight deceivèd me) as high it grew,
an airy vapourlet, a subtle fume
which, caught by windy currents, whirling flew:
Thence tow’ering tall to circumpolar gloom
a Tube appeared so thin, so faint of hue,
that man’s unaidèd sight could hardly see it:
Yet of some cloudy substance seemed to be it.

20

“Little by little growing high in air,
with bigger girth than biggest mast it loomèd;
here slim its middle, broad its bosom, where
great gulps of water were in floods enwombèd:
The wave of ev’ery Wave it seemed to share;
while gathered vapours o’er its summit gloomèd;
increasing ever more, and overchargèd
as the huge water-load its bulk enlargèd.

21

“E’en as a ruddy Leech sometimes is seen
fixt on the lips of beeve (that careless stood
to drink on frigid fountain’s hem of green),
slaking her fire of thirst with alien blood:
Sucking, she rounds her form with hunger lean;
and swills and swells till full of gory food:
Thus the grand column greater volume gaineth
itself, and heavier weight of cloud sustaineth.

22

“But, when ’twas wholly filled, and fully fed,
withdrawn the footing planted on the Main,
athwart the welkin pouring floods it fled,
with water bathing ’jacent watery plain;
and all the waves it suckt in waves it shed;
wherein no salty savour mote remain.
Now let our Sages deft in Script expose
what mighty secrets these which Nature shows.

23

“Had the Philosophers, who fared of eld
so far the Wonders of the World to find,
the Miracles which I beheld, beheld;
the canvas spreading to such divers wind;
what many weighty volumes had they fill’d!
what pow’er to Stars and Signs had they assign’d!
what growth to knowledge! what rare qualities!
and all the purest Truth that scorneth lies.

24

“Five times the Planet, which maintains her place
in the first sky, her swifter course had made,[117]
now showing half and then her full of face,
while over Ocean our Armada sped:
When poised on topmost yard, in giddy space,
‘Land!’ shouts a lynx-eyed sailor, ‘land ahead!’
Hurry the crews on deck in huge delight
and over Orient sky-rim strain their sight.

25

“In misty manner ’gan their shapes to show
the highland-range attracting all our eyes;
the pond’erous anchors stood we prompt to throw,
and furl the canvas which now useless lies:
And that with surer knowledge mote we know
the parts so distant which before us rise,
with Astrolábos, novel instrument,
which safe and subtle judgment did invent:

26

“We landed, lost no time, on long and wide
Bight,[118] and the seamen scattered ’bout the shore,
to see what curious things be there descried,
where none descried or ever trod before:
But with my Pilots I retired aside
on farther sands, our landfall to explore;
and lief the solar altitude would span,
and map the painted world in chart and plan.

27

“Here had our wand’ering course outrun, we found,
of Semi-capran Fish the final goal,[119]
standing atween him and the gelid round,
Earth’s austral portion, the more secret Pole.
Sudden I see my crew a man surround,
complexion’d sooty as the charrèd coal,
tane as he hied him far from home to take
combs of rich honey from the hilly brake.

28

“He comes with troubled gest and gait, as though
he ne’er had found him in such fell extreme;
nor he our speech, nor we his jargon know,
a salvage worse than brutal Polypheme:
Of the fine fleecy store to him I show
the Colchos-treasure, gentle ore supreme,
the virgin silver, spices rich and rare,
yet seemed the Sylvan nought for these to care.

29

“Then bade I baser things be brought to his view,
bunches of glassy beads transparent bright,
of little tinkling falcon-bells a few,
a cap of cramoisie that glads the sight.
By signs and signals then I saw and knew,
in such cheap trash he takes a child’s delight:
I bid them loose him with his treasures all,
when off he hurries for the nearest kraal.

30

“His friends and neighbours on the following day,
all mother-nude, with night-entinctur’d skin,
adown their asp’erous hillocks fand their way,
làrgesse and gifts their mate had won, to win:
In crowds they gather’d and so tame were they,
the show of softness bred much daring in
Fernam Velloso’s brain to see the land,
and thread the bushes with the barbarous band.

31

“Now doth Velloso on his arm rely
and, being arr’ogant, weens to wend secure;
but when already overtime goes by
wherein no sign of good I can procure;
standing with face upturned in hope to ’spy
the bold Adv’enturer, lo! adown the dure
hillocks appears he, making for the shore,
with more of hurry than he showed before.

32

“Coelho’s galley lightly rowed for land
to take him off, but ere the shore she made
a burly Blackmoor cast a bully hand
on him, for fear their prisoner evade:
Others and others coming, soon the band
grappleth Velloso, who finds none to aid;
I haste, our gallant oarsmen strenuous working,
when shows a Negro flock[120] in ambush lurking.

33

“Now from the clashing cloud a rattling rain
of shafts and stones began on us to pour,
nor did they hurtle through the lift in vain,
for thence my leg this hurt of arrow bore.
But we, like men with causes to complain,
send such thick-woven answer strong and sore
that from their exploit gainèd some, perhaps,
a blush of honours crimson as their caps.

34

“And, saved Velloso from such imm’inent fate,
fast to the Squadron both the boats retirèd,
seeing the rude intent and ugly hate
of brutes by bestial rage and malice firèd;
from whom no better tidings could we ’wait
anent that India-land, the dear-desirèd,
save it lay far, far, far, the fellows said:—
Once more the canvas to the breeze I spread.

35

“Then to Velloso quoth a mate in jest
(while all with meaning smile the jibe attend),
‘Holá, Velloso! sure that hilly crest
is hard to climb as easy to descend.’
‘Yea, true!’ the daring volunteer confest;
‘but when so many curs afar I ken’d
packing, I hurried, for I ’gan to doubt me
ill-luck might catch you were ye there without me.’

36

“He then recounted how, when duly made
that wooded Mount, the blacks of whom I speak,
his further travel o’er the land forbade
threat’ening unless he turn death-wrong to wreak:
Then, straight returning, ambuscade they laid,
that we when landing a lost mate to seek,
might straight be banisht to the Reign obscure,
that at more leisure they the loot secure.

37

“But now five other suns had come and gone,
since from our landfall went we forth to plow
seas to the seaman still unseen, unknown,
while from astern the breezes favouring blow;
when, as a night closed in, all careless strown
the Crew kept watch upon the cutting Prow,
deep’ening the welkin’s darkling hues, a cloud
sails high o’erhead, and seems the sky to shroud.

38

“It came so chargèd with such tem’erous stride
in every falt’ering heart blank fear it bred:
Roars from afar and raves the sombre tide
as though vain thunder’ing on some rocky head:
‘Almighty Pow’r, o’er worlds sublime!’ I cried,
‘what threat from Heaven, or what secret dread,
shall now this climate and this sea deform,
what greater horror than the natural storm?’

39

“These words I ended not, when saw we rise
a Shape in air, enormous, sore the view o’it;
a Form disformèd of a giant size;
frownèd its face; the long beard squalid grew o’it;
its mien dire menacing; its cavern’d eyes
glared ghastly ’mid the mouldy muddy hue o’it;
stainèd a clayey load its crispy hair
and coal-black lips its yellow tusks lay bare.

40

“So vast its eerie members, well I can
assure thee, all the double deemed to sight
of Rhodes’ Colossus, whose inord’inate span
one of the world’s Seven Wonders once was hight.
But when its gross and horrent tones began
to sound as surged from Ocean’s deepest night:
ah! crept the flesh, and stood the hair of me
and all, that gruesome Thing to hear and see.

41

“ ‘O rasher, bolder Race:’—’twas thus it spoke—
‘than all whose daring deeds have tempted Fate;
thou, whom no labours tame nor war’s fell stroke,
nor rest wilt grant on human toils to ’wait:
Since these forbidden bounds by thee are broke
who durst my Virgin Seas to violate,
which long I guardèd, where I ne’er allow
plowing to foreign or to native prow:

42

“ ‘Since the dark secrets com’st thou here to ’spy
of Nature and her humid element,
which from Man’s highest lore deep hidden lie,
on noble or immortal mission sent;
from me the Terrors which ye dare defy
hear now, the sequence of thy rash intent,
o’er ev’ery largest Sea, o’er ev’ery Land
which still thy cruel conquest shall command.

43

“ ‘This know, what ships shall sail my waters o’er
and brave, as brav’est thou me, to work my worst;
to them assurèd foe shall prove my shore,
where blow the storm-winds, and the tempests burst:
Hear! the first Squadron[121] that shall dare explore
and through my restless waves shall cleave the first,
such improvisèd chastisement shall see,
more than all dangers shall the damage be.

44

“ ‘An Hope deceive not, here I hope to deal
consummate vengeance on th’ Explorer’s head;[122]
nor he the latest shall my fury feel
by pertinacious confidence ybred;
nay, ye shall ev’ery year see many a keel
(if me my judgment here hath not misled)
such wrecks endure, shall see such fate befall,
that Death shall seem the lightest ill of all.

45

“ ‘And to the first illustrious Leader[123] whom
Fame’s favour raiseth till he touch the skies,
I will give novel and eternal tomb,
by the dark sentence of a God all-wise:
Here of hard Turkish fleet that dree’d his doom,
he shall depose the prideful prosp’erous prize;
here shall at length my wrath and wrack surpass a
Quíloa in ruins and a rent Mombasah.

46

“ ‘Shall come Another, eke of honour’d fame,[124]
a Knight of loving heart and liberal hand,
and he shall bring his dainty darling Dame,
Love’s choicest treasure bound by Hymen’s band:
Ah, sore the sorrow, dark the day when came
the pair to this my hard and hateful land,
condemn’d from cruel wreck their lives to save
and, suffer’ed toils untold, to find a grave.

47

“ ‘Shall see slow starving die their children dear,
sweet pledges bred of love, in fond love born;
shall see the Caffres, greedy race and fere,
strip the fair Ladye of her raiment torn:
Shall see those limbs, as crystal light and clear,
by suns, and frosts, and winds, and weather worn,
when cease to tread, o’er long drawn miles, the heat
of sandy waste those delicatest feet.

48

“And, more, shall see their eyne, whom Fate shall spare
from ills so dreadful, from so dire a blow,
the two sad lovers left in mis’ery, where
implac’able thorns and terrible thickets glow:
There, when the stones wax soft at their despair,
shown by their ceaseless woe, sigh, groan, tear, throe,
in a last strained embrace their souls exhale
from out the fairest, fondest, saddest jail.”

49

“The fearful Monster would more ills unfold,
our doom disclosing, when aloud cried I:—
‘Who art thou, whose immense stupendous mould,
pardie, is mighty miracle to mine eye?’
His lips and dingy orbs he wreathed and roll’d,
and with a sudden frightful wailing cry,
in slow and bitter accents he replied
as though the question probed and galled his pride:

50

“ ‘I am that hidden mighty Head of Land,
the Cape of Tempests fitly named by you,
which Ptol’emy, Mela, Strabo never fand,
nor Pliny dreamt of, nor old Sages knew:
Here in South Ocean end I Africk strand,
where my unviewèd Point ye come to view,
which to the far Antarctick Pole extendeth;
such he your daring rashness dire offendeth.

51

“ ‘Encelados, and Terra’s Titan brood,
Aegaeon and the Centiman, the line
of me, who Adamástor hight, withstood
the hand that hurleth Vulcan’s bolt divine:
Hill upon hill to pile was not my mood;
to conquer Ocean-waves was my design;
I went to seek, as Captain of the Main,
the fleet of Neptune which I sought in vain.

52

“ ‘For Peleus’ high-born spouse my burning love
lurèd me rashly to such rude emprize;
the belles of heaven ne’er my breast could move
mine Ocean-Empress filled my yearning eyes:
One day I saw her with the Nereids rove,
all bare and beauteous, ’neath the summer skies:
and in such manner she bewitcht my will
no other feeling can my bosom fill.

53

“ ‘But as my Ladye’s grace I could not gain
for being homely, huge of form and face,
I sware by forceful rape my want t’ obtain
and so to Doris I disclosed my case:
In dread she told her child my loving pain
when modest Thetis, with her merry grace,
replied:—‘What Nymph can boast, whate’er her charms,
the strength to wrestle in a Giant’s arms?

54

“ ‘Algates, that Ocean may once more be free
from this sad Warfare, I some mode will find,
to gar mine honour with his suit agree;’
thus was the message to mine ear consign’d.
I, who no treach’erous snare in aught could see
(for lovers’ blindness is exceeding blind)
felt with a buoyant hope my bosom bound,
and hopes of passion by possession crown’d.

55

“ ‘Love madden’d, moonstruck, now I fled the war,
and kindly Doris named the trysting-night;
at length my lovely love I saw appear,
my winsome Thetis, in her robeless white:
Like one possest I hurried from afar
opeing mine arms to clasp the life and sprite
of this my body, and hot kisses rain
upon her cheeks, her locks, her glorious eyne.

56

“ ‘Ah! how it irks to tell my sad disgrace!
thinking my lover in these arms to hold,
mine arms a rugged Mountain did embrace,
yclad with bramble bush, a horrid wold:
Before this rock, upstanding face to face,
which for that Angel front I did enfold,
no more was I a Man, no! lorn and lone
a rock, a stone, I stood before a stone.

57

“ ‘Oh Nymph! the loveliest born that bare the Main,
alb’eit my presence ne’er by thee was sought,
how could my poor delusion cause thee pain?
Why not be mountain, cloud, rock, vision, nought?
Raging I wandered forth well-nigh insane
for yearning grief with foul dishonour fraught,
to seek another world, where none could see
my trickling tears, and scoff at them and me.

58

“ ‘Meanwhile my brethren, who the conquest lost,
crusht in extremest conquer’d mis’ery pinèd;
whom, for more surety, that vain-glorious host
of upstart Gods ’neath various Mounts consignèd:
And, as Immortals scoff at mortal boast,
I, to my sorrows in no wise resignèd,
felt Fate, mine awful foe, begin to shape
a dreadful vengeance for my daring rape.

59

“ ‘My flesh slow hardens into solid earth,
to rocks and horrid crags enstone my bones;
these limbs thou seest and this mighty girth,
extend where desert Ocean raves and moans:
In fine, the giant-stature of my birth
to this far Headland sprent with rocks and stones
the Gods debased; and doubling all my woes,
round me white, winsome, watery Thetis flows.’

60

“Thus parlied he; and with appalling cry,
from out our sight the gruesome Monster died;
the black cloud melted, and arose on high
sonorous thunders rollèd by the tide.
To th’ Angel-choirs with hands upraisèd, I—
invisible Controls so long our guide—
prayed God in pity would those Ills withhold,
by Adamástor for our Race foretold.

61

“Now Pyroeis and Phlegon ’gan appear
with th’ other pair that hale the radiant wain,
when the tall heights of Table Mount we spere,
which from the mighty Giant form hath tane:
Standing along now easting shores we steer,
and cleave the waters of the Lévant main,
the coast-line hugging with a northing Prow,
and sight a second landfall o’er the bow.[125]

62

“The native owners of this other land,
the burnisht livery of Aethiops wore,
yet was their bearing more humane and bland,
than those who so mistreated us before.
With dance and joyous feasts, a merry band
approacht us tripping on the sandy shore,
bringing their Women and fat herds that grace
the pastures, gentle kine of high-bred race.

63

“The bronzèd Women, scorcht by burning clime,
astraddle rode the slow-paced gentle Steer,
beasts which their owners hold of beeves the prime,
better than any of the herds they rear:
Pastoral canticles, or prose, or rhyme,
concerted in their mother-tongue we hear;
and to the rustick reed sweet tunes they teach,
as Tit’yrus chaunted ’neath his spreading beech.

64

“These, who seemed glad to see the guest abide
amid them, greeted us with friendly mood,
and many a fatted fowl and sheep supplied,
their goods exchanging for the things deemed good:
But though my comrades tried, they vainly tried,
for not a word in fine was understood
that of our search a signal might convey:—
Anchor I weighèd, and I sailed away.

65

“Now here in mighty gyre our flight had flown
round Blackmoor Africk shore; and now regainèd
our Prores the torrid heat of Middle Zone,
while Pole Antarctick far in rear remainèd:
We left astern an Islet[126] first made known
by the first Squadron whose long toils attainèd
the Cape of Tempests; and, that Islet found,
ended her voyage at its bourne and bound.

66

“Thence drave we, cutting for a length of days—
where storms and sadd’ening calms alternate range—
undreamèd Oceans and unpathèd ways,
our sole conductor Hope in toils so strange:
Long time we struggled with the sea’s wild maze,
till, as its general Law is changeless Change,
we met a current[127] with such speed that sped,
against the flow ’twas hard to forge ahead.

67

“Of this prevailing flood the puissant force,
which to the southward our Armada hove,
such set opposèd to our northing course,
the winds to waft us onwards vainly strove:
Till Notus fashed to find us fare the worse,
(it seems) in struggle with the drift that drove,
enforced his blasts, and with such choler blew
maugre the mighty current on we drew.

68

“Reducèd Sol that famed and sacred Day,
wherein three Kings in Orient region crown’d,
a King came seeking who belittled lay,
a King in whom three Kings in One are bound:
That morn to other hythe we made our way
finding the peoples that before we found,
by a broad River, and we gave it name
from the high hol’iday when to port we came.[128]

69

“Sweet food we barter’d from their scanty store,
sweet water from their stream; but natheless here
gained we no tidings of that Indian shore,
from men to us that almost dumblings were.
See now, O King! what distant regions o’er
of Earth we wandered, peoples rude and fere,
nor news nor signal had our labours earnèd
of the fair East for which our spirits yearnèd.

70

“Imagine, prithee, what a piteous state
must have been ours when all save life was gone,
by hunger broken and the storm’s wild hate,
and curst by novel climes and seas unknown:
Our hearts despaired of Hope deferred so late,
till dull Despair had marked us for her own;
toiling beneath those strange unnat’ural skies—
our northern nature’s fellest enemies.

71

“And now decayed and damaged waxt our food,
sore damaging the wasted frame of man,
without one comfort, sans one gleam of good,
not e’en Hope’s flatt’ering tale nor Fancy vain:
Dost think that Sailor of the sturdiest mood,
or any Soldier save the Lusitan,
perchance, had loyalty so long preservèd
both for his King and for the Chief he servèd?

72

“Dost think, the wretches had not mutinied
against the Head who with their mood had striven,
parforce becoming Pyrats, turned aside
from duty, by despair, want, hunger driven?
In very sooth these men were sorely tried,
since from their hearts ne moil ne toil hath driven
Portingall-excellence, abounding still
in leal valour and obedient will.

73

“Leaving in fine that Port of fair sweet flood,
and, dight once more to cut the salty spray;
off from the coast-line for a spell we stood,
till deep blue water ’neath our kelsons lay;
for frigid Notus, in his fainty mood,
was fain to drive us leewards to the Bay
made in that quarter by the crookèd shore,
whence rich Sofála sendeth golden ore.

74

“This Sea-bight passing far, the nimble helm,
by men to saintly Nicholas assignèd,
where roaring Ocean raves on Terra’s realm,
this and that vessel’s prore eftsoons inclinèd:
And now from hearts which hopes and fears o’erwhelm,
hearts in such faith t’ a fragile plank resignèd,
as hope grew hopeless, esperance despair,
good sudden tidings banisht cark and care.

75

“And thus it happed, as near the shore we went
where beach and valley lay in clearest view,
a stream whose course in ocean there was spent,[129]
showèd of sails that came and went a few.
Good sooth, to greatest joyaunce all gave vent,
when first we sighted mariners who knew
mariner-practice; for we here were bound
to find some tidings which, indeed, we found.

76

“All Aethiopians are, yet ’twould appear,
they held communion with men better bred:
Some words of Arab parlance here we hear
imported sounds their mother-speech amid:
A flimsy wrapper of tree-wool they wear
a-twisted tight about each kinky head;
while other pieces dipt in azure tinct,
are round their middles and their shame precinct.

77

“In Arab language, which they little know,
but which Fernam Martins well comprehendeth,
ships great as ours, they say, scud to and fro
piercing the waters with the beak that rendeth:
But there where Phoebus leaps in air, they go
whither the broad’ening coast to south extendeth,
then from south sunwards;[130] and a Land is there
of folk like us and like the daylight fair.

78

“Here was each bosom with rare gladness cheerèd
by the good people, and their news much more:
From all the signals in this stream appearèd,
‘Stream of Good Signals’ christened we the shore:
A marble column on this coast we rearèd
whereof, to mark such spots, a few we bore;
its name that lovely Angel-youth supplied[131]
who did Thobias to Gabáël guide.

79

“Of shells and oysters, and the weedy load,
the noisome offspring of the Main profound,
we cleansed our kelsons which the long sea-road
brought to careening cloggèd and immund:
Our blameless Aethiops, who not far abode,
with pleasing jocund proffers flockt around
supplying maintenance we mainly sought,
pure of all leasing, free from feigning thought.

80

“Yet from our esp’erance great, our hopes immense
bred by this seaboard, was not pure and true
the joy we joyed; nay, cruel recompense
dealt us Rhamnúsia, sorrows strange and new.
Thus smiling Heav’en mixt favours doth dispense;
in such condition dark and dure man drew
the breath of Life; and, while all Ills endure,
Good changeth often, Good is never sure.

81

“And ’twas that sickness of a sore disgust,[132]
the worst I ever witness’d, came and stole
the lives of many; and far alien dust
buried for aye their bones in saddest dole.
Who but eye-witness e’er my words could trust?
of such disform and dreadful manner swole
the mouth and gums, that grew proud flesh in foyson
till gangrene seemèd all the blood to poyson:

82

“Gangrene that carried foul and fulsome taint,
spreading infection through the neighb’ouring air:
No cunning Leach aboard our navy went,
much less a subtle Chirurgeon was there;
but some whose knowledge of the craft was faint
strove as they could the poisoned part to pare,
as though ’twere dead; and here they did aright;—
all were Death’s victims who had caught the blight.

83

“At last in tangled brake and unknown ground,
our true companions lost for aye, we leave,
who ’mid such weary ways, such dreary round,
such dread adventures aidance ever gave.
How easy for man’s bones a grave is found!
Earth’s any wrinkle, Ocean’s any wave.
whereso the long home be, abroad, at home,
for ev’ery Hero’s corse may lend a tomb.

84

“When from that Haven we resumed our way
while brighter hopes with darker hearts combine’d,
we opèd Ocean where the down coast lay,
expecting surer signal e’er to find:
At last we rode in rude Mozámbic Bay,
of whose vile leasing, and whose villain kind
thou must have knowledge; and the foul deceit
wherewith Mombásah would her guests defeat.

85

“Until safe anchored in thy harbour, rife
with all the gracious guest-rites that bestow
health on the living, on the dying life,
God in His pity pleased the way to show:
Here rest, here sweet repose from grief, toil, strife,
new Peace appeasing ev’ry want and woe
thou gavest us: Now, if hast heard me well
told is the tale thou badest me to tell.

86

“Judge then, O King! an over Earth e’er went
men who would ’tempt such paths of risk and dread?
Dost deem Aeneas, or e’en eloquent
Ulysses, fared so far this Earth to tread?
Did any dare to see the Sea’s extent
howe’er the Muse their Gestes hath sung or said,
as I by force of will and skill have seen
and still shall see; or e’en the eighth, I ween?

87

“This, who so deeply drank of Fount Aonian,
o’er whom contend in conquest peregrine
Rhodes, Ios, Smyrna, with the Colophonian
Athens and Argos and the Salamine:
And that, the lustre of the land Ausonian,
whose voice altis’onous and whose lyre divine
his native Mincius hearing, sinks to sleep,
while Tyber’s waves with pride and pleasure leap:

88

“Sing, laud and write they both in wild extremes
of these their Demigods, and prowess vaunt
on fabled Magians, Circes, Polyphemes,
and Sirens lulling with the sleepy chaunt:
Send them to plow with oar and sail the streams
of Cicons; on th’ oblivious lands descant
where slumb’erous Lotus-eaters dazed and died;
e’en be their Pilot whelmed in Ocean-tide:

89

“Storms let them loosen from the Bags of Wind,
create Calypsos captivate by love;
make Harpies’ touch contam’inate all they find,
and in sad Hades make their Heroes rove;
however much, o’er much, they have refine’d
such fabled tales, which Poet’s fancy prove,
the simple naked truth my story telleth
all their grandiloquence of writ excelleth.”

90

Fast on our Captain’s facund lips depends
as drunk with wonder, all that soul-wrapt crowd;
until at length his travel-story ends;
his tale that told of noble deeds and proud.
The high-conceiv’ed intent the King commends
of Kings to not’able feats of warfare vow’d:
Their Lieges’ old and val’orous strain extols,
their loyal spirits and their noble souls.

91

Th’ admiring audience to recount are fain
each case, as each one best could understand:
None from the hardy Folk could turn their eyne
who by such long-drawn ways the waves had span’d.
Now, as the Delian youth turns round the rein
Lampetia’s brother held with feeble hand,
and in the Thetian arms way-weary falls;
the King hies sea-borne to his royal halls.

92

How pleasant sound the praise and well-won glory
of man’s own exploits as man hears them chime!
for noble travail, actions digne of story,
that dim or equal those of passèd Time.
Envy of famous feats untransitory
hath ’gendered thousand thousand deeds sublime:
The Brave who loves to tread in Valour’s ways
pants for the pleasure of his fellows’ praise.

93

Achilles’ glorious feats could not so ’flame,
nor Alexander’s soul to fight inspirèd,
as he who sang in numbered verse his name;
such praise, such honour most his soul desirèd.
Nought but the trophies of Miltiades’ fame
could rouse Themistocles with envy firèd;
who owned his highest joy, his best delight,
came from the voices which his feats recite.

94

Vasco da Gama striveth hard to prove
that these old travels in world-song resounding
merit not glory nor men’s hearts may move
like his sore travails Heav’en and Earth astounding.
Yes! but that Hero, whose esteem and love
crownèd with praise, prize, honours, gifts abounding
the Lyre of Mantua, taught her Bard to chaunt
Aeneas’ name, and Rome’s high glories vaunt.

95

Scipios and Caesars giveth Lusia-land,
gives Alexanders and Augusti gives;
but she withal may not the gifts command
whose want rears rough and ready working-lives:
Octavius, prest by Fortune’s heaviest hand,
with compt and learned verse her wrong survives.
Nor, certès, Fulvia shall this truth deny,
Gláphyra’s[133] wit entrapt her Anthony.

96

Goes Caesar subjugating gen’eral France,
yet worked his arms to Science no offence;
this hand the Pen compelling, that the Lance
he vied with Cicero’s gift of eloquence:
What most doth Scipio’s name and fame enhance
is of the Com’edy deep experience:
What Homer wrote that Alexander read,
we know, whose roll ne’er left his couch’s head.

97

In fine, the nations own no Lord of Men
that lackt a cultured learnèd fantasy,
of Grecian, Latian, or barbarian strain;
only the Lusian lacking it we see.
Not without shame I say so, but ’twere vain
to hope for high triumphant Poesy
till men our Rhymes, our Songs shall lay to heart;
for minds Art-ign’orant aye look down on Art.

98

For this, and not for Nature’s fault, be sure
Virgil nor Homer rise to strike the lyre;
nor shall rise ever, an this mode endure,
pious Aeneas or Achilles dire.
But—worst of all—it maketh man so dour,
austere, rough, frigid to poetic fire;
so rude, so heedless to be known or know,
few heed the want and many will it so.

99

Let grateful Gama to my Muse give grace,
for the great patriot-love that gars her sound
the Lyre for all her Sons, and aye retrace
the name and fame of ways and wars renown’d:
Nor he, nor they who call themselves his race
e’er in Calliope a friend so found,
or from the Tagus-maidens boon could claim,
to leave their golden webs and hymn his name.

100

Because fraternal love and friendly will
that deals to every Lusian Brave his meed
of laud, this thought, these resolutions fill
my gentle Tagides; and this their creed.
Yet ne’er let human bosom cease to thrill
with Hope to dare and do some mighty deed,
since or by these or, haply, other ways,
he ne’er shall forfeit prizes, value, praise.

Canto VII

On the occasion of the famous Discovery of India, a notable and poetic Exhortation is addrest to the Princes of Christendom, arousing them to like Enterprises: Description of the Reign of Malabar wherein lieth the Empire of Calecut, at whose Port the Armada anchoreth: Appeareth the Moor Monsaydé who giveth information to the Gama and eke instructeth him concerning the natives of the land: The Catual, or Governor of Calecut, fareth to see the Fleet.

Anchors, to Calecut safe come, the Fleet; (1–22)
Sent to its puissant King an Envoy goes; (23–27)
Monsaydé comes the Lusian ships to greet, (28–41)
And of the Province telleth all he knows:
The Gama fares the Samori to meet; (42–65)
Grace to the stranger th’ Indic people shows: (66–72)
Then joint the Regent and the Moorman hie (73–end)
Aboard, where many a flag and awning fly.

1

And now th’ Armada near’d the Morning-land,
many so much desirèd to have seen,
Reigns by those Indic currents moated, and
by Gange who dwelleth in the sky terrene.
Up Braves! and at them, an your valiant hand,
to snatch victorious Palms determined bene
Here ends your warfare; here before you lies
the realm of riches and your rightful prize.

2

To you, O race from Lusus sprung! I say,
to whom such puny part of Earth is dole’d
nay, what say I of Earth, but of His sway
who ruleth all the rounded skies enfold?
You, whom ne dangers dure ne dire dismay
from conqu’ering brutal Heathenesse withhold,
but eke no greed of gain may wean from love
of Mother-essence[147] throned the Heavens above.

3

Ye, Portingalls! as forceful as ye’re few,
who e’er disdain to weigh your weakly weight;
ye, who at cost of various deaths be true
the Laws of Life Eternal to dilate:
Cast by the heav’enly lots your lot ye drew,
however poor or mean your mundane state,
great deeds for Holy Christendom to show:
So high, O Christ! exaltest Thou the low!

4

See them, those Germans, stiff-neckt, herd-like horde
who browse the pastures of such wide extent,
to him rebellious who hath Peter’s ward,
choose a new Shepherd, a new Sect invent:
See them absorbed in ugly wars abhor’d
(nor yet with blinded errant ways content!)
fight, not the haught tyrannick Othoman,
but th’ apostolick yoke they fain unspan.

5

See the hard Englander[148] proclaim his right
of that old Sacred City King to be,
where reigns and rules the base-born Ishmaelite
(Honour of Truth so nude who e’er did see!);
’mid Boreal snows he taketh sad delight
to mould new mode of old Christianity:
For those of Christ he bares the ready brand,
not to rethrone Lord Christ in Holy Land.

6

Holds for himself meanwhile a faithless Roy,[149]
Jerus’alem City, the terrestrial;
who holds not holy law, but dares defy
Jerus’alem City, the celestial.
Then what of thee, vile Gaul[150] what need say I?
who wouldst thy vaunting self “Most Christian” call,
not that such title wouldest ward and guard,
but that the name thro’ thee be smircht and mar’d!

7

Thy claim to conquer Christian lands beseems
one who so much and such fair land doth claim?
why seek not Cinyps[151] and the Nilus, streams
which ever hate that ántique Holy Name?
There should they feel of steel the hard extremes,
who would the Church’s truthful song defame:
Of Charles, of Louis,[152] name thou didst inherit
and lands;—why not of justest wars the merit?

8

What shall I say of those who ’mid delights,
which vilest Idlesse bare for manhood’s bane,
spend life and love to waste the gold that blights,
and clean forget their ancient valiant strain?
Tyrannick best to hostile act incites,
which virile races view as foulest stain:
To thee I speak, O It’aly! sunk by curse
of thousand sins, who dost thyself adverse.

9

Ah, wretched Christians, who such cross incur,
be you perchance the teeth by Cadmus sown,
that waste of brother-blood ye thus prefer
when all by self-same mother-womb are grown?
How durst you see yon Holy Sepulture
owned by the bandogs who such feuds disown,
who come to hold and have your ancient ground,
their warlike prowess making them renown’d?

10

Ye know ’tis now their usance and decree,
whereof they are observantists entire,
to levy restless hosts of Heathenry,
and harm the hearts that dear Christ’s love desire:
While fierce Alecto ’mid your chivalry
for ever soweth tares of wrath and ire:
Look! an your eyes to risks like these ye close,
how they and you to you be deadliest foes.

11

If lust of lucre and of lordship led
your course to conquer far and foreign lands,
see you not Hermus and Pactólus shed
adown their fertile valleys aureate sands?
Assyria, Lydia, spin the golden thread,
lurk veins of sheeny ore in Africk strand:
Let these rich treasures sluggish sprites arouse
since rouse you not the rights of Holy House.

12

Those fierce projectiles, of our days the work,
murtherous engines, dire artilleries,
against Byzantine walls, where dwells the Turk,
should long before have belcht their batteries.
Oh, hurl it back in forest-caves to lurk
where Caspian crests and steppes of Scythia freeze,
that Turkish ogre-prog’eny multiplied
by op’ulent Europe’s policy and pride.[153]

13

Georgians, Armenians, Grecians, hapless Thrace
cry on your name to quell th’ unspeakable horde
that dooms parforce their darlings to embrace
Alcoran’s precepts (tax of blood abhor’d!):
Prove, when you punish yon inhuman race,
the Sage’s spirit and the Soldier’s sword;
nor covet arr’ogant praise and vainest boast
of vaunting valour o’er a brother-host.

14

But while ye blindly thirst to drink the blood
of your own veins, Oh hapless Race insane!
never hath failèd Christian hardihood
in this our little household Lusitane:
Her seats are set by Africk’s salty flood;
she holds in Asian realms the largest Reign;
She sows and ears o’er all the Fourth new-found;
and there would hasten had but Earth more ground.

15

Meanwhile behold we what new chance befell
the seld-seen Voyagers who Fame would earn,
Since gentle Venus deigned the gale to quell,
and futile furies of fierce winds to spurn;
when they the large-spread Land’s appearance hail,
of stubborn obst’inate toil the bound and bourne,
and where the Saviour’s seed they wend to sow,
enthrone new lords, new lights, new laws bestow.

16

Soon as along the stranger-shores they lay,
a fragile fleet that fishing people bare
they found, and by such guidance learnt the way
to Calecut, whose denizens they were:
Thither inclined the Prores without delay;
for ’twas the City fairest ’mid the fair
in land of Malabar and where abode
the King, whose orders all that Region owe’d.

17

Outside of Indus, inside Ganges, lies
a wide-spread country famed enough of yore;
northward the peaks of caved Emódus[154] rise,
and southward Ocean doth confine the shore:
She bears the yoke of various sovranties
and various eke her creeds: While these adore
vicious Mafóma, those to stock and stone
bow down, and eke to brutes among them grown.

18

There, deep i’ the mighty Range, that doth divide
the land, and cutteth Asian continent,
whose crests are known by names diversified,
of ev’ry country where its trend is bent;
outburst the fountains, which commingling glide
in pow’erful streams, that die when travel-spent
in Indic Ocean, and the arms of these
convert the country to a Chersonèse:

19

Twixt either river from this breadth of base
puts forth the spacious land a long thin horn,
quasi-pyramidal, which in th’ embrace
of Ocean lies with Isle Ceylón toforn:
And, near the source that shows the natal place
of Gange, if olden Fame of Truth be born,
the happy Peoples of th’ adjacent bowers,
feed on the fragrance of the finest flowers;

20

But now of many usance, mode and name
are all the tribes who have and hold the ground;
Pathans and Delhis urge the proudest claim
to land and numbers, for they most abound:
Deccanis, Oriás, who both misclaim
salvation in the sounding flood is found
by Ganges rolled; and here the land Bengal
is rich in sort her wealth exceedeth all.

21

The sovranty of bellicose Cambay,
(men say ’twas puissant Porus’ olden reign);
Narsinga’s Kingdom, with her rich display
of gold and gems but poor in martial vein:
Here seen yonside where wavy waters play
a range of mountains skirts the murmuring Main,
serving the Malabar for mighty mure,
who thus from him of Canará dwells secure.

22

The country-people call this range the Ghaut,
and from its foot-hills scanty breadth there be
whose seaward-sloping coast-plain long hath fought
’gainst Ocean’s natural ferocity:
Here o’er her neighbour Cities, sans a doubt,
Calecut claimeth highest dignity,
crown of the kingdom fair and flourishing:
Here he entitled “Samorim”[155] is King.

23

Arrived the Squadron off that wealthy land,
she sent a Portingall to make report,
so mote the Géntoo monarch understand
who hath arrivèd in his distant port:
A stream the Herald struck which, leaving land
entereth Ocean; and his novel sort,
his hue, his strange attire, his stranger-ways
made all the lieges gather round to gaze.

24

Amid the swarming rout that thronged to view,
cometh a Muslim, who was born and bred
in distant Barb’ary ’mid her barbarous crew,
there, where in ancient day Antaeus sway’d:
Right well the Lusitanian realm he knew,
or by the scanty distance thither led,
or ’signèd by the Sword and Fortune’s brand,
to long-drawn exile in a foreign land.

25

With jocund mien our Messenger to sound,
for-that he speaketh well the speech of Spain,
he thus:—“Who brought thee to this new world’s bound,
far from thy Fatherland, the Lusitan?”
“Op’ening,” respondeth he, “the seas profound
which never openèd the race of man;
for Indus’ mighty flood we hither bore,
to win for Holy Faith one triumph more.”

26

By the long voyage sore astonied stood
the Moor Monsaydé, thus his name was known;
when told the Lusian how the terr’ible flood
had all the temper of a tyrant shown:
But, as that errand’s drift, he understood,
concern’d the Ruler of the Land alone,
he tells the stranger how the Monarch lay
outside the city at a little way:

27

And that while travelled to the royal ear
news of that advent strange, if judged he meet,
repairing to his humble dwelling near,
’twere well refreshment of the land to eat;
whence by short rest restorèd and good cheer,
the twain together might regain the Fleet;
for life has nothing like the joy and glee
wherewith near neighbours meet in far countrie.

28

The Portingall, accepting not ingrate
what glad Monsaydé for his guest deviseth;
as though their friendship were of olden date,
eats, drinks, and does whate’er the host adviseth:
Now from the City wend they, making straight
towards the Squadron which the Moor agniseth;
and scale the Flagship’s flank, where all the crew
with kindly glances Moor Monsaydé view.

29

Embraceth him our Chief, whom hugely please
the well-remembered accents of Castile;
seateth him near, and asketh him at ease
anent the land and folk therein that dwell.
Even as flockt on Rhodopé the trees,
to hear the Lover of the Damosel
Eurydice, his lyre of gold resound,
the Folk to hearken flockt the Moor around.

30

Then he: “O Nation! who by Nature’s hand
was ’stablished neighbour to my natal nide,
what mighty Chance, what Destiny’s command
upon such voyage drave you far and wide?
Not causeless, no; though darkly, deeply plan’d
from unknown Minho, distant Tagus-tide,
your course o’er Oceans aye by keel unplow’d
to Reigns such distance and such dangers shroud.

31

“God bringeth you, pardie! for He intendeth
some special service which your works await:
For this alone He guideth and defendeth
from en’emies, Ocean and the winds’ wild hate.
Know, that ye look on Inde wherein extendeth
a world of nations, rich and fortunate
in lucent gold, and gems of princely price,
and odorif’erous fumes and biting spice.

32

“This Province, in whose Port your ships have tane
refuge, the Malabar by name is known;
its ántique rite adoreth idols vain,
Idol-religion being broadest sown:
Of divers Kings it is; but ’twas the Reign,
as olden legend saith, of only one,
hight the last King was Sarmá Perimal,[156]
who ’neath one sceptre held the Kingdom all.

33

“But as this region there and then was sought
by other races from the Arab Bight,
who Mahometic worship with them brought—
the same my parents planted in my sprite—
it hapt their wisdom and their pray’ers so wrought
upon the Perimal; and lit such light
that to the Faith convert with fervour high,
he only hoped a Saint in it to die.

34

“He mans his ships and loads with merchandise
and many an offering curious, rare and rich,
and there religious life to lead he hies
where lies our Prophet who our Law did preach:
But ere abandon’d home, his satrapies,
that lackèd lawful heir, he parts to each
and all he lovèd: Hence his intimates he
from want made wealthy, and from serfdom free.

35

“To this Cochim, to that falls Cananor,
one hath Chalé, another th’ Isle Piment,
a third Coulam, a fourth takes Cranganor,
the rest is theirs with whom he rests content.
Only one Youth, for whom warm love he bore,
when all was parted, did himself present:
Nothing save Calecut for him remainèd,
which, by her traffick, wealth and rank had gainèd.

36

“On him the title par’amount he bestows
of Emperor, with sway o’er ev’ery state;
and, made this partage, there he dil’igent goes,
where, after Santon-life, he met his fate:
Thus ’twas the name of Samorim arose—
of all this region proudest potentate—
borne by the Youth, and by his heirs from whom
this who now wields imperial pow’er is come.

37

“The Law that holds the people, high and low,
is fraught with false fantastick tales long past:
they go unclothèd, but a wrap they throw
for decent purpose round the loins and waist:
Two modes of men are known; the nobles know
the name of Nayrs, who call the lower caste
Poléas, whom their haughty laws contain
from intermingling with the higher strain:

38

“For men who aye had office in one guise
with mates of other office ne’er may wive;
nor may the son the calling exercise
save sire’s and foresires’ long as he shall live.
These Nayrs as sin and shame, forsooth, despise
the touch of outcasts, and they fain believe
that, peradventure, if the touch occur,
a thousand rites must wash their bodies pure.

39

“In sim’ilar form the Júdaean folk of old
touch’d not the peoples of Samaria-reign:
But strangenesses far stranger than I’ve told
of varied usages shall meet your eyne.
None save the Nayrs affront the manifold
chances of war, who like stone-wall sustain
their King from enemies, arms aye in hand,
in left the target, and in right the brand.

40

“Entitled Brahmins are their ghostly race,
time-honour’d title of high eminence:
His far-famed precepts, eke, they still embrace
who first to Science lent a modest sense:[157]
A living thing to kill they hold as base,
such be from ev’ery flesh their abstinence:
Only in joys venereal their delight
hath more of licence and a laxer rite.

41

“Common the women are, although confine’d
to those belonging to their husbands’ blood:
Happy condition! happy humankind,
who over jealous wrongs may never brood!
These and more customs various shall ye find
among the Mal’abar men still holding good:
Great is the country, rich in ev’ery style
of goods from China sent by sea to Nyle.”

42

Thus spake the Moorman: Now on vagueing wing
about the city Rumour wildly flew
with bruit of foreign comers; when the King
sent out his servants seeking tidings true:
Then through the streets begirt by mighty ring
of ev’ery age and sex that flockt to view,
came the Grandees who by the King were bade
to bring the Captain of the strange Armade.

43

But he by royal leave allow’d for land
to change his floating home, accompanied
by his stout Portingalls, a chosen band
in richest robes to meet the Monarch hied:
The beauteous contrasts of the hues command
the crowd’s approval, who with wonder eyed:
Smiteth the cadence’d oar with cooly gleam
now the salt ocean, then the frore fresh stream.

44

There stood a Regent of the Realm ashore,
a chief, in native parlance “Cat’ual”[158] hight,
by noble Nayrs surrounded, waiting for
illustrious Gama, with a strange delight:
Now to the land our Chief in arms he bore,
and a rich-cushion’d couch in litter light
he proff’ereth as a coach (an usage old),
which bearer-people on their shoulders hold.

45

Thus he of Lusus, he of Malabar,
wend whither sitteth ’waiting them the King:
Follow the Portingalls in form of War
for foot-troops, marching fierce and threatening:
The people, buzzing with confusèd jar
to see the strangers, fain of questioning
gather’d, but in the cent’uries long gone by
the Babel-tower did such hope deny.

46

Now with the Cat’ual Gama speech exchangèd
on things th’ occasion and the moment chose:
Interpreteth the tongues so far estrangèd
Monsaydé, for the twain right well he knows.
Thus the procession through the City rangèd,
whither a noble, splendid pile arose;
and, reached the precincts of a sumptuous Fane,
through the tall portals paced on equal plane.

47

Here frightful forms of men’s idolatries
stand carved in lifeless stock and death-cold stone,
varied in gestures, various of dyes,
e’en as by feigning Fiend to man made known:
Abominable forms the sight surprise
with mingled members like Chimaera shown:
The Christians, wont to see their God-in-Man,
these hybrid monsters with blank wonder scan.

48

One bore two horns insculpture’d on his brow
like Jove called Ammon in the Libyan wold;
this, double faces on one form did show,
like two-faced Janus limned in church of old;
that had of arms a long divided row
mocking Briareus’ members manifold;
that thing a canine front external bore,
such as th’ Anubis Memphians did adore.

49

The barb’arous Géntoo in his Gods’ abode
a superstitious adoration paid;
then both went straight, ne’er straying from the road,
where the vain people’s King his sojourn made:
The stream of starers fuller still o’erflow’d,
for all to sight the stranger Chief essay’d;
while to the roofs and casements gazing came
greybeard and stripling, damosel and dame.

50

Now near they, marching with no shorten’d stride,
fair fragrant gardens and perfumèd bowers,
wherein the royal palace-buildings hide,
a structure sumptu’ous though not tall in towers:
The chiefs and nobles choose to build and ’bide
where cooly bosquets teem with fruits and flowers:
Thus dwell the rulers of the race, delighting
in seats the City and the Camp uniting.

51

The precinct portals by their work betray
subtleties telling of the daedal hand,
in forms whose noble presences display
the hoar antiquities of India-land:
The marvel-stories of her ancient day,
with such a living art enfigured stand,
that whoso reads them with a lore exact,
knows from the Fiction what hath been the Fact.

52

There puissant armies show and proudly tread
that Orient region which Hydaspes laves;
a smooth brow’d Capitayne is at the head,
and with his leafy Thyrsus leads his Braves.
By him was Nysa-city ’stablishèd
hard by the margin of the murm’urous waves;
so proper was the God e’en Semelé
her son beholding would have said, “ ’Tis he!”

53

And there yon arrowy river draining dry
th’ Assyrian peoples multitud’inous bear
a queenly sceptre, fem’inine seigniory,
of fair the fairest and as foul as fair.[159]
Fast by her side with fury flaming high
her sculptured genet proudly paweth air,
in whom her son a rival lover fand
Oh vile incont’inence! Oh amour nefand!

54

At farther distance trembled in their pride
the flags and banners of the glorious Greek,
of Monarchies the Third, and conqu’ering hied
far as the bill’owy Gange his sea doth seek:
That youthful Captain’s semblance is their guide,
whom Vict’ory’s wreathèd palms of valour deck,
who claims a seat among the Gods above
no longer Philip’s son, but son of Jove.

55

While on these mem’ories dwelt the Portughuese,
thus did the Cat’ual to the Captain say:—
“Soon dawns the day when other victories
shall these thou seest, dim and disarray:
Here shall indited be new histories,
made by the Wand’erers who shall wend this way:
Thus Fate was found by wise and wizard men,
inspirèd Magians who the future ken.

56

“And eke inspireth them the magick sense,
that nought availeth to defend such Ill,
of all that mortals bring to their defence;
for earthly Wits must bend to heav’enly Will:
It also saith the Stranger’s excellence
in Arts of Peace, as in his bellic skill,
shall be so puissant, all the world shall know
the Conq’ueror’s measure by his conquered Foe.”

57

Discoursing thus they reached the levèe-hall,
wherein that great and glorious Emperor
sat on a cushion’d couch which, though ’twas small,
for work and worth was never seen before:
Showed his reclining gest imperial
a potent, grave, and prosperous Signior:
Golden his loin-cloth, and the diadem
that crowns his brow doth blaze with many a gem.

58

Hard by his side an old man reverent,
knelt on the floor, and now and then a few
green leaves of pungent pepper did present,
in wonted usage for the Sire to chew.
A Brahmin, personage pre-eminent,
with gliding gait beside the Gama drew,
and led him up the potent King to greet,
who with a nod designed a facing seat.

59

When near that splendid couch took place the guest,
and others farther off, prompt glance and keen
the Samo’rim cast on folk whose garb and gest
were like to nothing he had ever seen:
Then, speaking gravely from his stately breast,
adding authority to noble mien,
and gaining credence of the King and crowd,
his royal message spake our Chief aloud:—

60

“A mighty King there thronèd, whither roll
voluble Heavens in eternal round,
where Earth by Earth conceals the rays of Sol,
tingeing the world he left with gloom profound;
hearing the rumours which from distant goal
respond to Echo, how on Indic ground
thine is the sole imperial Majesty,
the knot of Friendship lief would knit with thee.

61

“And by long devious courses his command
sent me to say, that all things mercantile,
which go by ocean or which go by land,
supplied by realms betwixt the Tage and Nyle;
from foggy Zealand’s frore Pole-fronting strand,
to the far lands where Sol ne’er changeth style
of days, that splendid shine on Aethiop shore,
all these his kingdom holds in mighty store.

62

“And if thou wilt, with pacts and firmest ties
of naked, sacred Peace and Friendship rare,
allow exchange of superfluities
his earth and thine with like abundance bear;
making the rents and rev’enues richer rise
(wherefore men toil and travail, sweat and fare)
for both the countries, certès, shall pertain
to him great glory and to thee great gain.

63

“And when thus knitted Friendship’s steadfast knot
which aye you mighty monarchs twain shall bind,
prompt will he be against all adverse lot,
by chance of warfare to thy reign design’d,
with soldiers, arms, and ships; so men shall wot
thy friend and brother they in him shall find:
He hopeth eke that when thy course is tracèd
by sure response to see my mission gracèd.”

64

Such royal message spake our Chief before
the Géntoo King, who thus vouchsafed reply,
that to receive such fair Ambassador
from land so far he holdeth honour high:
But that his final will fain standeth o’er
till tane the counsel of his ministry,
who shall make certain, after long debate,
what King he speaketh of, what race, what state.

65

Meanwhile from labours past the Chief may wend
where rest awaits him, and in brief delay
to the despatch he will due care extend,
whereby their King shall greet their homeward way.
This said, brought sombre Night the wonted end
to human labours of the livelong Day,
soothing the weary limbs with balmy swoon,
and tirèd eyne with sweet Oblivion’s boon.

66

The Gama, with his Portingalls remainèd,
whom, upon hospitable thought intent,
the noble Indian Regent entertainèd
with feast and joy and general content.
The Cat’ual, to his monarch’s service trainèd,
sought surest tidings; ’twas his regiment
to learn how, when, and whence the Folk had come,
what laws were theirs, what customs, and what home.

67

Soon as he saw the Delian Car of fire
the fair Youth drives, come forth and light restore,
he summoneth Monsaydé for desire
to know the strangers new to th’ Indian shore.
Ready and curious now he ’gins enquire
if certain signs, pure proofs, the Moorman bore
anent these foreigners, as men had said
hard by his country they were born and bred:

68

That punct’ual proof partic’ular he must bring
with general information; as ’twould be
notable service done to tell the King
all that could guide him in such novelty.
Rejoins Monsaydé:—“Alb’eit ev’erything
I lief recount, yet count it not from me:
I only ken they bide in distant Spain,
where bathe my nest and Phoebus in the Main.

69

“They hold a Prophet’s Law who was begot
sinless, nor stained with carnal detriment
His Virgin-Mother; Him the Breath[160] they wot
of God who holdeth Earth in government.
But what my sires ancestral ne’er forgot,
of them, is Valour fierce, sanguinolent
in arms, that on their arm resplendent gloweth,
as many a Geste with our forefathers showeth.

70

“For they, with brav’ery better than of man,
outdrave our grandsires from the fertile leas
where fresh Guadiána and rich Tagus ran,
with famed and memorable instances:
Still seeking triumphs, in far African
parts, spurning perils of the stormy seas
our plans of safety and of peace they foil,
they break our lofty walls, our towns they spoil.

71

“Nor less of force and fraud they showed, whene’er
kindled were other wars by Fate’s decree,
or when Spain’s warlike sons to fight would fare,
or there, when others poured down Pyrenee:
And thus, in fine, to thrust of foreign spear
ne’er bowed they, owning alien mastery
ne’er yet was known, I swear no man can tell us
to Hannibals like these e’er came Marcellus.

72

“And if my tidings faulty seem and few,
what thou requirest that to ask them send;
ask of themselves, for they be proud and true
and falsehoods most annoy them and offend:
Go see their fleet and arms, their manner view
of moulded metal, ready all to shend:
Wend thou and note the Lusians’ various art
in Peace and War, the sight shall glad thy heart.”

73

Flamed with desire the Idol-servant’s mind
to sight the marvels told him by the Moor:
He bade the boats be manned, and straight incline’d
to view the vessels which the Gama bore:
Both leave the foreshore, and their boat behind
came Nayran hosts, till Ocean curdled o’er:
They scale the Flagship’s gunwales strong and tall;
and, reacht the main-deck, are received by Paul.

74

Her purple awnings and her banners shine
with the rich tissue which the worm hath made;
whereon appear portray’d with rare design
the warlike actions of the mighty Dead:
Here show fierce accidents of ’battled line,
and there fere single-fights, a scene of dread,
wherefrom the Géntoo seeking all to ’spy
may not withdraw the pleasure of his eye.

75

He asks of all he sees: But Gama pray’d
he first be seated, and in cool retreat
be pleased to taste the food before him spread,
which Epicurus’ sect holds highest treat.
The spumy vases gen’erous liquors shed
which first did Noah make the world to weet:
Yet nills the Géntoo-man to break his fast,
as ’twas forbidden by the laws of Caste.

76

The blaring Trumpet, which in Peace the thought
of Warfare im’ages, rends the lift like thunder:
The diabolick instruments fire-fraught
wake slumb’ering echoes there, the sea-depths under.
Noted the Géntoo all: But most he sought
to read th’ intention and the works of wonder
done by the Heroes which in scanty space
Picture, mute Poesy, had power to trace.

77

He riseth, Gama rising by his side,
and there Coelho with the Mauritan:
With curious eyne a warlike form they eye’d,
an old white Sire of aspect sovereign,
whose name and honours in our hearts shall ’bide,
long as the World shall know the name of man:
In garb of Grecian usage stands he dight,
bearing device of leaf-branch in his right.

78

His right a leaf-branch bore:—But oh! how blind
I madly rush to ’tempt without your stay,
ye Nymphs of Tagus and Mondego kind,
a path so varied, long and ard’uous way!
Lend me your favour while my way shall wind
o’er the deep Ocean ’mid the Storm’s affray;
for sore I fear me an ye leave the helm
the waves my fragile barque shall overwhelm.

79

See how my Lay so long to sing hath striven
your Tagus and the Lusians dear to you,
how oft this exile Fate from home hath driven,
new labours ever suff’ering, losses new:
Now tempting Ocean, then all helpless driven
the dread Mavortian risks and wrongs to rue;
self-doomed as Canacé to death abhor’d,
in this hand aye the Pen, in that the Sword:

80

Now sunk by hateful scornèd Penury
to chew the bitter bit of beggar-bread:
Then mockt by Hope already brought so nigh
to be anew and more than e’er misled:
Then with bare life in hand condemned to fly
where life depended from so fine a thread;
only a greater miracle could save,
than what to Judah’s King[161] new life-lease gave.

81

And still, my Nymphs! ’twas not enough of pain
such sorrow-clouds around my life should close;
but they, for whom I sang the patriot-strain,
with sad return must pay my toils, my throes:
In place of Peace and Rest I hoped to gain,
in lieu of Bay-wreaths bound around my brows,
troubles by men unseen they must invent,
when ills of every kind my soul torment.

82

Behold, ye Nymphs! what high-bred Lords and wise
breedeth your Tagus, what a gen’erous race,
who in such fashion with such favours prize
the Bard whose boon hath lent their lordships grace!
For coming writers what examples rise
to raise Man’s genius to its Pride of Place,
to shrine memorious in the Poet’s story
Deeds that deserve to gain eternal glory!

83

But since such hosts of ills around me lie,
let not my Fancy of your favour fail
here chiefest wanted as the goal draws nigh,
that mighty feats wax mightier by my tale:
Aid me you only, long indeed sware I
no grace to grant where good doth not prevail,
and none to flatter whatso their degrees,
on pain of losing all my pow’er to please.

84

Think not, ah no, my Nymphs! I would enfame
the man who dares his country and his King
forget for private int’erest’s pit’iful claim,
by law of God and Man a felon thing.
Nor poor ambition, whose degraded aim
is to win office, shall my Song e’er sing,
whose only object in th’ ignoble prize
is larger range of Vice and Infamies.

85

None, who misusing pow’ers on him confer’d,
makes them the panders of his ugly greed;
none, who to court and cringe before the herd
in change of figure Proteus shall exceed.
From me, Camenae, fear no fav’ouring word
for him who comes, in grave and honest weed,
in new-born rank his King contenting more,
to fleece and flay the miserable poor.

86

Nor him who, holding ’tis but just and right,
his King’s severest orders to fulfil,
holds it not Justice fitly to requite
the servile brows that weary sweat distil:
Nor him whose bosom, lacking pract’ical light,
seeketh for causes, and by prudent skill
taxeth with niggard heart and hand unfair,
the toils of aliens which he doth not share.

87

Only of men I’ll sing the glorious name
who riskèd darling life for God, for King;
when losing life they lengthened life by fame,
and well deserved the best that Bard can sing.
Apollo and the Nine, who with me came,
redoubled fury to my song shall bring
when rest and breathing from my travail tane
I to my toil refresht shall come again.

Canto VIII

The Governor of Calecut seeth various pictures upon the banners of the Armada; and heareth the account of them given by Paul da Gama: Origin of the word “Lusitania”: Glorious feats of the Portugueze Kings (and of their Vassals) till the reign of King D. Afonso V: The Samori ordereth the Haruspices to consult futurity respecting the Armada: They report to him evil of the Navigators: They attempt to destroy Da Gama who satisfieth the King in a notable speech.

Seen are the Founders of the Lusian race, (1–42)
And Braves whose valiant actions brightest shine,
On Mem’ory’s page deserving highest place,
And tuneful hymn, and Poet’s numbered line:
What way of Calecut the Regents base (43–end)
Consult the famous Augurs who design,
Bought with all-puissant bribes, to show their skill,
And by their cunning the Discov’erers kill.

1

Tarried the Cat’ual, standing mute before
the first of painted forms that stood in sight;
who for Device in hand a leaf-branch bore,
with meteor-beard, long-flowing, flossy-white.
“Whose counterfeit presentment this; wherefore
the strange device he holdeth in his right?”
When Paul, with sober accents answering said—
while the wise Moor for both interpretèd:—

2

“All of these figures which to thee are shown
so bold in bearing, dreadful to behold,
and bolder, dreader far, the men were known
in mouth of Fame, for words and works of old:
Ancients yet moderns are, still brighter grown
with names in Genius’ highest rank enrol’d:
This first in sight is Lusus, from whose fame
our ‘Lusitania’ gained her royal name.

3

“He was the Theban’s son or comrade tried,
the God who divers regions overran;
it seems he came to hold our Spanish nide,
pursuing conquests which his youth began:
Douro’s and Guadiána’s plains of pride,
of yore ‘Elysian Fields,’ his fancy wan
so much, he there would give his weary bones
the Tomb eterne, the term our country owns.

4

“The branch-Device, thou see’st him bear in hand,
is the green Thyrsus Bacchus wont to wield,
which to our cent’ury doth belief command
he was a comrade or belovèd child.
See’st thou yon other treading Tagus-land,
the Plow’er who long hath plow’d the wild Sea-field,
where the perpetual walls he reared on high,
and fane of Pallas for all memory?

5

“Ulysses ’tis who builds that sacred fane
to her, whose favour tongue facund supplies;
if there he fired tall Troy on Asian plain
here made he mighty Lisbon’s walls arise.”
“Whom have we here, who cumbers with the slain
the field, whose furious presence frights the eyes?
He drives great armies to disgraceful rout,
and on his banners painted eagles float.”

6

The Géntoo thus, and Gama’s answer came:—
“Thou see’st a Herdsman who his flock forsook;
we know that Viriátus was his name,
who aye preferred the Lance before the Crook:
He shook and shattered Roman pride and fame;
from this unvanquisht victor ne’er she took
Ah, no! nor ever could her power take
the primacy which Pyrrhus failed to break.

7

“Not force but fraud she used, and underhand
she filcht his life that cowed her coward sprite;
for mighty straits make men of honest brand
break the magnan’imous laws of Honour bright.
This other here, against his angry land
with us forgatherèd, an exiled wight:
Right well chose he the men wherewith to rise,
and of immortal lustre snatch the prize.

8

“Thou see’st with us he beats the Flags that bear
Jove’s valiant birds, victorious, sovereign;
e’en in those days no Braves so brave but wear
our yoke, subjected to our might and main:
See his so subtle arts, his wily care
the people by his deep design to gain;
that Prophet-Hind aye dealing wise advice:
Sertorius he; the Doe is his Device.

9

“See now this other painted flag upon,
of our first Kings the great progenitor:
Our Hist’ory makes him to be Hung’ary’s son,
but strangers say Lorraine the hero bore.
When with the chivalry of proud Leon
and the Gallego he lay low the Moor,
unto Sanct Sep’ulchre saintly Henry hied
that might his kingly trunk be sanctified.”

10

“Say, prithee, who be this that frights my sight?”
(asketh th’ astonied man of Malabar)
“who all these squadrons, all these men of might
with his thin legions thus can rout and mar?
Who breaks such bulwarks proud in breadth and height,
who gives such battle, never tired of war,
who comes so many crowns in many parts
to trample under foot, and estandarts?”

11

“The First Afonso ’tis,” the Gama spake,
“by whom the Moor all Portugalia lost;
for whom Fame sware her oath by Stygian Lake
no more of noble Roman name to boast:
The Zealot he whom God would ne’er forsake
by whose brave arm He tames the Moorish host,
for whom their wallèd reign He lays so low
no more is left for future days to do.

12

“Had Caesar, or King Alexander led
a power so puny, men-at-arms so few,
against the multitudes unnumberèd
this excellent Commander overthrew;
deem not their names had earth thus overspread,
nor could their deathless glories death subdue:
But leave we such inexplicable Deeds
and see what worth of vassal-men he leads.

13

“This whom thou seest sight with kindling eye
his broken pupil, fierce in high disdain
bidding him rally flying hosts, and try
once more the desp’erate fortunes of the plain:
Returneth Youth with Age to do or die,
and turns the vanquisht Vanquisher again:
Egas Moníz, the gallant vet’eran hight,
is Knighthood’s mirror to each loyal knight.

14

“See’ him here self-yielded with his sons he goes,
naked of silk and cloth with neck in cord,
because the Youth to break the promise chose
which to Castile he gave with plighted word:
He lured by specious promises the foes
to raise the siege when sov’ereign waged the sword:
To life’s last pains he dooms his sons and wife
and self-condemnèd saves his Liege’s life.

15

“Less did the Consul[162] whom the hosts surround
when to the Caudine Forks he careless came,
and there his head to bow and pass was bound
’neath the triumphant Samnites’ yoke of shame:
This, blamed at home, an inborn firmness found
to yield him singly, true to constant aim;
this other yieldeth self and innocent seed
and wife—more glorious and more grievous deed.

16

“See’st thou the Brave who, left his ambuscade,
falls on the King besieging yon tall town,
the town unsieging and the King waylaid:
Illustrious action Mars might call his own!
See him, here wends he, limned in yon Armade,
till eke at sea the Moormen slain or flown
lost all their galleys; while he claims the prize
that heads our host of maritime victories:

17

“Fuás Roupinho ’tis; o’er wave and land
his name shall aye resplend with equal light,
reflecting flames that lit his daring hand
in Moorman galleys under Ab’yla’s height.
See how at just and saintly War’s command
happy he loses life in holy fight:
Enters by Moorish hands the heavenly calm
his Soul, triumphant with the well-won Palm.

18

“See’st not this Gath’ering in strange garb that came
swarming from out yon Navy new and brave,
who holp our first of Kings the foe to tame
and ’leaguing Lisbon saintly proof they gave?
Behold Henrique,[163] Knight of peerless fame,
and eke the Palm that grew beside his grave:
Thro’ them His marvels God to man hath shown:—
Germans be they the martyrs Christ shall own.

19

“Behold a Churchman brandishing his skeyne
against Arronches which he takes, the chance
of Leïría ’venging lately tane
by men who couch for Mafamed the lance.
’Tis Theotonio, Prior.[164] See again
besiegèd Sant’arem, and shalt see the glance
assured that figures on the mure and first
wave o’er the walls the Quinal Banner durst:

20

“See here he hies, where low our Sancho layeth
the Vandal Moor who in fierce fight atones;
pierceth th’ opponent host, his Ancient slayeth,
and trails th’ Hispalic pendon o’er the stones:
Mem Moniz he, who in his life portrayeth
the valour buried with his Father’s bones;
digne of these Banners, since his force ne’er failèd
to raise his own, to rout whate’er assailèd.

21

“Behold that other, sliding down his spear—
bearing two head of sentinels he slew—
better to hide his ambush; now appear
his Braves whose might and sleight the town o’erthrew:
And now her ’scutcheon shows the Cavalier
proper who holds in hand the coupèd two
cold ghastly heads. A deed ne’er done indeed!
Giraldo Sem-pavor[165] the stout name read.

22

“See’st not a Spaniard[166] who, dissatisfied
with our ninth King Afonso, by old hate
of Lara movèd, with the Moor abide
in friendship hostile to our Port’ugal state?
Abrantes town he takes accompanied
by the hard Infidel, his Moorish mate:
But see a Portingall with pow’er so spare
rout him, and stoutly lead him prisoner:

23

“Martim Lopés the Knight by name is known
who from the traitors palms and laurels took.
But here behold the Bishop Mil’itant shown,
who changed for steely Lance his golden Crook:
See him, ’mid faithless faithful found alone,
fight to refuse refusing, shake and shock
the cruel Moorman: See in shining skies
the sign whereby his few he multiplies.

24

“See, fly the Kings of Cord’oba and Sevile
routed, with other twain in shortest tale:
Routed! nay, rather, ruined. Miracle
God-wrought, not worked by arm of mortal frail!
See Alcacer low bend her haughty will;
ne tow’ers of flesh, ne walls of steel avail
’gainst Lisbon’s Bishop, Dom Mathéus: See!
crowned with the palmy crown there standeth he.

25

“Behold a Master of Castilian line,[167]
a Portingall by right of birth, o’errun
Algarves Kingdom till she shows no sign
of men-at-arms his force hath not undone:
By guile, and might and main, and star benign
towns, castles, cities, all are stormed and won.
Soon ’spite her townsmen Tavila-town he breaks,
and for the Se’ven slain Hunters vengeance takes.

26

“See him with bellic arts from Moormen gain
Sylves, they gainèd with enormous host:
Paio Corrêa ’tis, whose might and main
and cunning purpose men aye envy most.
Nor pass the fighting three[168] in France and Spain
who won a name that never shall be lost
for tournay, challenges and joustings gay;
winning of public trophies proud display:

27

“See’st them? how clept ‘Adventurers,’ they came
Castileward, whence alone the prize and pride
they bore, the winnings of Bellona’s game
as to their loss all found a fall who tried:
See them strike down the Knights of proudest fame
who of the three the principal defied,
’tis Gónçalo Ribéiro, name so brave
hath nought to fear from Lethe’s whelmy wave.

28

“To one attend, whose Fame so far extendeth,
that with no fame of old she rests content,
who, when his country on a thread dependeth
lends stalwart shoulders to the burden bent;
See’st not how anger-flusht he reprehendeth
the cowèd throng’s suspicions cold and lent;
and makes the wretches hail the gentle rein
of home-born King, not foreign Suzerain?

29

“See him, with daring and advice replete
God-guarded only and by Holy Star,
make possible th’ impossible, and defeat
one-handed, proud Castilia’s pow’er of war.
See how by valour aided, might and wit,
in second slaughter vict’ory similar
he gains o’er those who, fierce as infinite, dwell
betwixt Tartessus and Guadiána’s vale?

30

“See’st not already all but overthrown
our Lusitanian pow’er, when left his line
the Capitayne devout, who wends alone
t’ invoke that Essence, the Most Highest Trine?
Now see him summoned hast’ily by his own,
who plead that Fortune must parforce incline
to whelming force, and pray his presence cheer
the soldiers, and enforce their feeble fear.

31

“Yet see the careless holy confidence,
wherewith ‘ ’Tis not yet time,’ he answerèd;
as one in God reposing trust immense
of human vict’ory won by heav’enly aid:
E’en so Pompilius, hearing the offence
of en’emies urging o’er his land the raid,
to him who brought the heavy news replies,
‘But I, you see, am off’ering sacrifice!’

32

“If one whose Brave’ry rests his God upon,
perchance thou wouldest know how named and known,
‘Portugale’s Scipio’ is the name he won,
but ‘Nuno Alvares’ claims more renown.
Happy the Land that bare her such a son!
or, rather sire: For long as Suns look down
on Earth where Ceres and joint Neptune reign
for such a Scion she shall sigh in vain.

33

“In the same Warfare see what prizes gaineth
this other Captain of a slender band;
driving commanders he the drove regaineth
which they had lifted with audacious hand:
See how the lance again in gore he staineth
only to free, at Friendship’s firm command,
his thrallèd friend whom Honour made a thrall:—
Pero Rodrigues ’tis of Landroal.

34

“Look on this Treachetour[169] and how he payeth
his caitiff trick’ery and his perj’ury fell;
Gil Fernandes of Elvas ’tis that slayeth
the wretch, and sends him to his proper Hell:
Harrying Xeres-plain the crops he layeth
with floods of blood that raineth proud Castile:
But see how Rúy Pereira’s face and front
enshield the galleys, bearing battle-brunt.

35

“See yon sev’enteen to Lusus who belong
upon this hillock standing, life defend
against the Spaniards who four hundred strong,
to take them captive in their rear extend:
But to their sorrow these shall find ere long
the stout defenders also can offend:
Feat digne to last till Earth succumb to Time;—
in the far Past, in Present day sublime!

36

“How the three hundred Braves, ’twas known of old,
did with a thousand Romans battle wage,
in the good times when virile deeds and bold
which Viriátus did, illumed his age:
He snatcht memorious triumphs from their hold,
bequeathing this our noblest heritage,
the Brave though few shall ne’er the Many fear,
as sithence thousand times we proved full clear.

37

“Pedro and Henry view, those Infants twain
of kingly John the gen’erous progeny:
That gars his fame illustrious to remain
in German-land and doometh Death to die:
This Prince inspired by Heaven claimed the Main
as her Explorer; and lay bare the lie
of tumid Moor’s vain boast in Ceita’s wall,
and, forced the gateway, entered first of all.

38

“See’st Country Pedro,[170] daring to support
two sieges laid by Barb’ary’s might entire;
and see’st yon other Count[171] who shows the port
of earthly Mars in martial force and fire:
Sufficeth not to fence Alcacer-fort
from swarming hosts; his spirit flieth higher,
his King’s beloved life the Brave defends
as stone-wall standing till his own he ends.

39

“And here the Painters who in Art prevail,
pardie, had many painted and portray’d;
but fail their pencils and their colours, fail
prize, praise, and premium, of Art’s life the bread.
Fault of the vices flowing from th’ entail
of men degen’erate, who so far have stray’d
from valour’s paths where trod their lustrous sires,
deep mired in vanities and low desires.

40

“Those high illustr’ious Fathers who gave birth
to generations on their grace depending,
fought for fair Honour, sternly strove on Earth
to found a fam’ily that could bear descending:
Blind! if paternal toils of priceless worth,
won name, fame, claim so far and wide extending,
they leave their lesser sons but more obscure,
when left in crap’ulous vice to live impure.

41

“Als there be others, sons of wealth and might,
who to no lordly tree by birth belong:
Fault of the Kings, who oft some favourite
prefer to thousands, wise and true and strong:
For these the painted Past hath poor delight,
feeling vain colours work them present wrong;
and aye as nat’ural foe in hate they bear
the speaking pictures which their semblance wear.

42

“Gainsay I not, that some of high descent
from wealthy houses, men of gen’erous strain,
still with their noble lives and excellent
’herited titles worthily sustain:
And if the light which ancestry hath lent
no novel glory by their doings gain,
at least it faileth not, nor dim it groweth:—
But ah! few men like these the Painter knoweth.”

43

Thus Gama’s el’oquence told the mighty deeds,
disclosed by various tints to stranger view,
where Art to sing’ular Artist-hand concedes
depainting Nature with her nat’ural hue.
The Cat’ual’s ready glance distinctly reads
the surd-mute story and the tale so true:
A thousand times he askt, a thousand heard
each tasteful battle which his eyne prefer’d.

44

And now the light a doubtful lustre showèd,
when veiled the mighty Lamp its lucent ray
beneath the sky’s round rim, and lum’inous glowèd
on our Antipodes the smile of Day:
The gen’erous crowd of Nayrs and Géntoos rowèd
off from the stalwart ship on homeward way,
seeking repose and sleep’s delicious swoon,
to weary beings Night-tide’s gentle boon.

45

Meanwhile those Augurs who most fame affy
in false opinion, that by sacrifice
forecast of future things which dubious lie,
thro’ diabolick sign and show they wis;
by royal mandate hied Black Arts to ply,
and various offices ’gan exercise,
to find what projects brought across the Main
unheard of foreigners from unknown Spain.

46

By Demon-aidance truthful sign they learn,
how doth this novel visitor portend
a yoke perpet’ual, servitude eterne,
the Race’s ruin and its valour’s end.
Th’ amazèd Augur, whom the proofs constern,
wends to the King and tells (e’en as he ken’d)
the fearful symptoms that had met his sight
by victim’d bowels brought anon to light.

47

These signs confirming, to a Priest devout,
a man of mark in Mafamedé’s creed,
from preconceivèd hatred not remote
’gainst Holy Faith, that doth all faiths exceed,
in the False Prophet’s form of evil note,
who drew his being from slave Hagar’s seed,
Bacchus the hateful in a dream appears,
whose hate is doubled by redoubled fears.

48

“Guard ye, my children, guard ye,”—thus he spoke,
“from snares and perils laid by deadly foes
who o’er the tumid waters hither flock,
before the danger more immediate grows.”
The Moorman, startled by these words, awoke
in visionary fear: But soon arose
the thought that vulgar dream his brain opprest,
and thus returned he tranquil to his rest.

49

When Bacchus thus returneth:—“Know’est thou not
the mighty Maker, who the Law devisèd
for thy forefathers, he whose will ye wot
and lacking whom had many been baptizèd?
I wake for thee, for me dost sleep, thou sot?
Then by the Future soon shalt be advisèd
how these new-comers come with bane and ban
to break the laws I taught to seely man.

50

“Until this feeble folk full force hath won,
contrive resistance in all manner o’ ways;
for, easy ’tis upon the rising Sun
firm eyne to fix sans fear of blinding rays:
But, when to zenith hath his race been run
the strongest eye-sight that would dare to gaze
remaineth dazed, and so shall ye remain
unless ye let them ere the root be tane.”

51

Then with the Dreamer’s sleep away he speedeth:
Trembling remains th’ astonisht Hagarene;
springing from couch his slaves bring light he biddeth,
the fervid venom fest’ering in his spleen.
As the pale dawn-light, which the sun precedeth,
display’d her angel-cheek and brow serene,
convoked the Doctors of the turpid sect,
he of his vision renders ’count direct.

52

Divers opinions couchèd contrary
are told and heard as each best understood:
Astute waylayings, argute treachery,
were workt and woven in their vengeful mood:
But shirking treason which may danger dree,
they sought the spilling of the Strangers’ blood
with plots and projects of the subtlest school,
by bribes the Rulers of the Land to rule.

53

With golden bribe, rich fee, and secret gift,
they strive the country-principals to please;
showing with proofs discreet of not’able drift,
how shall perdition all the people seize;
“These be,” they say, “a folk of scanty thrift,
rovers who run from occidental seas,
pyratick rapine is their sole design,
sans Roy, sans Loy, or human or divine.”

54

Ah! how behooves the King, who rules aright,
to choose his counc’illors or his friends belovèd,
by rule of conscience, Virtue’s inner light,
whose sprites sincere affection long have provèd!
The man exalted to that dizzy height,
the kingly throne, of things from note removèd
can gain no notice sure, no knowledge clear,
save what th’ adviser’s tongue will teach his ear.

55

Much less I counsel Kings to rest secure
in the clear conscience of the men who show
of humble pauper cloak the form of lure;
Ambition haply lurketh rags below:
And men in all things pious, just, and pure,
often of worldly knowledge little know;
for ill shall trustful Innocence take part
in mundane matters, when God holds the heart.

56

But each and ev’ery Cat’ual gross in greed,
the puissant rulers of the Gentile herd,
gained by the glozings of the hellish breed,
unto the Portingalls dispatch defer’d.
Whereon the Gama—whose one only heed
despite the mischief by the Moormen stir’d,
was at the kingly feet sure sign to lay
of the discover’d World left far away:—

57

Worketh for this alone, as well he knew
that, when sure tidings and clear proofs appear,
arms, armour, ships, and men would send anew
Mano’el, the King who rules the Realm sans peer;
that to his yoke and law he would subdue
the globèd earth, and e’en the wat’ery sphere;
himself was nothing but the dil’igent hand
that pioneer’d the road to Orient-land.

58

The Géntoo Monarch forth he fares to find,
that with dismissal he may wend his ways;
seeing already how the Moor’s black mind
would baulk his heart’s desire by long delays.
The King, who if by tales of forgèd kind
amazèd were, ’twould not so much amaze,
confiding fully in his Augurs’ troth,
confirmèd too by Moormen’s wordy froth:

59

Feels Fear a-freezing his ignoble breast:
Burneth on other hand a base desire,
which ever held his spirit in arrest,
flaming with Lucre-lust’s unquench’able Fire:
The richest profit sees he manifest
appear in future, if with truth entire,
he make just contract and its cons’equent gain,
for long years offered by our Lusian Reign.

60

Hereon the counc’illors whom the King most prizèd
different counsels and opinions dealt;
for those whereby he wont to be advisèd
money’s almighty magick might had felt.
To call our valiant Captain he devisèd,
and him when come thus spake:—“Now, an thou wilt
here in my presence own the nude clean truth,
thy felon actions still shall claim my ruth:

61

“The message, say they and I understand,
thy King hath sent me, is a falsehood vain;
no King doth own thee, ownest thou no land,
but leadest vaguing life upon the Main:
Say! who from ultimate Hispanian strand,
or King or Lord past hope of cure insane
would send his navies or one ship to stray
over such distant Ocean’s dubious way?

62

“And if great wealthy kingdoms doth thy King
sway, as thou say’est with kingly majesty,
what rich rare presents do I see thee bring
earnests of doubtful unknown verity?
The splendid robe, the costly offering
betwixt high King and King link amity:
I hold no valid sign, no certain pledge,
the pleas a vagrant seaman may allege.”

63

“If as hath hapt to many a high-born Brave,
perchance in exile be your lot to roam,
my land shall lend you refuge and shall save;
for ev’ery country is the strong man’s home:
If ye be Pyrats housed upon the wave,
own it me, fear nor infamy nor doom;
for in all ages life to save must be
the primal law of life’s necessity.”

64

He thus: The Gama, who divin’d the game
perfidious, with a cunning treason play’d
by jealous Muhammadick hearts, whence came
the foul suspicions which the King misled:
With high-soul’d confidence, as did beseem,
commanding credence which he merited,
bowing to Venus Acidalia’s hest
proffered this answer from his prudent breast:—

65

“If man’s orig’inal Sin in hoary Time,
whereby sore fall became our hapless fate,
had never caused the cup of deadly crime—
that cruel scourge of every Christian state—
with enmity to brim in every clime
for Adam’s sons with falsity innate
(O King sublime!) of that foul turpid sect,
ne’er hadst thou held me of such deed suspect.

66

“But, sithence nought is won or good or high
sans stumbling-blocks, and sees each nobler deed
on fair Hope’s footstep Fear aye following nigh,
which on its bosom-sweat delights to feed;
meseems thou deignest little to rely
on this my very truth, nor takest heed
of other reasons, which regard thou must
didst thou not trust to men unworthy trust.

67

“For, an I be a Robber rapine-fed,
undivagous, far banisht from mine own,
how can I, thinkest thou, so far have sped
to seek these seats unseen, these realms unknown?
By what false Hope, what love of profit led
should I ’mid angry seas my lot have thrown,
Antarctick rigours and the fires of air,
which they who dwell beneath the Ram must bear?

68

“If thou demand that gifts of high degree
must the good credit of my words maintain,
I came but stranger climes and skies to see
where Nature chose to set thine ancient reign:
But if my Fortune grant such good to me
home to return and Fatherland regain,
By rich and splendid presents thou shalt learn
the ’assurèd tidings of my glad return.

69

“If this my visit Chance inop’inate seem,
that King should send from far Hesperian strand,
know that yon noble heart and bosom deem
no geste, no poss’ible feat too great and grand.
Well seems it fitting, that the thought supreme
of Lusian spirit should at least command
larger belief and faith of loft’ier flight,
and hold it boundless in its height and might.

70

“Know that long ages passèd, since our old
Kings with a settled purpose ’gan propose
to conquer toils and travails manifold,
which aye to noble plans their pow’er oppose.
They opèd hostile seas that fain withhold
from mortal man the boon of soft repose;
they willed to trace their bounds, to track their shore—
the farthest margent where their billows roar.

71

“Conceit right worthy of his branch so blest
that vent’urous King,[172] who plowed in primal rank
the waves and drave from out his well-loved nest
the last possessor of Mount Ab’yla’s flank:
He by rare Genius, toils that never rest,
unto one plank conjoining other plank,
disclosed the parts, where shine in clearest air
Argo with Hydra, Ara with the Hare.[173]

72

“These early seeds abundant harvest bore,
and waxt our bosoms braver till we came
little by little stranger paths t’ explore,
devel’oping each an antecedent aim:
The latest dwellers on the Blackmoor shore
Austral, whose eyne ne’er saw the Sev’enfold Flame,[174]
were seen by us when left behind in turn
whatever peoples ’neath the Tropick burn.

73

“Thus with firm bosom, fixt resolve to win,
we vanquisht Fortune and we snatcht the prize,
till harbour’d this thy new-found kingdom in
we taught the crowning Column here to rise:
Cleaving perforce clean through the liquid tin,
horrible Tempests’ importunities,
to thee we come, and only pray from thee
some sign and signal which our King shall see.

74

“This, King, be truth: Nor deem that I would make—
for such uncertain good, such petty gain,
which, b’eing my words untrue, mote be the stake—
such long proëmium forgèd, false and vain.
Liefer would I my rest unending take
on the fierce restless bosom of the Main
by mother Thetis rockt, a Pyrat dour
who makes his wealth by making others poor.

75

“If then, Oh King! this honest truth of mine
thou take for what it is, one-fold, sincere,
aid us, to our despatch thy heart incline
and gust of glad return to mar forbear.
But an my tale appear some feigned design,
heed thou my pleadings proved so fair and clear,
as seen by Judgment-lights that never fail,
for Truth is strong and Truth shall aye prevail.”

76

Th’ attentive Monarch felt assured content
when thus Da Gama provèd his discourse:
Conceives in him reliance confident,
and the firm trust that lent his language force:
He weighs of every word the full intent
pond’ering the pleading from such trusty source;
and ’gins to hold as men by self deceivèd
those caitiff Cat’uals who had bribes receivèd.

77

Jointly his lucre-lust claims firm effect,
which Lusian contract shall he hopes ensure;
Hope bids him listen, and far more affect
the Captain’s honour than the crafty Moor:
In fine he biddeth Gama hie direct
aboard, and thence from hurt and harm secure
the fittest stuffs for traffick shoreward send
against his spicey stores to truck or vend.

78

The stuffs to send, in fine, he gives command,
which in Gangetick realms the rarest be
if aught of value brought he from the land,
where ends the shore and where begins the sea.
Now from the Royal presence venerand
the Captain seeks the port to make his plea
before the Cat’ual honored with his charge,
for loan of boat as his were all at large.

79

For boat whereby to board his ship he pleadeth:
Yet the bad Regent plotting novel snare
wherein to ’trap the stranger, nought concedeth,
but stay and hindrance straightway doth prepare;
Then, faring from the quay, his Guest he leadeth
far from the royal Palaces; and there,
where kens the Monarch nought of such intent,
would work the mischief which his malice meant.

80

When reached the distant site, he ’gan to say
fitting conveyance should be soon supplied,
or to the dawning of the crastine day
the passage to defer he best decide.
But now perceivèd from prolonged delay
the Gama how the Géntoo was allied
with the deep-plotting Moors’ revengeful brood,
a truth he had not hereto understood.

81

This Cat’ual also gifts and bribes had tane,
tempted like others by the Muslim folk;
eke was he chief who held the guiding rein
of all the cities ’neath the Samo’rim’s yoke:
From him alone the Moormen looked to gain
their base and wicked wills by hook or crook:
He, who in concert vile with them conspires,
despaireth not to glut their ill desires.

82

To him the Gama with much instance prays
for passage shipward, but without avail;
for thus had order given, as he says,
the proud successor of the Perimal.
“What cause of hindrance here, why these delays
to land the stuffs and goods of Portugal?
Subjects perforce obey what Kings command
who dares their dreadful orders countermand?”

83

That bribed Cat’ual lent no heed as due
to the high words; nay more he rackt his thought
to find some subtle fantasy and new,
some deep and devilish scheme, some monstr’ous plot;
or how his brutal steel he might imbrue
in that detested blood he ever sought;
or how the vessels he might blast and burn
that none and nought therein may home return.

84

That none to Fatherland return intendeth,
and nothing less, the Muslims’ fiendish plan;
so ne’er shall ken how far and wide extendeth
Th’ Eöan land our sovran Lusitan.
In fine goes not the Gama whom forfendeth
of those barbarian hordes the ruling man;
lacking whose permit none might leave the beach
as all the boats were borne beyond his reach.

85

To the Chief’s reasons and rough words replieth
that Idol-worshipper, he must command
to bring near shore the Fleet that distant lieth
so mote it easier be to board and land:
“Of foe or thief the tactick it implieth
when in far offing thus the vessels stand,”
quoth he, “for ne’er shall true and trusty friend
from those he loveth danger apprehend.”

86

Shrewd Gama seeth in each wily word
the Cat’ual’s drift, who fain would bring the Fleet
nearer, where dire assault of flame and sword
were ready made for wreaking mortal hate.
His thoughts he scatters better aid t’ afford:
He seeks in Fancy’s realm some cure discreet
some counterplot ’gainst evil plans preparèd;
in fine he fearèd all, for all he carèd.

87

As beam reflected by the burnisht bright
mirror of steel, or glass-plate crystal-clear,
which sometime struck by ray of solar light
in other part re-strikes the dazzling glare;
and waved by wanton hand of curious Spright
about the house to sparkle here and there,
o’er walls and roofs the shimm’ering species plays,
nor rest its trem’ulous, fitful, quiv’ering rays.

88

So did his vaguing judgment fluctuate
when captive Gama’s mem’ory brought to mind
Coelho, lest he peradventure wait
ashore with boats as by command design’d:
With message priv’ily sent he warned his mate
fast for the Fleet his homeward way to find,
lest he fall lightly in the bitter lace
he feared, the fierce fell work of Moorish race.

89

Such should be he who would, by grace of Mart,
follow th’ illustrious and their fame outvie:
His nimble thought must fly to every part,
see through, and ’scape the danger ere ’tis nigh.
His soldier-instinct rare, and subtle art
must read, mark, learn his baffled enemy;
note all in fine; nor shall that Captain’s lot
be praise of mine, who pleads I thought it not!

90

Insists the Malabar his guest remain
pris’oner, till orders bring th’ Armada near;
he constant, firèd with hot high disdain,
hears eve’ry menace with unfrighten’d ear;
rather shall he the weight on self sustain
which vilest malice born of hate and fear
machinates, than to shade of risk expose
his Liege’s navy riding safe from foes.

91

That livelong night in durance vile he lies,
and of next day a part, when he ordains
once more to see the King: But leave denies
the Guard that not a few of men contains.
To tempt with other tricks the Géntoo tries,
fearing his Monarch pay him for his pains,
when shown the malice which must soon be known,
if there a longer time the stranger wone.

92

He bids him order ev’ery stuff be brought
straight shoreward, all he hath of vendible,
that they might duly barter’d be or bought;
for who nills commerce war is wont to will.
Though knows the Gama what felonious thought
and damnable desires that bosom fill,
yet he consenteth, for right well knows he
with these same stuffs he buys his liberty.

93

Concert they now the Blackmoor shall prepare
launches and lighters fit the wares to land;
to trust his boats our Captain did not care,
where fone might capture or might hold in hand.
Put forth th’ almádies for the beach to bear
Hispanian stuffs, the best he mote command:
He writes his brother fearing all delay
to send the bales that shall his blackmail pay.

94

The merchandise now landed is ashore,
where by that greedy Catual ’tis tane:
Alvaro and Diogo guard the store,
with leave to truck or vend as best they can.
That more than duty, than obedience more,
Gain rules th’ ignoble breast of lawless man
well doth that Pagan to the worldling show;
for gained the goods he let the Gama go:

95

He lets him go, for in the goods he thought
to hold sufficient pledge and pawn that may
a better penny to his purse be brought,
than if for longer time our Chief he stay:
The Gama, certain that no more he ought
to land, and haply ’counter fresh delay,
and to his vessels being now restor’d,
resolves with tranquil mind to bide aboard.

96

Aboard the ships he bides with mind at ease
till seen what circumstance the days shall show;
for now his spirit no reliance sees
upon that bribèd Regent vile and low.
Here let the Casuist who riddle rees,
see how the wealthy as the wantful too,
are ruled by lucre and the noxious thirst
of gain that gars us dare and do the worst.

97

By Thracia’s Sovran Polydore is slain,
only to have and hold his wealthy store;
the guarded edifice may not contain
Acrisius’ daughter ’gainst the golden shower;
so raged Tarpeia’s avarice insane
that she in truck for shining yellow ore,
the lofty towers to the foe betrayeth,
and stifled, crusht, the price of treason payeth.

98

This opes of warded Fort the valvarte-wall,
maketh the felon friend his faith forego:
This changeth noblest Thane to vilest Thrall
and yieldeth Captains to the luring foe:
This maketh purest maiden foully fall,
and know no fear, no reck of Honour trow:
This Art and Science shall at times deprave,
blind sanest judgment, consciences enslave:

99

This loves to gloss with subtler sense than meant
the Texts: This maketh Laws and Laws unmaketh:
This tainteth subjects with a traitor-taint:
This in the patriot King the tyrant waketh.
E’en he, self-vowèd to th’ Omnipotent,
as proved by thousand instances, forsaketh
God’s way by Gold’s enchanting Siren woo’d;
yet haply showing still some tint of good.

Canto IX

Now, free’d from the snares and perils which threatened him, Vasco da Gama quitteth Calecut, and returneth to the Kingdom (Portugal), with the glad tidings of having discovered Oriental India: Venus directeth his course to a delicious Island: Description of that same Island: Landing of the Navigators: Festive shows wherewith they are there received; the soldiers by the Nereids and Da Gama by Thetis (sic).

Fareth from Calecut the Capitayne | (1–16)
Bearing glad tidings of the Orient;
To whom, amiddle of the tumid Main, | (17–63)
Venus displays an Island excellent:
Here from all nobly suffered loss and pain, | (64–82)
Rest and Repose they find convenient,
And with the gentle Nymphs the livelong day | (83–95)
They pass in wassail, and in Love’s fair play.

1

Within the City long remainèd pent
nor found a purchaser our Factor-twain:
The wily Infidels by foil and feint
made every trader cease from trade and gain:
For all they purposèd, and hoped, and meant,
was there the stout Discov’erers to detain
of India, till arrive th’ expected Fleet
of Mecan vessels and the foe defeat.

2

There, where the City crowns the Red Sea bight
founded by Egypt’s royal Ptolemy,
and from his sister-spouse Arsin’oe hight,
to Suez changèd in our modern day;
the harbour lieth at a distance light
from far-famed Meca, raised to high degree
by the false superstition and profane,
the Holy Water of the Moorish men.[175]

3

Gidà the hythe is ’titled, where the trade
of all the Red Sea shore-lands flourisht most,
whereby was great and grateful gain convey’d
unto the Sóldan,[176] who possest the coast:
Hence to the Malabars, by contract made
with th’ Infidel, tall ships, a potent host,
each year fares sailing over Indic seas
stocking their teeming holds with spiceries.

4

Upon these ships firm hopes the Moors had set,
e’en as their puissance was so much the higher,
that these who sought their gains so grateful great,
they might consume with crepitating fire:
For the good succour all confiding wait,
and from th’ Explorers naught they now require,
save to retard their sailing in such sort,
that the famed Meca-fleet should make the port.

5

But He who rules the Heav’ens and human race,
who for whatever willèd hath His will,
the fittest causes from afar doth trace
which shall His provident effects fulfil;
pitiful accidents of ruth and grace
dealt to Monsaydé, who, with guarded skill,
devoted self Da Gama to advise,
and gain his rightful guerdon—Paradise.

6

He, whom the Moorish rout might not suspect,
being like them a Moor, but firmly thought
a villain member of the villain sect,
unveiled the frauds with foulest treason fraught:
The ships by distance from the shore protect,
in stealth with pious heart full oft he sought,
mourning the causeless evils that ordain
malignant hate and vengeance Sarracen.

7

He warns the wary Gama that th’ Armade
due from Arabian Meca year by year,
is that whereon his fellows’ hope is laid,
to be the deadly arm of certain snare:
“They sail with armed hosts amain,” he said,
“and Vulcan’s horrid thunderbolts they bear;
So may ye read’ily fall an easy prey
as you be poorly furnisht for the fray!”

8

And eke the Gama, now considering
the time had come for him to quit the Port,
and that no gladder tidings from the King
he could expect who doth the Moors support;
the Factors left ashore straight summoning,
he bade them haste aboard: And, lest report
of such a flitting might their flight impede,
he bids them privily their steps to speed.

9

But in the shortest space had Rumour flown
on res’onant wing, nor here as wont did lie,
that both the Factors were in prison thrown,
when found attempting from the town to fly.
Without delay the true report was known
to the shrewd Captain, who incont’inently
reprisals dealt on certain who had sought
the Fleet to traffick with the gems they brought.

10

Now those detained are merchants grave and old,
richards of Calecut in good repute;
and in their absence all their brethren hold
the ships withhold them and full true the bruit.
But in the Fleet our Mar’iners brave and bold
the capstans man, and each in several suit
is told to task; these haul the cables in,
those with hard breasts to shove the bars[177] begin.

11

Others to yard-arms hanging on let go
the sail that bellies with a bell’owing sound;
yet the King heareth louder sounds which show
that fast the Squadron fareth homeward-bound:
The wives and children, dight to die of woe
for their lost loved ones, crowd in tears around
the Samorim, and piteously complain
from these their fathers, mates from those are tane.

12

Forthwith the Lusian Factors he restoreth
with stuffs in fullest tale and all-tax free,
despite the rancorous Moor who all abhorreth,
so might the prison’d lieges renderèd be:
Pardon for his deceit the King imploreth.
The Captain greeteth, far more glad to see
Factors than phrases hear; sets loose some Blacks
and, making sail, adown the coast he tacks.

13

Down coast he tacketh, for he comprehendeth
that with the Géntoo King ’twere labour vain
to knit those peaceful bonds, which he intendeth
should strengthen commerce and her object gain:
But seeing how the glorious Realm that trendeth
Aurora-ward, must aye well-known remain,
with these glad news he seeks dear Fatherland,
sure tokens taking of what things he fand.

14

He taketh eke some Malabars aboard
parforce, the fellows by the Samorim sent
when were the Factor-pris’oners restor’d:
Of purchased stores he taketh hot piment:
Nor is of Banda the dried flow’er[178] ignor’d,
nutmeg and swarthy clove, which excellent
makes new Malucan Isle,[179] with cinnamon
the wealth, the boast, the beauty of Ceylon.

15

All this was gathered by the deft design
of true Monsaydé, borne aboard the Fleet:
who thus of Angel-influences digne
is register’d in Christ His roll-call writ:
Blest African! whom clemency divine
in prison-gloom with Gospel-light hath lit,
who thus couldst find, from country forced to roam,
the way to mortal man’s true heav’enly home!

16

Then turning from that coast of torrid heat
the vent’urous Prores their southing courses bend,
where Nature pleased to place her farthest mete,
the Good Hope Cape, where Austrine shorelands end;
bearing the joyful news, and hopes to greet
their Lisbon homes from Morning-land they wend,
again resigned to snares of terror spread
by seas uncertain, glad, withal in dread:

17

The joy one’s own dear Land once more to view,
sweet home and kith and kin to sight again,
with whom old voyage-feats we face anew,
and tell of climates strange and stranger men;
to taste the honey’d draught of praises due
by long mischances, toil, and ill and pain,
each hath of pleasure such a perfect store,
the shallow vessel of man’s heart brims o’er.

18

Natheless the Cyprian goddess, who ordainèd
had been her Lusitanian sons to guard;
and by the Sire Eterne had been constrainèd,
through rolling years to lend them watch and ward;
the Glory gallant toils and travails gainèd
the weals that nobly suffered ills reward,
for them ordaining was, who did intend
all their sea-sorrows in sea-joys should end.

19

In thought revolving for a season brief
how they had faced the might’iest Sea that flows;
and thinking how the God sore gall and grief
worked, who in Amphionean Thebae rose;
she had already planned right glad relief
a prize outweighing all their passing woes,
to find them rare delight and gentle rest
deep in the liquid crystal’s tranquil breast:

20

Something, in fine, of that repose so sweet,
refocillating bodies weary-wan,
for these her wanderers, and pay interest meet
of toil, that short’eneth life of short-lived Man.
Then to secure the ear it seemèd fit
of her Son-god, whose might of Gram’arye can
degrade the high Divine to low terrene,
and raise our human clay to Heav’en serene.

21

And, duly pond’ering, all her thoughts incline
there to bespread upon their wat’ery way,
’mid waves of Ocean-stream, some Isle divine
with bloom enamel’d and with green’ery gay;
for she hath many, where her realms confine
with the First Mother[180] girt by ’bosoming bay,
besides those Gardens of the Midland Seas,
within the portals oped by Hercules.

22

There ’tis her will, the watery Damosels
await the coming of her hero-train,
the Nymphs who worth’ily bear the name of belles,
for eyne a pleasure and for hearts a pain;
with choirs and dances, and by potent spells
bring secret hoards of Love their love to gain,
that all should labour with the best of will
the Youths they love with lover-joys to thrill.

23

Erst so she schemèd for the son she bare
to her Anchises, that he welcome found
in the fair country, where by subtle snare
a single ox-hide spanned the spacious ground:
She seeks his aidance whom she may not spare,
fierce Cupid, in whose force her force is bound;
that e’en as in her olden enterprise
he aided, aid he now to pluck the prize.

24

Yoked to her chariot are the Birds whose song
doth exequies of Death in Life’s own tide,
and they whose figure took in syne gone long,
Peristera[181] who pluckt the daisies pied.
Behind the hasting Goddess troop the throng,
all through the lift with billing kisses glide:
Where’er on windy wings the Goddess flies
with gracious movement she serenes the skies.

25

Now o’er th’ Idalian mounts her car impendeth,
where for her coming waits her Archer-son,
who mustering potent host with it intendeth
to fare on famous expedition,
and rebel worlds debel till he amendeth
those direful errors long by mortals done,
who love goods given by the Gods above
for man to use and not for man to love.

26

He saw Actaeon, hunter so austere,
so blindly bent on snatching brutal prize,
that to pursue some ugly beast and fere,
far from the human form divine he flies:
The Boy for vengeance sweet as ’tis severe
charms with chaste Dian’s shape his hungry eyes;
then let the for’ester take him careful heed
lest his loved Hounds upon their Hunter feed.

27

He sees the wide world o’er how evry Lord,
for public welfare naught doth reck nor feel;
he sees that none the boon of love afford,
save where Philautia[182] counsels selfish weal:
He sees how men who sit at royal board
for words of wisdom aye prefer to deal
in sale of flatt’eries vile, which ne’er permit
the tares be weeded from the fair young wheat.

28

He sees that men, to poverty who owe
duty of Holy Love and Charity,
live only pow’er to gain and wealth to show,
pretending Justice and Integrity:
Of ugly Tyr’anny breeding asp’erous woe
they coin a right with vain severity:
Laws they devise in favour of the King;
Laws which the lieges favour down they fling,

29

He sees, in fine, none love as all should love,
save that which dealeth only ill delight:
Nor for a longer time doth it behove
to waive a punishment as dire as right.
He bids his summoned Ministers to move
armaments, fitted for that mortal fight
he lists engage with yon misgovern’d crowd,
that hath till now allegiance disavow’d.

30

Of these small wingèd Impes a band is set
to varied labours in their several crafts;
these on the grindstone piercing piles to whet,
and those to shave and thin the caney shafts:
Soothes ev’ery labour love-sweet canzonet,
wedding strange chances to the song that wafts
sonorous melodies and roundels gay;
suave is the song, angelical the lay.

31

Th’ immortal Furnaces wherein they forgèd
for their swift arrows points that penetrate,
with fiery Hearts by way of fu’el are gorgèd,
and Vitals vital still that palpitate:
The temp’ering waves wherein the tips were mergèd,
are lovers’ Tears in love unfortunate:
The live bright light and never-failing fire
is ever burning ne’er outburnt Desire.

32

Some hied their dext’erous hands to exercise
on the rude Vulgus’ hard unfeeling hearts:
Re-echo’d through the welkin frequent sighs
of victims smitten by the shaft that smarts:
Fair be the Nymphs who deal the remedies
dear to the hurts they deal, and such their arts,
the sorely hurt not only they revive,
but boon of life to life unborn they give.

33

Beauteous the many, while the few are plain,
consonant with the qual’ity of the wound;
for to heal venom spread through ev’ery vein
the bitter’est Theriacks oft the best are found.
Many are doomèd aye to wear the chain
by subtle bond of weirdest witch’ery bound:
thus haps it mostly, when the darts acerb
are armed and tinctured with the poyson-herb.

34

And from such wilful shots discharged sans aim,
wherewith those awkward Impes aye joy to play,
arise a thousand loves that mar and maim
the victims wounded in such wretched way:
E’en of the Heroes boasting highest fame
a thousand impious loves the sight dismay;
Such was May Byblis, such the Cinyraean:[183]
This Youth Assyrian born, and that Judaean.[184]

35

Ye too, my Lordlings! oft have seen the hour
when love of Shepherd-lass your souls hath smit;
and ye, my Ladies! oft the couthless boor
hath meshed your Ladyships in Vulcan-net.
These waiting nocturns to the tryst fain scour,
those scale the casements and o’er pantiles flit:
Yet hold I mainly that such loves indign
are more the Mother’s than the Son’s design.

36

Now the light char’iot on the green depose
the pure white Cygnets, slowly softly wending;
and Dionaea, who conjoinèd shows
roses in waste of snows, is seen descending.
Her Bowyer-son who dareth Heav’en oppose,
to greet her hasteth with douce smile unbending;
while of the little Cupid lads a band
crowdeth to kiss the Queen of Beauty’s hand.

37

She, to save precious time from vanities,
whispers the Boy embosom’d in her arms
confident thus:—“Dear Son whose hand supplies
the firmest footing of my chiefest charms;
Son! on whose pow’ers my power aye relies;
thou, holding cheap Typhoeus’ dread alarms,
her force by thine t’ enforce, an urgent case
bringeth thy mother to bespeak thy grace.”

38

“The Lusitanick toils well hast thou ken’d,
whom I for ages watch with tenderest guise.
Since sware the Parcae unto me, their friend,
they shall adore my name, my favour prize;
and, as their feats of armèd prowess shend
all feats of rival Rome, I lief devise
some mode of aidance in what things I may,
far as our force o’er man extendeth sway.

39

“And, seen how hateful Bacchus hath beguile’d,
with mortal plots, their course on Indic plain,
and how by wavy Ocean’s injuries foil’d
rather than tirèd they were lost or slain:
I will that in this sea to them so wild,
’mid ever restless waves their rest be tane:
Here shall they gather guerdon sweet and glorious
of toils that make the names of men memorious.

40

“Wherefore I pray thee, Son! forthwith go fire
the Nereus-maidens on their deep-sea ground;
burn they with Lusian love, bring warm desire
to these Explorers of a world new found,
all in an Islet joined in glorious choir,
an Isle unknown in Ocean-depths profound
embowel’d, I will haste on high to raise
where lovely Flora with her Zephyr plays:

41

“There with a thousand sherbets, odorous wine,
delicious viands, perfumed breath of roses,
in sing’ular scenes of palace crystalline,
fair couches, fairer what on couch reposes;
with thousand joys unvulgar shall, in fine,
each Nymph await the Brave her fancy chooses
and all love-smitten, longing to bestow
what Hope can figure, or what eyes can show.

42

“ ’Tis my good will that in the Neptune-reign,
my place of birth, a fair brave race be born,
which a shrewd proof shall be to worlds malign,
and to the rebels who thine empire scorn;
that nought shall save, ne mure adamantine
ne triste Hypocrisy, these men forsworn:
Ne’er shall these earth-things hope their selves to save
when burn immortal Love-fires ’neath the wave.”

43

Thus willeth Venus and her wilful Boy
obeys, and flies to see her will be done;
he bids them bring his bow of ivory,
with golden-headed arrows many a one:
The Cyprian with glad gest of wanton joy
within her chariot receives her son;
and slacks the bridles for the Birds whose song
the Phaëtonian death wailed loud and long.

44

But Cupid warneth that still wants their scheme
a famous Go-between of high degree
who, though a thousand times she baulked his aim,
a thousand times firm friend prefer’d to be.
Gigantia was the Goddess, daring dame,
vain-glorious, boastful, false and true was she
who sees with hundred eyne, flies every where
and that she sees a thousand tongues declare.

45

They wend to seek and send her on in state,
to blow her trumpet of the clearest strain;
and so the wandering Braves to celebrate,
as never mortals could such praises gain:
Now Fame, with murm’uring sounds that penetrate,
flies through the deepest grottos of the Main:
and scatt’ereth Truth believèd true to be;
for Fame’s own gossip is Credulity.

46

These goodly lauds, and rumours excellent
the hearts of God and Goddess, whilom firèd
by Bacchus and to harm the Heroes bent,
changed and with something likest love inspirèd.
The fem’inine bosom, ever diligent
in shifting will, of settled will soon tirèd,
now crieth cru’elty, shame and over zeal
for such high valour evil will to feel.

47

Meanwhile the lither Lad had loosed his bow
shaft urging shaft; loud groans from Ocean rise:
They pierce point-blank the waves that restless flow
these straight, those whirling in a spiral guise:
The fair Nymphs fall and breathe the secret throe,
the ’bosomed burden of their burning sighs;
each falls ere seen the face that makes her die,
for oft the ear hath loved before the eye.

48

Now of his iv’ory Lune the cusps drew near,
with might and main th’ indomitable Boy,
who fired at Tethys more than any fair,
for-that was she to love the coyest coy.
Now of its arrows is the quiver bare,
nor lives in sea-plain Nymph her life to ’joy;
and, if the wounded breathe a living breath
’tis but to savour that they strive with Death.

49

Give way, ye tall cerulean waves, give way!
for look ye, Venus brings her medicine,
showing the snow-white belly’ing sails that stray
o’er swelling crests of billows Neptunine:
That thou reciprocal response convey,
Oh ardent Love! to longings feminine,
an honest modesty must ne’er withstand
whatever Venus deigneth to command.

50

Now the fair Nereid-choir itself enrol’d;
and side by side the gentle bevy sped
with tripping dances, usance known of old,
straight for that Island whither Venus led:
And there the Goddess ’gan to all unfold
her thousand feats of loving hardihed:
They, to be victims of sweet Love preparèd,
each trick would try and dare whate’er she darèd.

51

Cutting the broad highway the vessels ride
o’er ample Ocean seeking Home’s dear shore,
wishing but cool sweet water to provide
for their long voyage briny waters o’er:
When all attonce with start of joy descried
Love’s Isle rise lovely stretched their eyes before,
as bursting radiant through the morning air
rose Memnon’s Mother delicately fair.

52

The bien and bonny Isle afar they hail,
by Venus wafted through the wavy flood,
(e’en as the Zephyrs waft the snow-white sail)
whither the sturdy Fleet fast sailing stood;
and lest unheeding pass the crews, and fail
there to take harbour as she willed they should,
right on their courses threw her lovely bower
that Acidalian of omnip’otent power.

53

Firm and immobile she disposed it where
she saw the seamen seek and shape their way;
so fixt stood Delos when Latona bare
Phoebus and her who joys in forestry.
Thither the hurrying Prores thro’ Ocean tare
where bends the seaboard in a little bay
quiet and curved, upon whose snow-white sand
her rosy shells strewed Cytheréa’s hand.

54

Three fairy hillocks threefold headlets showèd
swelling superbly gracious to the sight,
whose greeny clothing grass-enamel’d glowèd,
in that fair joyous Island of Delight:
While glassy-clear three limpid fountains flowèd
from peaks with gleaming verdure deckt and dight;
and from the milk-white rocks derivèd flow
fugitive wavelets, prattling as they go.

55

Down a sweet dale that dints the hillocks, glide
the sparkling waters to their trysting-place,
and make a table of so fair a tide;
never could Fancy such a landskip trace:
O’erhang it graceful groves on ev’ry side
like one who bendeth pranking form and face,
and in the crystal mirror joys to view
his proper semblance and resemblance true.

56

Skywards a thousand trees rise tall and straight,
apple’d with od’orous fruitage passing rare:
Here th’ Orange painteth on her dainty freight
the hues that burnt in Daphné’s burnisht hair:
Droops low crusht earthwards by her juicy weight,
the Citron glowing with her saffron gear:
Lemons with scented spherelets deckt and drest
mock budding honours of the maiden’s breast.

57

The forest-growths that clothe the hillocks trine
with frondent ringlets fronts and heads array;
Alcides’ Poplars with the Laurels twine
loved by the laurel’d fair-faxt Lord of Day:
and Cytheraea’s Myrtles with the Pine
of Cybelé, to strange amour a prey:
The spiring Cypress pointeth to the skies,
where man hath built his air-based Paradise.

58

Pomona’s choicest gifts spontaneous grow,
and all in diff’erent taste and gust abound;
no want of cult’uring hand these arbours know,
withouten culture better fares the ground:
Cherries with Tyrian tincture purpled glow;
and Morus eke that mimicks Amor’s sound;
while from her patrial Persia-land the Pome[185]
flourisheth fairer in her foreign home.

59

Gapes the Granado tints incarnadine
whereby, O Ruby! shent is all thy sheen;
’braced by her husband-Elm the happy Vine
beareth her berrièd birth, here red, there green.
And ye, O Pears! if long your boughs design
with luscious pyramids to deck the scene,
busk ye to ’dure what hurt and harm may wreak
to your soft flanks the Bird’s injurious beak.

60

The gorgeous tapestry, rare colours blending
and robing rustick earth with rainbow dye,
makes Achaemenia’s[186] webs the less resplending,
yet softer shades on sombre vales to lie.
Here the Cephisian flow’er[187] his head low bending
eyeth the lakelet lucid as the sky:
There Cinyras’ grandson-son[188] still bleeds in bloom,
and, Paphian goddess! still thou wail’st his doom.

61

’Twere hard, in sooth, to judge which case be true,
where sim’ilar splendours mantle earth and air,
if fair Aurora lend the flow’ers her hue,
or if the flowers lend her hues so fair.
There Zephyr aided Flora to bestrew
Vi’olet with colours Love-wan lovers wear;
with Iris red and freshest blooth of Rose,
which on the Damsel’s cheek all beauteous glows:

62

The snow-white Lily with the rory tear
of Dawntide dripping, and the Mangerona:[189]
Letters on hyacinthine leaves appear,
Hyacinth loved by son of lone Latona:
Each fruit and flow’ering Daisy shows full clear,
that fain would Chloris rival with Pomona.
Then, if the Birds disport on airy wing
Earth has a joyaunce for each four-foot thing.

63

Along the streamlet sings the snowy Swan,
percht on her spraylet answereth Philomel:
Startled Actaeon stands no more to scan
his horny forehead where the waters well;
Here the fast lev’ret flies the hunter-man
from densest thicket, or the shy gazelle:
There hurrying homewards to her darling brood
the light-wing’d Birdie bears the grateful food.

64

’Mid such a freshness swift-foot sprang aground
our second Argonauts, far-left the Fleet,
where in the wood-depths willing to be found
strolled the fair Nymphs as though no fear they weet;
These waked the Zitter’s soft pathetic sound,
those made the Harp and Flute sing song as sweet;
and bearing golden bows appeared a few
the prey pursuing they did not pursue.

65

Thus taught their Tut’oress in such teaching wise,
to scatter careless o’er the hill and plain;
so might the Barons see’ing a doubtful prize,
first burn with hot desire the prize to gain.
Some maids whose natural charms the veil despise,
in pride of soveran Beauty justly vain,
casting all Art’s adulteries aside,
bathe their pure bodies in the pearly tide.

66

But the stout seamen when their feet were set
ashore, all hastenèd to greet the strand;
nor was there any who his ship had quit
sans hopes of finding game upon the land:
None think such game that needs ne springe ne net
on those fair hillocks thus would come to hand;—
so bien, so bonny, so benign a prey
by Venus cast love-wounded in their way.

67

Some with the spingard armed and arbalest,
hoping to slay the horny hart or hind,
in sombre bosques and valleys hotly prest,
determined Vert and Venerie to find:
Others in shadows that high noon arrest
from scorching verdant turf, to walk incline’d
along the gentle riv’ulet’s grassy reach,
o’er the white pebbles purling to the beach.

68

Begin with sudden start the Youths to ’spy
variegate colours glance through greeny boughs;
colours that catch the judgment of man’s eye
as not of nat’ural bloom, ne flow’er, ne rose;
but fleecy laine and silk of diff’erent dye,
Dress, that with double force Desire endows,
wherein the human Rose herself enshrines,
and, Art enhancing Nature, brighter shines.

69

Loud cries Velloso, marv’elling at the sight:
“My masters! wondrous game,” quoth he, “is this;
if yet endure that olden Pagan rite,
the Grove be sacred to the Goddesses:
Here meet we more than what the human Sprite
ever desirèd; and right well we wis
excellent wonders and great things here lie
by Nature veiled from Man’s imprudent eye.

70

“Follow we fast these Goddesses, and speer
an they be Fantasm or divine indeed!”
Thus he; and, fleeter than the fleet-foot deer,
all follow coursing o’er the riv’erine mead.
Between the branches flying Nymphs appear,
haply with more of hurry than of speed;
and, slack’ening pace with shrieks and laughter gay,
each yields her graces as her greyhound’s prey.

71

From this the breezes golden tresses blow,
from that the robe’s frail hem is reft aside:
High burns Desire, enkindled by the snow
of living loveliness so sudden ’spied.
One falls apurpose, and her fall doth show
by loving languor more than plaint or pride,
she wills her follower stumble, falling o’er
the lovely quarry on the pebbly shore.

72

Others seek other places where the stream
reveals of bathing Nymphs the secret charms:
who startled ’gin to fly with shriek and scream,
as though surprised by rude assault of arms.
While others feigning to feel less esteem
for fear and shame than force, veil false alarms,
plunge in the brake and give to greedy eyes
denied to grasping hands the goodly prize.

73

That, who in hurry to resume contrives
the modesty that marks the Hunter-maid
hides in the wave her limbs; another strives
to snatch the garment on the stream-bank laid.
Youngling there is who in the river dives
all clad and booted (lest too long delay’d
by doffing garments he should miss the game),
to quench in water Love’s consuming flame.

74

As Hound of Hunter, crafty beast and ware,
taught cripples to retrieve from brook or tarn,
seeing the steely tube upraised in air;
cov’ering the well-known quarry, duck or hern;
ere heard the crack, uneath the sight to bear
he plungeth, certain praise and prize to earn,
and swimmeth barking: Thus the Brave made free
to seize the Fair—no Phoebus’ sister she!

75

Le’onard, a soldier whom good gifts adorn,
a knightly Belamour and delicate,
who was not once the prey of Cupid’s scorn,
but ever dree’d Love’s life-long spite and hate;
he, who so long believed he was not born
to Love-luck being e’er unfortunate,
not that he held all Hope beyond his range
when Destiny shall deign his doom to change:

76

Here willed his Fortune, he should wing his way
chasing the fairest Daughter of the Wave,
Ephýre, lief to make him dearly pay
that which for giving Nature to her gave.
Spent by the race he stayed his steps to say:—
“O thou too beauteous cruelty to crave,
when of my life the palm to thee is dight,
ah! wait this body since thou hast its sprite!”

77

“All rest of running weary, Nymph divine!
Each yields her wishes to her en’emy’s will;
Why to the wood alone fly only mine?
Who told thee I am I, who chase thee still?
If told thee so mine angry doom malign,
which allwheres dogs me always to mine ill,
believe it not, e’en I when I believèd,
each hour a thousand times my heart deceivèd.

78

“Tire not thyself, to tire me; for if I
must chase those flying charms and chase in vain,
such is my Fortune an thou wait and try
her will perverse shall never gar me gain.
Wait! if thou will I would again descry,
what subtle mode of ’scape for thee remain,
and thou in fine shalt note, and fain confess so,
Tra la spiga e la man qual muro è messo.[190]

79

“Ah, fly me not! E’en so may Time foot-fleet
ne’er from thy youthful beauties urge his flight!
For only stay the twinkling of thy feet
and thou shalt vanquish Fortune’s dure despight.
What Emp’eror, nay what mighty Host dare meet
the force array’d by Chance’s furious might,
which in whate’er I wished still hounds my way,
this canst thou do, thou only, an thou stay?

80

“Wouldst in my roll of foes thyself enrol?
To back the stronger is not bravely done!
Wouldst steal my lib’eral heart that was so whole?
Loose it me then, the faster thou shalt run!
Burdens thee not this Soul, my mesquin Soul,
which in those threads of glancing gold bespun,
tangled thou bearest? or thus won the prize,
hast lightened Fortune which so heavy lies?

81

“In this sole Esp’erance thee, my Fair, I chase;
that or thou weary her sad load to bear;
or haply shall thy Beauty’s magick grace
have power to change her sour malignant Star:
And if thus change she, cease this useless race,
for Love shall smite thee, gentle Ladye fair:
And thou shalt wait when Love shall smite thee sore;
and if thou wait what wait I, want I more?”

82

No longer fled the lovely Nymph, to play
her sad pursuer’s heart, her pow’er to try;
as still to revel in the lovely lay
which told the soldier’s loving agony:
Bending her brow that beamed a holy ray,
all bathed with sweetest smiles of gentle joy,
she falls a victim at the victor’s feet,
melted with purest love by dear defeat.

83

Ah me! what hungry kissings wake the wood!
What choirs in suavest unison acclaim!
What pretty pettings! What coy pettish mood
which pleasant laughter presently became!
What Morn and Noontide saw and understood,
as Venus joyed her lovers’ joys to ’flame,
were better far t’ experience not to judge,
yet judge it he whose Fate such boon shall grudge.

84

This way in fine conform the fair and bright
Nymphs, and each Bride with love her Groom endowers,
all heads are crowned with chaplets of delight,
of bays and gold and amaranthine flowers:
Their soft white palms they prest in wedded plight:
With formal phrase and stipulating powers
that pledge for endless time their mutual Faith,
honour and joyaunce, till life end in Death.

85

One, chiefest She, whose mandate proudly led
the Nymphs, obedient vassals of her throne,
Coelus and Vesta’s progeny ’twas said,
as by her queenly bearing might be known;
who over Earth and Ocean glamour shed,
the noble Captain, digne such boon to own,
with honest princely pomp comes forth to greet
as for such great egregious Ladye meet:

86

And, told the station and the name of her,
in high exordium with high grace ornate,
her cause of coming ’gan to him prefer,
by the high influ’ence of immobile Fate;
and ope before his eyne the gen’eral sphere
of vasty regions, seas unnavigate,
the secret knowledge couched in prophecy,
which he and his alone deserved to see;

87

Taking his hand in hers she guides her guest
straight to a tow’ering head of Hill divine,
whereof a splendid Pleasaunce is the crest,
plated with purest gold and crystal shine.
Therein the greater part of day they rest
where loving play and lasting pleasures reign:
The Queen enjoys her loves in palace-bowers,
the Nymphs in sylvan shades amid the flowers.

88

Thus Fair and Brave in fittest union meet,
while minute by the merry hours of light;
and taste the genial gladness rare as sweet
which their long labours and dark days turn bright:
Man’s high heroick deed, and daring feat
of famous force, the World shall aye requite
with guerdon merited, and boon sublime—
a Name and Fame that stand the test of Time.

89

For, all our Ocean-maids so fair, so sprightful,
Tethys, and eke her Isle of angel-ground,
None other thing be they, but the delightful
Honours that make our human life renown’d:
That high pre-em’inence and that glory rightful
are but the Triumphs, and the brows becrown’d
with Palms and Bay-wreaths, wond’ering gaze and praise:
Such the delights my fabled Isle displays;

90

These Immortalities—in young world feignèd
by men who cherisht toils of noble aim,
there on Olympus’ star-lit heights, attainèd
on inclyt wings that soar to deathless Fame,
whose Deeds of Derring-do the guerdon gainèd,
by dint of endless toil and moil we name
the Path of Virtue, stony, steep t’ ascend,
but joyous-glad, delicious-sweet at end:

91

Were nought but prizes brother-men impart
in change for Feats immortal, sovereign,
to that baronial Host, whose Arm and Art
made to be Gods that had been only men:
Jupiter, Phoebus, Mercury, and Mart,
Aeneas, Rom’ulus, and the Theban twain,
Ceres, Diana, Juno, Pallas, were
but human flesh to human weakness heir.

92

Yet Fame, that trumpet of Man’s high emprize,
on Earth bestowed them names of strange estate,
Godheads, and deathless Semi-deities,
Indigetes and Heroes, “Grand” and “Great.”
Wherefore, oh, ye! who Fame’s fair guerdon prize,
if in the World with these ye lief would mate,
awake from Slumber, shake off Sloth ignave
that sinks Man’s freeborn soul to soul of slave.

93

And bridle Av’arice-sin with iron bit,
rein that Ambition which o’er-reigns your race
in thousand fashions, and the base conceit
of vicious Tyr’anny breeding vile disgrace:
Such tinkling honours, gold so counterfeit,
to true and honest worth ne’er raised the base:
Better to merit and the meed to miss,
than, lacking merit, every meed possess.

94

Or give us Peace, and Laws impartial deal,
that baulk the rich from plund’ering poorer men;
or cloak your forms in coats of flashing steel,
and crush the law of hostile Saracen:
Thus shall your valour raise the Commonweal
all gaining ampler, none a smaller gain;
deservèd riches shall to you be rife
with Honours, alt-relief of human life.

95

Thus shall ye serve the King ye love so dear
now with your proffer’d counsels sagely bold
then by the Sword, that shall your names uprear
to dizzy heights where trod your sires of old:
To ’tempt impossibilities forbear;
who wills aye finds a way; and thus enrol’d,
your names shall rival this heroick band,
and gain fair greeting in Dame Venus’ land.

Canto X

Tethys inviteth the Navigators: The Siren’s prophetick Song, wherein she toucheth upon the principal achievements and conquests of the Portugueze Viceroys, the Governors, and the Captains in India until the days of D. Joam de Castro: Tethys with Da Gama ascendeth a Mount, whence she showeth him the Spheres, terrestrial and celestial: Description of the Globe, especially of Asia and Africa: The Navigators quit the Island; and, pursuing their Voyage, happily reach Lisbon.

At tables spread with life-restoring food, (1–74)
’Companied by their Nymphs, the Lusians bold
Hear of their Future singular and good,
And daring deeds in number’d verses told:
Tethys displays them all that Ocean-flood (75–143)
Girdeth, and circleth Heaven’s luminous fold,
Dwarfed to a scanty volume; when the Fleet (144–end)
Homewards her well-loved Tagus flies to greet.

1

Now had the glowing Amourist, who won
fair faithless Larissaea’s love, incline’d
his steeds where lies, girt by the great Lagoon[191]
Temistitam, the western world behind:
Favonius’ breath the brenning of the Sun
cooleth, and o’er the nat’ural tanks his wind
crisps the sea-mirror, and awakes the Lily
slumb’ering with Jasmin through the noontide stilly:

2

When the fair Nymphs, who each her lover led,
hand linkt in hand, conforming and content,
trooped where the radiant Pleasaunce reared its head
all gay with gold and metals lucident;
when bade the Queen that tables there be spread
with varied viands chosen, excellent
for loved and loving vigour to restore,
the pow’ers which Love from weary nature bore.

3

There on the radiant thrones, rich, crystalline,
sit the blithe couples, cavalier and dame;
while on the golden dais in state recline
the lovely Goddess, Gama loved by Fame:
Delicious dainties, delicate, divine,
that ántique Egypt’s lux’ury sink to shame,
heap the huge chargers of the tawny gold
from far Atlantis-treas’ury hither roll’d.

4

The wines of fragrant scent not sole excel
Falernus’ vintage, proud Italia’s boast,
but e’en th’ Ambrosia Jove esteems so well
and eke esteems his sempiternal Host;
in cups where steely file may not prevail,
they spume crisp foam that glads man’s innermost
bosom, and warms his heart with sudden glow;
and with ice-water temper’d, leap and flow.

5

Told were a thousand tales of joy and mirth;
sweet smiles met subtle sayings warm with wit
which to this course and that gave double worth,
and sharpened edge to blunted appetite:
Nor of the Harp harmonious was there dearth,
(which in profoundest Pit the naked Sprite
awhile can respite from eternal pain),
sweeten’d by Siren-voice of Angel-strain.

6

Thus sang that Nymph, the fairest of her kind—
her descant ech’oing down the halls sublime—
with consonance of instrument combine’d
and all conforming to one tone and time:
A sudden silence husheth every Wind,
and makes the Wavelet plash with softer chime,
while salvage animals in nat’ural lair
to slumber charmed, a dreamy music hear.

7

Her voice of silver raiseth to the skies
the coming race of Barons high renown’d,
whose prototypes were shown to Proteus’ eyes
within the hollow Sphere’s diaph’anous round;[192]
Jove’s goodly present and the choicest prize
giv’en him in vision. To the Realm profound
the tale prophetick told he, and the Maid
in Mem’ory’s depths the glorious hist’ory laid.

8

Subject of buskin ’tis, and not for sock,
what in that vasty Lake the Nymph made known,
things from Iópas hid and Demodoque;
Phoeacian this, and that of Carthage-town.
Thee, my Calliope! I now invoke
in this mine éxtreme labour, thou alone
canst for my writing to my sprite restore
the gust of writing, which I ’joy no more.

9

My years glide downwards, and my Summer’s pride
mergeth in Autumn, passing, ah! how soon;
Fortune my Genius chills, and loves to chide
my Poet-soul no more my boast and boon:
Hopes long deferrèd bear me to the tide
of black Oblivion, and eternal Swoon:
But deign to grant me thou, the Muses’ Queen,
to praise my People with my proper strain!

10

Sang the fair Goddess how the wide Seas o’er
from Tagus bank, whence Gama cut his path,
shall sail strong Navies, conq’uering ev’ry shore
where Indic Ocean sucks his mighty breath:
How all the Kings, who Géntoo gods adore,
and dare our yoke reject shall rue the wrath
of hard and hardy Arms, with steel and lowe,
till low to Gama or to Death they bow:[193]

11

Of one she chaunted that in Malabar[194]
held of the Priesthood highest dignity,
who, lest be loosen’d with the singular
Barons the knot of love and amity,
shall see his towns, his cities in the war
with fire and sword, and wrath and cruelty
undone, which potent Samorim shall wage:
Against the stranger such shall be his rage.

12

And eke she singeth how shall join the Fleet
in Belem moor’d, to ’bate this deadly bane,
when of his burden nought could Ocean weet,
our great Pacheco,[195] ’Achilles Lusitan:
Lo! as he ent’ereth all his weight shall greet
the curvèd timber and the fervid Main,
as in the waters every keel that groaneth
sits deeper swimming than its nature owneth.

13

But hardly landed on those Orient ends,
and, leaving with the royal Unbeliever
of Cochim-realm, some native troops where bends
its salty branches Cochim’s snakey river;
the Nayrs’ infernal bands he breaks and rends,
in the Pass Cambalam,[196] whereat shall shiver
with freezing fear the Orient’s fiery glow,
seeing so few so many men o’erthrow.

14

The Samorim shall summon fresh allies;
Kings hurry’ing come from Bipur and Tanor,[197]
and where Narsinga’s serrièd crests arise
vowing high valour to their Grand Seignior:
Lo! at his bidding every Nayr-man hies,
that dwells ’twixt Calecut and Cananor,
two hostile peoples linkt at War’s demand,
by sea the Moormen come, Géntoos by land.

15

Again shall scatter all their strong array
Pacheco grandly bold on shore and Main;
the mighty Meiny he shall crush and slay,
and be the Marvel of the Mal’abar plain:
Again shall dare the Pagan sans delay
to offer battle for his bitter bane;
taunting his Host and off’ering vainest vows
his deaf, and dumb, and heedless Gods to ’rouse.

16

No more the Passes only now defending,
he shall with fire consume thorpe, fane and town:
The Hound, waxt wood to see with toil unending
his fencèd Cities on the plain bestrown,
shall drive his soldiers, life so freely spending,
against Pacheco, who with wings hath flown
for double movement: But at single bout
hither and thither all he puts to rout.

17

Shall come in person Sam’orim fight to dare,
to cheer his forces and fresh force enjoin;
but soon a bullet singing through the air
shall stain him red in lofty palanquin.
Naught now availeth him, ne wile ne snare
ne force Pacheco deemeth like to win;
he shall vain venoms deal, deal treasons base
which aye gain less of gain by God’s good grace.

18

“He[198] shall a seventh time,” she sang, “aspire
the brave beleaguer’d Lusian to assail,
whom toil and travail lack the strength to tire;
but save confusion nothing shall avail:
Then shall he bring to battle dread and dire
machines of timber, unknown, terrible,
to sink the Carvels by the board assailèd,
when force and fraud both tried alike have failèd.

19

“On water-plain upheaping fiery hill
he now shall ’tempt the Lusian Fleet to ’flame:
But soldier-science and the war-man’s will
the strength shall weaken wherewithal he came.
Ne’er hath a Baron famed for martial skill,
that starward soarèd on the wings of Fame,
rivallèd this, who Palms from all hath won:—
Illustrious Greece, or Rome, my words condone!

20

“For, such fierce battles in such manner gainèd
by a poor hundred or few more, such fight,
such feints, such strength, such stratagems sustainèd
so many hounds not heartless hurled to flight;
such feats, I say, must seem as Fables feignèd,
or that the Hosts of Heav’en invoked, alight
earthward to aid him, shall to him impart
daring and doing, heart and warrior art.

21

“Nor he who in the chàmpaign Marathonian,
Darius’ mighty powers piecemeal rendeth;
nor with four thousand men Lacedaemonian
he who the Pass Thermopylae defendeth;
nor youthful Cocles of the strain Ausonian,
who with the whole Etrurian host contendeth
the Bridge to hold, nor Quintus Fabius e’er
like this in war showed strength and savoir-faire.”

22

But here the Nymph’s triumphant measure dies,
shifting to sadden’d murmur low and slow,
she sings ’mid tears and ill-suppressèd sighs
the mighty Gestes that did no grat’itude know.
“Oh, Belisarius! thou who aye shalt rise
in ninefold Choir, and ever nobler grow,
if Mars dishonour’d didst behold in thee
one to console thee here thy Shade shall see!

23

“Thou hast a Rival, not alone in deed
but in his dolence and his guerdon dour:
In thee and him two breasts of noblest breed
we see degraded to low state obscure:
To die in ’spital, on the bed of need,
who King and Law like wall of i’ron secure!
Thus do capricious Kings, whose will demandeth
more than what Justice or what Truth commandeth:

24

“Thus do the Kings who, drunk with flatt’ery, feel
the charm of show that gains their hearts’ content;
the doles of Ajax’ arm the due they deal
to tongue of vain Ulysses fraudulent:
But—oh Revenge!—these goods of little weal,
wasted on those who ghosts of Good present,
if brave and gentle Knights miss all their grants,
such grants but glut their greedy sycophants.

25

“Yet thou! who paidest in such sorry ways,
such liege, oh King! unjust in this alone,
if ne’er ’twas thine to give him grade and praise,
’twas his to give his King a golden throne.
Long as Apollo bathes with blessèd rays
this ball of Earth, I swear, shall aye be known
amid the Great and Good his name and fame,
and thine for Av’arice aye shall bear the blame!

26

“See now!” she sang, “another[199] comes in pride
of the Blood Royal, and he brings from home
the Son, whose name shall sound o’er Ocean-tide,
high as the Roman’s in best days of Rome.
The two with warrior arms to hearts affied,
shall deal to fertile Quiloa dreadful doom,
and crown a gentler King of loyal strain,
who ends the Tyrant’s fell perfidious reign.

27

“Mombasah-city, with her brave array
of sumptuous palace, proudest edifice,
defaced, deformed by fire and steel shall pay
in kind the tale of byegone malefice.
Thence on those Indian shores which proud display
their hostile fleets, and warlike artifice
’gainst the Lusians, with his sail and oar
shall young Lourenço work th’ extremes of war.

28

“What mighty vessels Sam’orim’s orders own
covering Ocean, with his iron hail
poured from hot copper-tube in thunder-tone
all shall he shatter, rudder, mast and sail;
then with his grapples boldly, deftly thrown,
the hostile Ammiral he shall assail,
board her, and only with the lance and sword
shall slay four hecatombs of Moors abhor’d.

29

“But God’s prevision ’scaping human sight,
alone who knows what good best serves His end,
shall place the Hero where ne toil ne might
his lost young life availeth to forfend.
In Cháúl-bay, where fierce and furious fight
with fire and steel shall fervid seas offend,
th’ Infidel so shall deal that end his days
where Egypt’s navy doth conjoin Cambay’s.

30

“There shall the pow’er of man’ifold enemies—
for only stronger force strong force can tire—
and Winds defaulting and fierce injuries
of Ocean, ’gainst a single life conspire:
Here let all olden men from death arise
to see his Valour, catch his noble fire:
A second Scaeva[200] see who, hackt and torn,
laughs at surrender, quarter holds in scorn.

31

“With the fierce torture of a mangled thigh,
torn off by bullet which at random past,
his stalwart arms he ceaseth not to ply,
that fiery Spirit flaming to the last:
Until another ball clean cuts the tie
so frail that linkèd Soul and Body fast;—
the Soul which loosèd from her prison fleets
whither the prize eterne such Conq’ueror greets.

32

“Go, Soul! to Peace from Warfare turbulent
wherein thou meritedst sweet Peace serene!
for those torn tortured limbs, that life so rent
who gave thee life prepareth vengeance keen:
I hear e’en now the furious storm ferment,
threating the terrible eternal teen,
of Chamber, Basilisco, Saker-fire,
to Mameluke cruel and Cambayan dire.

33

“See with stupendous heart the war to wage,
driven by rage and grief the Father flies,
paternal fondness urging battle-gage,
fire in his heart and water in his eyes:
Promise the sire’s distress, the soldier’s rage,
a bloody deluge o’er the knees shall rise
on ev’ry hostile deck: This Nyle shall fear,
Indus shall sight it, and the Gange shall hear.

34

“As when some lusty Bull would train and teach
his limbs for cruel fight, with horns he playeth
on trunk of builder-oak, or mast-like beech,
and wounding empty air his might essayeth:
Thus ere his keels Cambaya’s Gulf can reach
Francisco, fierce with vengeful ardour preyeth
on Dabul,[201] op’ulent harbour, whets his brand
and ’bates the tumid bragging of the land:

35

“And soon shall scatter, sailing up the Bight,
of Diu[202] enfamed for siege and battle dread,
Calecut’s strong Armada weak of fight,
that trusts to paddles steely mail instead:
She of Melique Yáz, who boasts her might
of balls by thee, O Vulcan! scatterèd,
shall see her Carvels to the frore deep sent
where hidden sleeps the humid element.

36

“While she of Mir Hosem[203] which, linkèd fast
with grapples waits th’ Avenger side by side,
shall sight the lopt-off arms and legs float past,
sans owner-bodies, o’er the shifting tide:
Like flamey bolt on Earth by thunder cast
in blinding mist of blood the Braves shall ride:
There naught shall strike the shrinking ear and eye
save fire and steel-flash, shout and slogan-cry.

37

“But, ah! that homeward from such wars victorious,
bound for the Tagus of his Fatherland,
he nigh should forfeit meeds so great and glorious,
by sad black chance I see in Fortune’s hand!
The Cape of Storms that guards his name memorious
shall guard his bones, nor blush shall stain its strand,
that noble spirit from the world to tear,
Egyptian strength ne’er tore nor Indian snare.

38

“There salvage Caffres shall have pow’er to do
what ne’er could do the pow’er of dext’erous foe;
and the rude fire-charred club and staff subdue
whom ne’er subduèd ball nor artful bow.
Forsooth His judgments hide from human view!
Vain fools who vainly judge what none may know,
call a misfortune, term a fate malign,
what is but Providence pure, all-wise, divine.

39

“But, oh! what lustrous Light illumes mine eyes,”[204]
resumed the Nymph, as rose again her tone,
“there where Melinde’s blood-dyed Ocean lies
from Lamo, Oja, Brava-town, o’erthrown
by hand of Cunha, such a deed ne’er dies,
o’er farthest seas his name shall aye be known
that lave those Austral Islands, and the shore
Saint Lawrence[205] hight and ring the wide world o’er.

40

“This Light is glance and glare of lucent arm
wherewith your Albuquerque’s hand shall tame
the Hormuz Parsi’s heart which be his harm,
refusing gentle rule as yoke of shame.
There shall he see of shafts the strident swarm,
in air revolving with recurvèd aim
upon his archer, for our God shall aid,
who holy faith of Mother Church would spread.”

Then waxt the woeful wail a sorer strain,
“Oh, God, what vision in the further days!
That fair young Prince of Gaul’s imperial vein,
so knightly valiant, fain of fame and praise:
I see him fighting, stricken, fallen, slain,
piercèd in front by Caffre assegais:—
Blush, Albion! blush, when Britons dare to flee
and leave such Prince such óbscure doom to dree!”

41

“There the Salt Mountains[206] never shall defend
corruption from remains of men that met
War’s doom, and o’er the seas and shores extend
of Gerum Isle,[207] Maskat and Calayat:
Till by pure force of arms they learn to bend
the subject neck, and pay the scot of Fate:
Compulsion sore this wicked Reign shall vex
and tithe of pearl that Barem’s oyster decks.

42

“What wreaths of glorious Palms I see them weave
wherewith by Victory’s hand his head is crown’d;
when he sans shade of fear or shame shall reave
illustrious Goa’s Island world-renown’d.
See, forced by Need’s hard law his prize to leave,
he seeks new favouring chance; and, soon as found,
the taken he retakes; such Arm and Art
shall conquer Fortune and the self of Mart.

43

“Lo! he returns and bursts what dares oppose,
thro’ bullet, lance-plump, steel, fire, strongest hold;
breaks with his brand the squadded host of foes,
the serried Moor, the Géntoo manifold.
His inclyt sold’iery more of fury shows
than rampant Bulls, or Lyons hunger-bold,
that Day[208] for ever celebrate and digne
of Egypt’s Martyr-maid, Saint Catherine.

44

“Nor shalt thou ’scape the fate to fall his prize,
albeit so wealthy, and so strong thy site
there on Aurora’s bosom, whence thy rise,
thou Home of Opulence, Malacca hight!
The poysoned arrows which thine art supplies
the Kríses[209] thirsting, as I see, for fight,
th’ enamoured Malay-men, the Javan braves,
all of the Lusian shall become the slaves.”

45

She had more stanzas sung in Siren-strain,
lauding her Albuquerque’s high renown,
when she recalled the pass’ionate deed, the stain
on his white fame that o’er the world hath shone.
The mighty Captain whom the Fates ordain
to view his toils win Glory’s lasting Crown,
should ever ’prove him kind and loved compeer
of his own men, not cruel judge severe.

46

In days of hunger and of dire distress,
sickness, bolts, arrows, thunder, lightning-glint,
when the sore seasons and sad sites oppress
his soldiers, rendering services sans stint;
it seemeth salvage act of wild excess,
of heart inhuman, bosom insolent,
to make last penalty of Laws atone
for sins our frailty and our love condone.

47

Abominable incest shall not be
his sin, nor ruffian rape of virgin pure,[210]
not e’en dishonour of adultery,
but lapse with wanton slave-girl, vile, obscure:
If urged by jealous sting, or modesty,
or used to cruelty and harshness dour,
Man from his men mad anger curbeth not,
his Fame’s white shield shall bear black ugly blot.

48

Learnt Alexander that Apelles lovèd
and his Campaspe gave with glad consent,
though was the Painter not his Soldier provèd,
nor in hard urgent siege his force was pent.
Felt Cyrus, eke, Panthéa deeply movèd
Araspas, by the fire of Passion brent,
though he had tane her charge, and pledged his oath
dishonest love should never break his troth:

49

But see’ing the noble Persian ’slaved and sway’d
by pow’er of Passion, sans in fine defence,
he gives light pardon, and thus gained his aid
in gravest case, the fittest recompense.
Himself perforce the mate of Judith made
Baldwin hight “Bras-de-fer,” but his offence
her father, Charles, for troublous times condone’d,
and gave him life the Flanders’ reign to found.

50

Again the Lyre its soul of music sheds,
and sings the Nymph how shall Soáres fly
air-winn’owing flags whose terror far o’erspreads
the ruddy coasted lands of Araby:
Th’ abominable town, Medina, dreads
as Meca dreads and Gidá, and where lie
Abassia’s ultime shores: while Barbora fears
the fate that floodeth Zeyla-mart with tears.

51

“And, eke, the noble Island Taproban,
whose ancient name ne’er fail’d to give her note,
as still she reigns superb and sovereign
by boon of fragrant tree-bark, biting-hot:
Toll of her treasure to the Lusitan
ensign shall pay, when proud and high shall float
your breezy banners from the lofty tower,
and all Columbo fear your castled power.

52

“Sequeira,[211] too, far sailing for the shore,
of Erythras, new way shall open wide
to thee, Great Empire! who canst vaunt of yore
to be Candáce’s and the Sheban’s nide:
Masuá[212] that hoards in tanks her watery store,
he shall behold by Port Arquico’s side;
and send explorers to each distant isle,
till novel wonder all the world beguile.

53

“Succeeds Menézes;[213] less enfamed his sword
shall be in Asia than in Africk-land:
he shall chastise high Hormuz’ erring horde
and twofold tribute claim with conq’uering hand.
Thou also, Gama! shalt have rich reward
for ban of exile, when to high command
entitled, ‘County’ thou shalt be restorèd
to the fair region this thy Feat explorèd.

54

“But soon that fatal Debt all flesh must pay,
wherefrom our Nature no exception knows,
while deckt with proudest Royalty’s array,
from Life shall reave thee and Life’s toils and woes
Other Menézes[214] cometh sans delay,
who few of years but much of prudence shows
in rule; right happy this Henrique’s lot
by human story ne’er to be forgot.

55

“Conquer he shall not only Malabar,
destroy Panáné and Coulété waste,
hurling the bombards, which through hurtled air
deal horrid havock on th’ opposing breast;
but, dower’d with virtues truly singular,
he deals to seven-fold Spirit-foes his hest:
Covetise with Incont’inence he shall spurn—
the highest conquest in the years that burn.

56

“Him, when his presence shall the stars invite
O Mascarenhas brave![215] thou shalt succeed;
and if injurious men shall rob thy right
eternal Fame I promise for thy meed!
That ev’ry hostile tongue confess thy might
and lofty valour, Fate for thee decreed
far more of Palm-wreaths shall thy glory crown,
than the Good Fortune due to thy renown.

57

“Where Bintam’s[216] reign her baleful head uprears,
Maláca humbling with her harmful hate,
in one short day the thousand tyrannous years
with bravest bosoms shalt avenge and ’bate:
Inhuman travails, perils without peers,
a thousand iron reefs, and dangerous strait,
stockade and bulwark, lances, arr’owy sleet,
all shalt thou break, I swear, all shalt submit.

58

“But Inde’s Ambition, and her Lucre-lust,
for ever flaunting bold and brazen face
in front of God and Justice, shall disgust
thy heart, but do thine honour no disgrace.
Who works vile inj’ury with unreas’oning trust
in force, and footing lent by rank and place,
conquereth nothing, the true Conq’ueror he
who dares do naked Justice fair and free.

59

“Yet to Sampaio[217] will I not gainsay
a noble valour shown by shrewdest blows,
that shall o’er Ocean flash like thunder-ray,
curded with thousand corpses of his foes.
He shall in Bacanor make fierce assay
on Malabar, till owns in terror-throes
Cutiále,[218] beaten with his battered Fleet
the dreadful ruin of a rout complete.

60

“Nor less of Diu the fierce and fere Armade,
the dread of Cháúl, daring, proudly man’d,
with single glance shall fall, till all have fled
our Hector da Sylveira’s heavy hand:
Our Hector Portingall, of whom ’tis said,
that o’er yon ever armed Cambayan strand,
such wrath on Guzerats ’tis his to wreak
as Trojan Hector wreakèd on the Greek.

61

“Then shall succeed to fierce Sampaio’s powers
Cunha,[219] and hold the helm for many a year;
building of Chálé-town the lofty towers,
while quakes illustrious Diu his name to hear:
Bassein to him her sturdy standard lowers,
yet not sans bloodshed, for with groan and tear
Melíque[220] se’eth his proudest estocade
storm’d not by firebrand but by sway of blade.

62

“Next comes Noronha,[221] whose auspicious sway
Diu from the barbarous Rumé-warman rends;
Diu, which beleaguer’d in his warrior way
Antonio da Sylveira well defends:
Soon must Noronha doom of death obey,
when branch of thine,[222] O Gama! aidance lends
to govern empire, and his fiery zeal
Fear’s pallid hue to Red Sea waves shall deal.

63

“From thine Estevam’s hands shall take the rein,
one raised already to a high degree
by his Brazilian wars, and trophies tane
from the French Pyrat[223] homed upon the sea:
Then dubbèd Amm’irall of our Indian Main,
Damán’s proud Valverte in her panoply
he scales, the first that open gate to thread
by flames and thousand fletchers coverèd.

64

“To him Cambaya’s King, that haughtest Moor,
shall yield in wealthy Diu the famous fort,
that he may gain against the Grand Mógor
’spite his stupendous pow’er, your firm support:
Thence shall he wend, most valiant conqueror,
to hem the Géntoo King, in Cal’ecut port
so let and hinder’d, he and all who hied
with him, retirèd in their blood red dyed.

65

“Low shall he lay the city Repelim
her Monarch forcing with his men to run;
then well-nigh reached the Cape ’clept Comorim,
another wreath of Fame by him is won;
the strongest squadron of the Samorim
who doubted not to see the world undone,
he shall destroy with rage of fire and steel:
Be’adálá’s self his martial yoke shall feel.

66

“Then from all Indus-land thus swept the foes,
the Conqu’eror, coming scepter’d state to claim,
finds no resistance where none dare oppose,
for nations tremble at his terrible name.
Alone shall risk of War the scourging woes
Baticalá[224] and dree Be’adálá’s shame:
Here blood and corpses shall defile the land
deformed by thund’erous gun and fiery brand.

67

“This shall be Martin, who the name of Mart
beareth and eke the deeds the name that gave:
As much esteemed for arms in every part,
as wise in stratagem, in counsel grave
Castro[225] succeeds, who Lusia’s estandart
shall bear for ever in the front to wave;
Successor the Succeeded’s work who endeth;
that buildeth Diu, this buildèd Diu defendeth.

68

“The fightful Perse, th’ Abassian, and the Rume
who hath revived the name of Rome, their liege,
of varied customs, various in costume,
fell tribes a thousand flocking to the siege;
on Earth against the Heav’ens shall vainly fume
that gars such handful so their lands abridge:
In blood of Portingalls this Paynimry
voweth its crookt and curved moustache to dye.

69

“Dread Basiliscos, Lyons’ fiery flare,
fierce Catapults, and mines that hidden spring,
shall Mascarenhas[226] and his Barons dare,
and to th’ assurèd Death glad mien shall bring:
Till, when all Hope is fled and reigns Despair,
Castro, the saviour, cometh offering
his sons’ young lives, and wills their names survive
God’s sacrifices aye in Death to live.

70

“One son, Fernando, sci’on of tree so high,
where violentest flames with loudest roar
blow shatter’d ramparts to the smoky sky,
there, stricken down on Earth, shall Heav’enward soar:
Alvaro, when mankind dread Winter fly
and shift from humid path for arid shore,
opens the waters ’spite what risks oppose,
and fighteth winds and waves to fight the foes.

71

“When, see! the Father cuts the wavy waste,
leading what resteth of the Lusitan;
with warman’s arm and arts which e’er be best
he offers battle’s rem’edy sovereign:
These scale the remparts and at gateways jest,
those cut broad gates through squads with rage insane:
Deeds they shall do so digne memorious glory,
song shall not suit nor Hist’ory hold the story.

72

“He shall once more upon the field appear
a strong intrepid victor, where his sight
Cambaya’s puissant King[227] shall strike with fear,
and hideous hosts of quadrupeds[228] affright:
Nor less shall fail his puissant reign t’ uprear
the Hydalcham,[229] when mighty arms shall smite
chastisèd Dábul, mistress of the coast,
nor shall spare Pondà’s distant inland post.

73

“Barons like these, with peers from various parts,
all worthy marvel and all mastering Fame,
raisèd to rank of Mart by martial arts,
shall come the pleasures of this Isle to claim:
Their hands shall wave triumphant estandarts
wherever keel-edge cutteth Ocean-stream:
Such men these Nymphs these banquets aye shall find,
Honours and Glories to high Gestes assign’d.”

74

Thus sang the Siren, while her sister-choir
with their sonorous plaudits filled the hall;
wherewith to hail the hour of glad desire
crowning the happy marriage-festival.
“However Fortune’s wheel shall turn its tire,”
with one harmonious accent chaunted all,
“renownèd People! rest your souls secure
of Honour, Valour, Fame, while worlds endure!”

75

When man’s corporeal necessity
was with the noble viands satisfied,
and when in sweet melodious suavity,
all had their lofty future feats descried;
Tethys, with grace adorned and gravity,
that with a higher pomp and double pride
be crowned the revels of this joyous day,
to glad and happy Gama thus ’gan say:—

76

“To thee Supremest Wisdom guerdon gave,
Baron! who hast beheld with fleshly eyne
what things the Future hath the pow’er to save
from Mortals’ petty pride and science vain.
Follow me firmly, prudent as thou’rt brave,
to yonder craggy brake with all thy train!”
Thus she, and straightway through a long wood led
arduous, gloomy, fere for foot to tread.

77

Nor far they steppèd when on culm’inant height
where stretcht a gem-enamel’d mead they stood;
Smaragd and Ruby-strewn, so rich the sight
presumed ’twas Paradisial floor they trod:
Here swimmeth air a Globe,[230] through which the light
of purest radiance piercèd in such mode
that as its polisht surface clearest clear,
so doth its centre and its core appear.

78

What mote its matter be escapes their eyes,
yet ’scapes them not it holdeth in embrace
var’ious Orbs, by wand of Him All-wise
disposed to circle round one central place:
Rolling it sinks and then returns to rise,
and yet ne sinks ne rises; while one face
is shown to all and every part, each part
begins in fine and ends with heav’enly art:

79

Uniform, perfect, and self-poised it be,
like th’ Archetype who drew the grand design.
Stood Gama overwhelmed this globe to see
with joy, and hope its nature to divine:
When thus the Goddess:—“Here th’ Epitome,
in little volume, to those eyes of thine
I give the gen’eral World, so shalt thou view
where goest thou, shalt go, and what shalt do.

80

“Here see the mighty World-machine appear,
ethereal where the fourfold el’ements blend,
made by His deep design, His lofty lere,
who lacks beginning and who has no end.
He who surrounding holds this shapely sphere,
this globe in filèd surface packt and pen’d,
is God: But what God is th’ intelligence
of mortal genius ne’er shall dare pretence.

81

“This primal Orb, that rolling doth enclose
the lesser circles in its lines confin’d;
this Sphere, whose flood of clearest radiance flows
blinding man’s vision and his vulgar mind
is hight th’ Empyrean:[231] Here the Blest repose,
here perfect Spirits bliss eternal find,
inèffable joys which He alone may ken
Who hath no likeness in the World of Men.

82

“Only to this Imperial Sphere belong
the Gods of Truth; for Saturn, Janus, I,
Jove and his Juno are a fabled throng,
a mortal figment, a blind fantasy:
Only to deck the Poet’s sprightly song
we servèd; and, if more humanity
we gained of man, ’twas that his wit hath given
our names and natures to the stars of Heaven:

83

“And, eke, because that Holy Providence—
the Jupiter of mythologick strain—
by thousand Spirits wise in perfect sense,
ruleth all mundane things it doth sustain.
Prophetick Science doth this Truth dispense,
a Truth so many instances maintain:
Sprites that be good aye guide and favour man,
the bad his course impede whene’er they can.[232]

84

“Here willèd Picture, lief with change to play
pleasing and teaching, mixing gay and grave,
to give them titles which your olden lay
to fabled Gods in poet-fables gave:
For even th’ Angels of th’ eternal day
as Gods enrollèd were in sacred stave;
which e’en denies not such exalted name
sometimes to sinner though with falsest claim.

85

“In fine the God Supreme who works His will
by second worldly causes, all commands:
Return we now the works profound to tell
of His divine and venerated Hands.
Beneath this circle, where all blissful dwell
pure godly Sprites, which fixt for ever stands,
another rolleth, and so swift none see
its course: This is the Primum Mobilé:[233]

86

“And with its rapt[234] and rapid whirl it drags
all lesser spherelets which its womb containeth:
By work of this the Sun who never flags
with alien courses Day and Night sustaineth:
’Neath this swift orb another orb slow lags,[235]
so slow, so hard a curb its ardour reineth,
while Phoebus makes, with ever splendid face,
two hundred rounds, this moves a single pace.

87

“Lower this other view,[236] enamel’d gay
with burnisht figures gleaming radiant bright;
which in it too hold constant ordered way,
orbs on their axes scintillant empight:
Thou seest well ’tis dight with brave array
of broad and golden Zone, the Zodiac hight,
wherein twelve starry forms of an’imals shine,
that Phoebus’ mansions limit and define.

88

“Behold in other parts the portraiture,
limned by the Stars that sparkling glances shed:
Behold the Wain, attend the Cynosure,
and, with her fierce Worm-father, Andromed:
See Cassiopeia’s beauty lovely pure,
with turbulent Orion’s gesture dread:
Behold the Swan that doth in song expire,
the Hare and Hounds, the Ship and dulcet Lyre.

89

“Beneath this firmamental canopy
thou seest Saturn’s sky, that Godhead old:
With faster flight doth Jove below him fly,
and Mars yet lower, bellick planet bold:
In the fourth seat shines Heaven’s radiant eye;
then Venus leadeth all her Loves enrol’d;
Mercury wends with eloquence divine;
and ’neath him Dian showeth faces trine.

90

“In all these orbits motion different
shalt see; in these ’tis swift, in those ’tis slow;
now fly they farthest from the firmament,
then sweep they nearest earth that lurks below;
even so willed the Sire Omnipotent,
who made the Fire and Air, the Wind and Snow:
These lie more inward, as thou shalt be shown,
and Earth with Ocean for their centre own.

91

“Within this centre, Inn[237] of humankind,
whose reckless spirits not alone defy
suff’erings and ills to stable Earth confine’d,
but e’en the Sea’s fierce instability;
thou shalt see various Continents define’d
by blindly raging tides, where parted lie
the various Realms which various monarchs sway,
whose varied Customs varied laws obey.

92

“See high, haught Europe that adores the Rood,
for pow’er and polity o’er all renown’d:
See Africk grudging ev’ery worldly good,
yon rough, incult and monster-haunted ground;
whose Stormy Cape till now your search withstood,
by Nature ’stablished as her Austral bound:
Behold this quarter where the Blackmoors dwell
sans-loys, sans-foys, whose numbers none can tell.

93

“Behold the Ben’omotápa’s puissant reign
of salvage Negros, nude and noisome race,
where shall for Holy Faith be foully slain
martyr’d Gonçalo,[238] suffering sore disgrace:
This hidden Hemisphere to golden vein
gives birth, which man must win by sweat of face
See from yon Lake, whence Nilus rolls his tide,
how springs Cuáma[239] from the farther side.

94

“Behold those Blackmoors and their huts that stand
sans doors, each castled in his natal nest,
they trust of Royal Justice the command,
and in the candour of the neighbour’s breast:
Behold how furious flies the bestial band
like flock of dingy stares thick packt and prest;
to fight Sofala’s fortress they pretend
which dext’erous Nhaia’s arm and wits defend:

95

“See there the Lakes that cradle Father Nyle[240]
whose ultime sources men of old ne’er knew:
See how he waters, ’gend’ering cockadrille,
Abassia-lond whose sons to Christ be true:
Behold how bare of bulwarks (novel style)
they show a better front against the foe:
See Meroe-island whilom known to fame,
which now the wild inhabitants Nobá name.

96

“On distant Africk hills a son of thee
in Turkish wars shall win the fame of Brave;
hight Dom Christóvam shall the hero be,
but flesh from destined Death no skill shall save.
Here view the Coast where shelter from the sea
and glad relief to thee Melinde gave:
Note how yon Rhaptus[241]-stream, whose wide expanse
natives call Obi, ent’ereth in Quilmance.

97

“The Cape which Ancients ‘Aromatic’ clepe
behold, yclept by Moderns Guardafú;
where opes the Red Sea mouth, so wide and deep,
the Sea whose ruddy bed lends blushing hue:
This as a bourne was far thrust out to keep
Asia distinct from Africk, and a few
of the best markets Negro seaboards claim
Arquico are, Masuá and Súanquem.

98

“View éxtreme Suez where, old Annals say,
once stood the city hight Hero’opolis;
by some Arsin’oe called, and in our day
she holdeth Egypt’s fleets and argosies:
Behold the watery depths, where clove his way
Moses the mighty in past centuries:
Asia beginneth here her huge extent
in regions, kingdoms, empires opulent.

99

“See Sinai mountain,[242] with her boast and pride
the silver bier of saintly Catherine:
See Toro-port and Gidá, scant supplied
with fountain-water soft and crystalline:
Behold the Straits which end the southern side
of arid Aden-realms, that here confine
with tall Arzíran range, nude stone and live,
whence soft sweet rains of Heaven ne’er derive.

100

“See threefold Ar’aby, cov’ering so much ground,
where tawny peoples vague o’er vasty space;
whence come the Rabytes,[243] best for battle found,
light-limbed, high-fettled, noble-blooded race.
Behold the coast that trends to bind and bound
yon other Persian Strait, where sight can trace
the Headland proud the potent name to own
of Fartak-city, erst to Fame well-known.

101

“Behold insign Dofar that doth command
for Christian altars sweetest incense-store:
But note, beginning now on further band
of Rosalgáté’s[244] ever greedy shore,
yon Hormuz Kingdom strown along the strand,
whose fame for riches still shall higher soar
when the Turk’s galleys, and his fierce Armade
see Castel-Branco[245] bare his deadly blade.

102

“Behold of Asabón the Head, now hight
Mosandam, by the men who plough the Main:
Here lies the Gulf whose long and lake-like Bight
parts Araby from fertile Persia’s plain.
Attend yon Barem Isle, with depths bedight
by the rich pearly shell whose blushes feign
Auroran tints; and view in Ocean brine
Euphrate and Tygre in one bed conjoin.

103

“Great Persia’s noble Empire here behold,
ever on Destr’ier or in Camp of War,
whose sons disdain the copper-tube to mould,
and hands not horny with the Cymitar.
But see yon Gerum Isle the tale unfold
of mighty things which Time can make or mar;
for of Armúza-town yon shore upon
the name and glory this her rival won.

104

“Here Dom Philippe de Menézes view
approved a doughty valiant man-at-arms,
who with his Portughueze exceeding few
shall quell the Lára[246] Parsi’s potent swarms:
Pedro de Sousa too shall make them rue
reversèd Fortunes, Warfare’s deadliest harms,
who had his prowess in Ampáza[247] shown,
and took the land by sweep of sword alone.

105

“But now the Narrows and their noted head
Cape Jask, Carpella called by those of yore,
quit we, the dry terrene scant favourèd
by Nature niggard of her normal store:
Whilere Carmánia ’twas intitulèd:
But view fair Indus-flood whose waters pour
adown his natal heights, and in the range
of neighbour-mountains see the source of Gange.

106

“Behold Ulcindé’s most luxuriant land
and of Jaqueta-shore yon intime bay;
the monster Bore which roaring floods the strand,
and ebb which flieth with like force away.
See where Cambaya’s rich feracious band
boundeth re-entering seas, the Gulf Cambay;
and thousand Cities which I leave untold,
here hoard their wealth for you to have and hold.[248]

107

“See, runs the cel’ebrate seaboard Hindostánian
southward till reached its point, Cape Comori,
erst ‘Cori’ called, where th’ Island Taprobanian
(’tis now Ceylon) encrowns the fronting sea:
Besides these waves thy people Lusitanian,
who with their doughty arms will follow thee,
by conq’uering wars shall lands and towns debel,
wherein your sons and sons of sons shall dwell.

108

“The regions lying ’twixt these Rivers twain,[249]
thou see’st, with various tribes are infinite:
Here rule the Muslims; there the Géntoos reign
whose Holy Writ the Devil did indite:
See where Narsinga’s seigniories contain
the saintly relicks blessing human sprite,
Thomé’s remains, the Miss’ioner sanctified
who thrust his finger in Lord Jesu’s side.

109

“Here rose the potent City, Meliapor
namèd, in olden time rich, vast and grand:
Her sons their olden idols did adore
as still adoreth that iniquious band:
In those past ages stood she far from shore,
when to declare glad tidings o’er the land
Thomé came preaching, after he had trod
a thousand regions taught to know his God.

110

“Here came he preaching, and the while he gave
health to the sick, revival to the dead;
when Chance one day brought floating o’er the wave
a forest-tree of size unmeasurèd:
The King a Palace building lief would save
the waif for timber, and determinèd
the mighty bulk of trunk ashore to train
by force of engines, elephants and men.

111

“Now was that lumber of such vasty size,
no jot it moves, however hard they bear;
when lo! th’ Apostle of Christ’s verities
wastes in the business less of toil and care:
His trailing waist-cord to the tree he ties,
raises and sans an effort hales it where
a sumptuous Temple he would rear sublime,
a fixt example for all future time.

112

“Right well he knew how ’tis of Faith aver’d
‘Faith moveth mountains’ will or nill they move,
lending a listening ear to Holy Word:
As Christ had taught him, so ’twas his to prove:
By such a mir’acle much the mob was stir’d;
the Brahmins held it something from above;
for, seen his signs and seen his saintly life,
they fear the loss of old prerogative.

113

“These be the Sacerdotes of Géntoo-creed,
that of sore jealousy felt most the pain;
they seek ill-ways a thousand and take rede
Thomé to silence or to gar him slain:
The Principal who dons the three-twine thread,[250]
by a deed of horror makes the lesson plain,
there be no Hatred fell, and fere, and curst,
as by false Virtue for true Virtue nurst.

114

“One of his sons he slaughters, and accuses
Thomé of murther, who was innocent:
Bringing false witnesses, as there the use is,
him to the death they doom incontinent.
The Saint, assurèd that his best excuses
are his appeals to God Omnipotent,
prepares to work before the King and Court
a public marvel of the major sort.

115

“He bids be brought the body of the slain
that it may live again, and be affied
to name its slayer, and its word be tane
as proof of testimony certified.
All saw the youth revive, arise again
in name of Jesu Christ the Crucified:
Thomé he thanks when raised to life anew
and names his father as the man who slew.

116

“So much of marvel did this Mir’acle claim,
straightway in Holy Water bathes the King
followed by many: These kiss Thomé’s hem
while those the praises of his Godhead sing.
Such ire the Brahmans and such furies ’flame,
Envy so pricks them with her venom’d sting,
that rousing ruffian-rout to wrath condign
a second slaughter-plot the priests design.

117

“One day when preaching to the folk he stood
they feigned a quarrel ’mid the mob to ’rise:
Already Christ his Holy man endow’d
with saintly martyrdom that opes the skies.
Rainèd innumerable stones the crowd
upon the victim, sacred sacrifice,
and last a villain, hast’ier than the rest,
pierced with a cruel spear his godly breast.

118

“Wept Gange and Indus, true Thomé! thy fate,
wept thee whatever lands thy foot had trod;
yet weep thee more the souls in blissful state
thou led’st to don the robes of Holy Rood.
But Angels waiting at the Par’adise-gate
meet thee with smiling faces, hymning God.
We pray thee, pray that still vouchsafe thy Lord
unto thy Lusians His good aid afford.

119

“And you, ye others, who usurp the name
of God’s Apostles, miss’ioners like Thomé,
say, an ye boast of apostolick claim
why fare not Holy Faith to preach and pray?
If ye be salt see how yourselves ye shame,
cleaving to home, where none the Prophet play;
how shall be salted in dark days as these
(Pagans I leave) such hosts of heresies?

120

“But now this per’ilous theme I pass beyond;
gain we again the limnèd shore and site.
Here with the City whereof Fame is fond,
bends the long bow-line of Gangetick Bight:
Runneth Narsinga rich and potent lond,
runneth Orissa vaunting tissues bright,
and at the bottom of the Bay’s long line,
illustrious Ganges seeks his home, the brine:

121

“Ganges whose acc’olents bathe, and bathing die,
and die in lively faith withal secure
whatever sins upon their spirits lie,
the Holy Waters lave them sinless-pure.
See Cathigam,[251] amid the highest high
in Bengal-province, proud of varied store
abundant, but behold how placed the Post
where sweeps the shore-line t’wards the southing coast.

122

“Arracan-realm behold, behold the seat
of Pegu peopled by a monster-brood;
monsters that ’gendered meeting most unmeet
of whelp and woman in the lonely wood.
Here bells of sounding orichalc they fit
upon their bodies, by the craftihood
of subtle Queen, who such new custom plan’d
to ’bate th’ accursèd Sin and Crime nefand.

123

“Behold Táváí City,[252] whence begin
Siam’s dominions, Reign of vast extent;
Tenassarí, Quedá of towns the Queen
that bear the burden of the hot piment.
There farther forwards shall ye make, I ween,
Maláca’s market grand and opulent,
whither each Province of the long seaboard
shall send of merchantry rich varied hoard.

124

“From this Peninsula, they say, the sea
parted with puissant waves, and ent’ering tore
Samátra’s noble island, wont to be
joined to the Main as seen by men of yore.
’Twas callèd Chersonèse, and such degree
it gained by earth that yielded golden ore,
they gave a golden ep’ithet to the ground:
Some be who fancy Ophir here was found.

125

“But on her Lands-end throned see Cingapúr,
where the wide sea-road shrinks to narrow way:
Thence curves the coast to face the Cynosure,
and lastly trends Auroraward its lay:
See Pam, Patáne,[253] and in length obscure,
Siam, that ruleth all with royal sway;
behold Menam, who rolls his lordly tide
from Source Chiámái called, Lake long and wide.

126

“Thou see’st in spaces of such vast extent
nations of thousand names and yet unnamèd;
Láós in land and people prepotent,
Avás and Bramás[254] for vast ranges famèd.
See how in distant wilds and wolds lie pent
the self-styled Gueons,[255] salvage folk untamèd:
Man’s flesh they eat: their own they paint and sear,
branding with burning iron—usage fere!

127

“See Mecom river fret Cambodia’s coast,
his name by ‘Water-Captain’ men explain;
in summer only when he swelleth most,
he leaves his bed to flood and feed the Plain:
As the frore Nyle he doth his freshets boast;
his peoples hold the fond belief and vain,
that pains and glories after death are ’signed
to brutes and soulless beasts of basest kind.

128

“This Stream with gentle, bland repose shall greet
in his embrace the Song,[256] that swam to land
from sad and piteous shipwreck dripping wet,
’scaped from the reefs and rocks that fang the strand;
from hunger-tortures and the perilous strait,
what time went forth the dour unjust command
on him, whose high sonorous lyre shall claim
such want of Fortune and such wealth of Fame.

129

“Here courseth, see, the callèd Champa[257] shore,
with woods of od’orous wood ’tis deckt and dight:
See Cauchichina still of note obscure,
and of Ainam[258] yon undiscoverèd Bight:
Here the proud Empire famed evermore
for wide-spread lands and wealth and matchless might,
of China runs, and boasts the whole her own
’twixt torrid Cancer and the frigid Zone.

130

“Behold yon wondrous and incred’ible Wall,
this and that other Region built to part;
most certain symbol this which shows to all,
Imperial Puissance proud in arm and art:
These their born Princes to the throne ne’er call,
Nor Son succeedeth Sire in subject heart;
the prop’erest man as Monarch they devise,
Some Knight for virtue famèd, brave and wise.

131

“Parforce hide other vasty lands from thee
until what time no land remain unfound:
But leave thou not those Islands of the Sea,[259]
where Nature rises to Fame’s highest round:
This Realm half-shadowed, China’s empery
afar reflecting, whither ships are bound,
is the Japan, whose virgin silver mine
shall shine still sheen’ier with the Law Divine.[260]

132

“Here see o’er Oriental seas bespread
infinite island-groups and alwhere strewed:
Tidore, Ternáte view, whose burning head
lanceth the wavy flame and fiery flood:
There see the groves the biting clove-bud shed,
bought with the price of Portughueze’s blood;
here dwell the golden fowls, whose home is air
and never earthward save in death may fare.

133

“See Banda’s Islets, which enamelled glow
various painted by the rosy fruits;
variegate birds, that flit from bough to bough,
take tithe and tribute of the greeny nuts:
See Borneo’s sea-girt shore where ever flow
the perfumed liquor’s thick and curded gouts,
the tears of forest-trees men ‘Camphor’ clepe,
wherefore that Island crop of Fame shall reap.

134

“Timor thence further sendeth forth her store
of fragrant Saunders, wood medicinal:
See Sunda’s Isle,[261] so stretch her farther shore
that hideth Auster’s regions of appall:
The wand’ering men who inner wilds explore,
tell of a stream whose marvels never pall;
for, where its lone and single current floweth,
dead wood that in it falls a live stone groweth.

135

“Behold yon land, made island of the sea[262]
by Time, whose trembling flame in vapour swelleth,
see Petroil-fountain, and the prodigy
of od’orous juice the weeping tree distilleth;[263]
sweeter than scent-tears shed in Araby
by Cin’yras’ daughter, where for aye she dwelleth;
and see, how holding all that others hold,
soft silk she hoardeth and the nugget-gold.

136

“See in Ceylon that Peak[264] so stark, so gaunt,
shooting high o’er the clouds or mocking sight:
The native peoples hold it sacrosanct
for the famed Stone where print of foot is pight:
O’er lone Maldivia’s islets grows the plant,[265]
beneath profoundest seas, of sov’ereign might;
whose pome of ev’ry Theriack is confest
by cunning leech of antidotes the best.

137

“Eke shalt thou see toforn the Red Sea strait
Socotra, famed for Aloë’s bitter growth:
I subject other sea-girt Isles to ’wait
your steps where sandy Africk seaboard show’th;
and yieldeth floating mass[266] rare, odorate,
but whence it cometh none of mortals know’th:
Of Sam Lourenço see yon famous Isle,
which certain travellers Madagascar style.

138

“Here distant Orient’s new-found climates see,
climes on the world by this your Feat bestowèd
that opened Ocean-portals patent-free,
whose vasty plain with doughty hearts you plowèd.
But in the Ponent als a reason be,
a Lusian’s noble exploit be avowèd,
who being greatly by his King aggrieved,
shall force a passage Fancy ne’er conceived.[267]

139

“See yon huge Region whose contin’uous lines
course from Callisto to the contr’ary Pole;
superb shall’t be by boast of lucent mines
whose veins Apollo’s golden tincture stole.
Castile, your ally, worthily designs
to make its barb’arous neck her yoke to thole:
In varied regions bide its various tribes,
with different rites which different use prescribes.

140

“But here where Earth spreads wider, ye shall claim
realms by the ruddy Dye-wood made renown’d:
These of the ‘Sacred Cross’[268] shall win the name:
By your first Navy shall that world be found.
Along this seaboard, which your arm shall tame,
shall wend him seeking Earth’s extremest bound
Magellan who, good sooth, by birth shall be
a Portughueze in all save loyalty.

141

“And when his courses pass the midway place
which from the Pole Antarctick parts the Line,
he shall behold an all but Giant race[269]
holding the countries which therewith confine:
Still onwards lie the Straits that aye shall grace
his name, which sea with sea through land conjoin;
a sea and land where horrid Auster bideth,
and ’neath his frozen wings their measure hideth.[270]

142

“Thus far, O Portingalls! to you was given
the feats of future ages now to know;
how o’er those Oceans which your keels have riven
great-hearted Barons grandest deeds shall do:
And hence, since all with mighty toils have striven,
toils by whose Fame your favour aye shall grow
with your eternal Spouses debonnair,
who shall weave glorious crowns for you to wear:

143

“Ye can embark, for fav’ouring blows the Wind
and to your well-loved home the seas be clear.”
Thus spake the Goddess, and the Braves incline’d
from the glad Island of sweet Love to steer.
They bear refreshment of the noblest kind,
they bear the longed-for Comp’any, each his Fere,
the Nymph that ever shall in heart abide,
long as the sunshine warmeth land and tide.

144

So fared they, cutting through the Main serene
with favouring breezes that ne’er blew in ire,
till they had sighted that familiar scene
their Fatherland, and ever fond desire.
They past the Tagus-mouth, our stream amene,
and gave their Country and their dread loved Sire,
who willed their voyage, glory and renown
and added lustrous titles to his crown.

145

No more, my Muse![271] no more, for now my Lyre
untunèd lies, and hoarse my voice of Song;
not that of singing tire I, but I tire
singing for surd and horny-hearted throng.
Favours which Poet-fancy mostly fire
our Land gives not, ah, no! ’tis plunged too long
in lust of lucre, whelmed in rudest folly
of vile, austere and vulgar melancholy.

146

Nor ken I wherefore, by what Fate indign
she ’joys ne genial pride, ne gen’eral taste,
which strengthen mortal spirit and incline
to face all travail with a happy haste.
Wherefore, O King! thou whom the Will Divine
hath on the kingly throne for purpose place’d
look that thou be (and see the realms of Earth)
sole Lord of vassals peerless in their worth!

147

Look how they gladly wend by many a way,
with raging Bulls’ or rampant Lyons’ might,
self-doomed to sleepless night and foodless day,
to fire and steel, shaft-show’er and bullet-flight:
To torrid Tropicks, Arcticks frore and grey,
the Pagan’s buffet and the Moor’s despight;
to risks invis’ible threating human life,
to wrack, sea-monsters and the waves’ wild strife.

148

All risks to serve thy cause they dare affront,
to thee though distant yield they homage due,
of ev’ry hard command they bear the brunt
sans answer, ever prompt and ever true:
On single look of favour could they count,
infernal Demons, black with Hell’s own hue,
with thee they fain encounter, and they dare
unconquer’d Conqueror their King declare.

149

Favour them alway, gladden every face
with thy fair Presence, blithe Humanity;
of rig’orous rule relieve them, deal the grace
of milder law that leads to sanctity:
impart to long Experience rank and place,
an with Experience ’habit Honesty
to work thy Sovran will; thus all shall trow
what things befall them, Whence and When and How.

150

All favour thou in Duty’s different way,
as in each life the storèd talent lies:
Let the Religious for thy gov’ernance pray,
and beg a blessing on each high emprize;
fast they and fash their flesh for those who stray
in vulgar vices, and as wind despise
Ambition, ne’er shall holy Priest mislead
glare of vain-glory, nor of gain the greed.

151

Foster the Cavaliers with fair esteem,
that oft their fearless, fiery blood have lent
to spread not only Heaven’s law supreme,
but eke thy royal Rule pre-eminent.
Such men who fare to face each fell extreme
of climate in thy cause aye diligent,
conquer a double foe; the fone that live,
and (deadlier task) with dark, dumb danger strive.

152

So do, my Sire! that sons of famous lands
Britons, Italians, Germans and the Gaul,
ne’er vaunt that might of mortal man commands
thy Portingalls, who should command them all.
Take counsel only with experienced hands,
men who long years, long moons, saw rise and fall:
Many for gen’eral science fitness show,
yet the partic’ulars none save experts know.

153

Elegant Phormion’s philosophick store,
see how the practised Hannibal deridèd,
when lectured he with wealth of bellick lore
and on big words and books himself he pridèd.
Senhor! the Soldier’s discipline is more
than men may learn by mother-fancy guidèd:
Not musing, dreaming, reading what they write;
’tis seeing, doing, fighting, teach to fight.

154

But I, what dare I say, rude, humble, low,
to thee unknown, yes, even in thy dreams?
Yet oft from lips of Babes and Sucklings flow,
I trow, the words of wisdom man esteems:
Right honest studies my career can show
with long Experience blent as best beseems,
and Genius here presentèd for thy view;—
gifts, that conjoinèd appertain to few.

155

For serving thee an arm to Arms addrest;
for singing thee a soul the Muses raise;
nought lacks me save of thee to stand confest,
whose duty ’tis the Good to prize and praise:
If Heav’en concede me this, and if thy breast
deign incept worthy of a Poet’s lays;—
as doth presage my spirit vaticine
viewing thee pace the human path divine:—

156

Or do’ing such derring-do, that ne’er Meduse
shall Atlas-mountain like thy glances shake,
or battling on the plains of Ampeluse
Marocco’s mures[272] and Terodant to break;
my now esteemèd and rejoicing Muse
thy name o’er Earth, I swear, so famed shall make,
an Alexander shall in Thee be shown
who of Achilles envy ne’er shall own.

The Rejected Stanzas

These Stanzas, omitted by Camões, were discovered by Manoel de Faria y Sousa, and published in his Commentaries (Juan Sanches, 1639). The whole are extant in three manuscripts. Number I, the better of the two first, contains only six cantos: Number II, belonging to M. Correia Montenegro, embraces the whole poem. The third MS., in the hands of M. Luiz Franco, is given by Viscount Juromenha (Vol. VI 419). It has only four “rejected stanzas”; the first three are those of Faria y Sousa; and the fourth is that of the established text (Canto I 79) with a few unimportant changes of words and rhymes.

The Stanzas number:—

MS. | No. | 1, | 48 + 2 fragments | = | 49
” | ” | 2, | (Correia Montenegro’s) | = | 26
” | ” | 3, | (Luiz Franco’s) | = | 4
Total | 79

I will not here enter into the consideration why the Stanzas were left out. Many of them fully equal those retained in the popular “Lusiads”; but almost all contain something opposed to public, or rather to priestly, sentiment. A cursory glance shows that not a few want the polish and finish which distinguish the Poem. I have purposely followed suit for the sake of contrast and fidelity. Juromenha’s original text is printed in verso, that the reader may judge how literal is my version, which, for additional security, was submitted to Mr. J. J. Aubertin, the translator of “The Lusiads.”

Manuscript No. I

Canto I Stanza 77 (modified).

1

He spake in fury wood, like wight insane,
And straight alighted on the Theban way,
Where mortal gest and human vesture tane,
He bore where new-born Phoebus bears the Day.
Now spans his flight the Med’iterranean Main,
Now spurns the bounds of Cleopatra’s sway;
Now leaves to right the Garamántes-land,
And circumjacent sheets of Libyan sand.

2

Now leaves he Mer’oe ’mid the fiery downs,
Fed by the waters of the Sev’en-flood River,
Realms which the high and holy President[273] owns,
Of Christ His doctrine old and true Believer:
He passes drouthy land whose people wones
Lacking the Lakes that roll their waters ever;
The very birth-place of the secret Nyle
Who breeds the monstrous brood of crocodile.

3

Hence to the Prasum Headland fast he flies;
And, making Mozambíque, in briefest space
Becomes the Counterfeit, in Moorman guise,
Of one that held high honourable place.
And, as the Regent much this Moor did prize,
Entering with somewhat sad and chargèd face,
Began the Theban thus his plaint to make,
Removing others who sat near the Shaykh.

Canto I (after Stanza 80).

“And eke, that credit these my words befall,
Showing what plotteth yon false Capitayne,
Know, when thou wendedst on thy guest to call
I heard this case debated ’twixt a twain:
In what I tell thee make no interval,
And I will truly tell thee how, where, when,
Thou canst destroy them; for I lief believe
We should deceive him who would us deceive.”

Canto III (after Stanza 10).

“Between this Ocean, and the waters shed
To feed large Tanaïs, flowing ceaseless flood,
Dwell the Sarmatae races, who are fed
On mare-milk diet mixt with purpling blood.
Here live the Mysian peoples that o’erspread
A part of Asia, low, inglorious brood;
Abii who banish women; and with these
A host of tribes that drink Borysthenes.”

Canto III.

“But his ill mother following whither led
Her woman’s bosom ready aye to range,
Took Dom Bermudo to her marriage-bed—
And Dom Bermudo’s brother takes in change.
See the foul, sinful, bestial action bred
By crime begetting crime! Strange, mighty strange!
That left her husband she remains for e’er
His marriage-sister and his married fere.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 2).

Translated in the Millié-Dubeux edit. of 1862.

“The meed of valour Bastards aye have claimèd
By Arts or Arms, or haply both conjoinèd;
Such were of fabled Gods the most enfamèd
To whom rude Ancients highest rank assignèd.
Hermes, and doct Apollo still are namèd
For varied Science with long Art combinèd;
Others by Arms alone prevail; so reign
Bacchus and Hercules, that Theban Twain.

2

“Homer and Orpheus, eke, of birth were base,
The pair by Po’etry raised to such degree;
And they, the Sires of that Imperial race,
Who founded Troy and Rome for Italy.
Nay, an in written legend trust we place,
Though many Philip made the father be
Of Macedonia’s Youth, not few would prove
Great Nectanébus[274]filcht his mother’s love.

3

“Thus Justiciary Pedro’s bastard son,
Being exalted o’er the realm to sway,
By Gestes of arms such goods of Fortune won
That equalled ev’ery Great of bygone day.
He, when his kingdom feared to be undone
And prostrate lie, the proud Castilian’s prey,
Bateth the terror his own lieges tries;
And in all others Esp’erance falsifies.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 11).

Omitted because Catalonia and Arragon
did not then belong to Castile (?).

“Remainèd none in realm of Tarragon
Who shirkt to mell in Mavors’ dour emprize:
None in the noble City, whose renown
Upon her founder Scipio’s name relies.
And last not least the far-famed Barcelon
Sent warmen tried in warlike exercise:
All these strong powers uniteth haughty Spain
Against our little Lusitanian reign.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 13).

“Oh, foes unnat’ural! Nature so misbred,
Race of thy race’s name disgrace that art!
Degenerates! caitiffs! say what feeble Dread,
Sans wisdom, reason, all Man’s better part,
Have made a gallant people, born and bred
Loyal and brave with clean and candid heart,
Offend in such base guise? But I suspect
Amid the Great this be the least defect.”

Canto IV (in lieu of Stanza 21).

“E’en as the noble Youth of Roman strain
Strengthend the Senate, fain in fear to fly
The Carthaginian who, all-sovereign,
His whetted blade to shrinking throats brought nigh;
When worth’ily winning surname ‘African,’
His furious force so did their force defy,
His doubtful country free as air he made
When jealous Fabius still his rede delay’d.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 27).

“Now Titan’s daughter fresh and rosy came
Bringing that memorable, deathless day,
When Vespers chaunted are in Mary’s name,
Hon’ouring the holy month whose name is May.
This day for battle having fittest claim
Was chosen: Now, as paled the morning Gray
Bleaching the skies, both Kings unsheathed their swords
Their hosts enheartening with hearty words.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 33).

“And, Emperors! you that held and had command
O’er so much Earth, aye ready to resist
In asp’erous conflict, and the wrong withstand
Of cruel Traitors raising Treason’s crest:
Complain ye not: Nay, well this chance attend,
One of the noblest Kings, and loved the best,
Sees ’gainst his law, his crown, his self, his all,
Vavasors rise to sue a stranger’s thrall.

Canto IV.

These Homeric stanzas on the deaths of Portuguese
knights took away interest from the central
figure, the King.

“Piercèd[275] Giraldo’s vitals through and through
And eke the huge thick targe he snatcht away
From Perez whom he killed; his own with hew
And strangest hack of cutlass useless lay.
Dies Pedro, and Duarte dies (in lieu
Of death amid the Brigians): Born were they
Both in Braganza, brave in youthful pride
Together lived they, fought they, fell they, died.

2

“Lopo and Vincent de Lisbóa bleed;
Sworn in the common cause to meet their fate;
Or both the crown to gain and Victory’s meed
To snatch from all whom most enfamed this bate.
Afonso flieth from his battle-steed;
For five Castilians (who in ambush wait
to ’venge five comrades slain in earli’er strife)
Packing around him pluck his precious life.

3

“Down falls Hilario drilled by spear-heads three;
But first he took the vengeance of his spear;
He mourneth not because his Sprite goes free,
But for-that comes in it Antonia fair:
Flitteth the fug’itive Spirit fast, and flee
With it the thoughts sustaining all to dare;
And as life fled the service of his dame,
Fell from his clay-cold lips her broken name.”

Canto IV (in lieu of Stanza 39).

“His foll’owers favour with a piercing cry
This goodly lunge of lance; nor is he slow
To snatch another (for innum’erous lie
The weapons lost by battle’s losing throw):
He runs with couchèd spear: His bravery
Urgeth his Braves who, brent with martial lowe,
Into the courser’s flanks keen rowels thrust,
And lance the foeman level with the dust.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 40).

1

The corresponding deaths of Spanish knights.

“Velasquez dies with Sanches de Toledo,
A mighty hunter this, and that a clerke:
Galbes eke perisheth surnamed ‘Sem Medo,’[276]
For thus his comrades called for countermark:
Montánchez, Oropésa, Mondonhedo
(Albeit skilled in arms, in sinews stark),
Fell by Antonio’s hand, stout youth and brave
Whose lance more dext’erous drave them to the grave.

2

“Braggart Guevára, who his front had dyed,
And hands and beard with blood that tinged the plain;
That he might bluster how the gory tide
Had spurted painting him with honour’d stain:
Him, bell’owing such bravados in his pride,
Pedro who heard the vauntings loud and vain,
Felled with such side stroke, that his empty head
Flew from his body and his base life fled.

3

“Flew high in airy space his feckless pate
While still a-boasting of some blatant Geste:
Pedro, besprinkled by the squirt and jet,
Feels black blood trickling down his beard and breast;
Wherewith the mal’apert pays his vengeance debt.
Carrilho’s sun eke setteth in its west,
Joam de Lorca and Robledo follow;
While th’ other braves in flight their boasts must swallow.

4

“Salazar, famous par’asite, and the head
Pander who made Sevilha town infame;
Whom his false leman had at night-tide fled
Though to the ’campment she had brought her shame;
Lief would with other friend this fair friend bed,
For-that the ducats wherewithal he came,
Were lost upon a cast; nor were they lost
Had but a hand of spades came uppermost.

5

“His she-friend’s treason gars him wits to tyne;
And threaten un’iverse, earth and vagueing skies
Blaspheming; and resolve with rage indign
All who dare cross his valour to chastise:
Encount’ering Gaspar (who his Catherine
Loves as his life) the broadsword fast he plies,
Till air fire-smitten makes him fain believe
Such stroke of mighty blade a hill could cleave.

6

“Fondly he hopes the foe to hew in twain;
But Gaspar, sighting overhead the blade,
Runs in, and catcheth him with gripping strain:
’Twas a fair feat of skill and hardihead:
The Spaniard clippeth, yet doth not restrain
His boastful threat’ening, although conquerèd;
The forceful Portingall with short delay
Unarms his hands and leaps from out his way.

7

“Then, lest his foeman use such crafty mode
Himself had used, he deals stoccado-thrust:
In fine the broadsword in his bosom-blood
He bathes that naught to vengeance mote he trust.
Flieth the furious ghost and in the wood
Tartarean still blasphemes; relates his lust
For vengeance, who no more can scourge his quean,
While him Alecto scourgeth long and keen.

8

“The Spatha’s[277] metal to the damnèd host
Ill-names he calleth heaping curses dread;
Which, when it entered not, his ducats lost,
And lost his life when it had enterèd.
Pluto to gar him pay Sin’s scot and cost,
Shows him the trait’orous ladye-friend who fled
’Joyed by his rival raining greedy kisses:—
He starts to strike them but the Shades he misses.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 44).

“Oh vain reflections’ guiling human sense!
How could this darkling error seal your sight?
How have ye hugged this gay and glad pretence
That lures to ’sanguined hate and baneful fight?
And now of bloodshed dour experience,
A sore dread trial of the deadly blight
Is shown to thee. And now when known thy lot
Thou shalt give counsel which thou tookest not.

2

“The corpses of the Cavaliers, our fone,
Fed the foul creatures of the field and wood:
The nearest fountains till some days were gone
Distilled their crystal black with human blood.
The meadow-shepherds, and the swains who wone
Upon the mountain, loathed the fulsome food,
The feral bird—which for a year and more,
Smackt of the gorgèd flesh and human gore.”

Canto IV (Stanza 49: varia lectio).

Pond’ering such mighty deeds of derring-do
Prophetick Proteus thus to Neptune cried:—
“I fear shall spring such Braves from Braves like these
Who the great sceptre of thy Reigns shall seize!”

2

“He gaineth now the Porte inexpugnable
Whereof the Traitor-Count[278] first oped the gate,
In blood to wash the love inevitable
Fired in Rodrigo’s[279] heart by hand of Fate.
Yet this was not the cause abominable
That wasted populous Hispanian State:
God for some hidden judgment gave command
The house be opened by Rodrigo’s hand.

3

“But now thou livest safe, O noble Spain!
(If knightly force can save its land a fall)
From other loss like this, from shame and stain,
Who for a Porter hast the Portingall.
This happy Fortune waited on the reign
Of King Joanné,[280] who the bounding wall
Of Spanish-lond molested many years;
And conquerèd a higher crest uprears.”

Canto IV (Stanza 61: varia lectio).

“Of Venice, splendid in prosperity,
Venice, whereto the fisher peoples fled
From Gothic fury, and the cruelty
Of Attila, and built the pauper town
Now raised to rich estate and high renown.”

Canto IV (after Stanza 66).

“Nor chosen was sans justest cause and care
To fill the lofty throne of governance,
This King, whose noble heart and spirit rare
Pledgèd and promised highest esperance:
For him, there being no directer heir
And urgèd mostly by such confidence,
Joanné chose as heir to reign alone,
Having no son-inheritor to the throne.

Canto IV (after Stanza 86).

“There did we promise, if His mercy deign
To bear us safe where Phoebus bursts the womb,
Or to blind worlds we would His faith ordain,
Or headstrong Heathenesse to death would doom.
All for our Souls’ eternal health were fain
With pure, veracious shrift our Sprites t’ illume,
Whereby, though Her’eticks may its power decry,
Souls like the ren’ovate Phoenix heav’enward fly.

2

“Then to partake of Ghostly Meat we went,
By whose most gracious boon so many days,
Sans taste of other earthly nutriment,
Erst were sustained Elias and Moysès:
Bread, whose deep secrets ne thought eminent
Ne subtle lore, ne soaring fantasies
Shall ever fathom, ever plumb its might,
An to dark Reason Faith deny her light.”

Canto VI (after Stanza 7).

There, in sublime Italia, yawns a cave,
Secret and celebrate, Avernus hight,
Wherethrough the Trojan leader bold and brave
Gainèd Infernus-realm of gloomy Night.
And als this Antre easy adit gave,
By road untrod, to Ocean’s middle site,
The Sea-god Neptune’s proper tenement:
Now thither Bacchus ’gan the long descent.

Canto VI (after Stanza 24).

Dolour of fell Dislove hath no respect
For fault or for unfault on either part;
If what thou lovest lief thy love reject
Only some sore revenge shall salve the smart.
But say, What profit shall thy love expect,
When she thou lovest hath bestowed her heart?
How shall for others Love himself deny
When Love delights his foll’owers aye to fly?

Canto VI (after Stanza 40).

“What boots recounting feats and gestes notorious
Of cel’ebrate Capitaynes and grand campaigns,
Where vaunting Death boasts asp’erous might victorious
O’er alien will he bendeth as he fain ’is?
Let others sing and say the deeds memorious
Achieved by Conq’uerors on their battle-plains:
Let it be mine (if worlds will hear) to tell
How by a pair of eyes’ mere force I fell.”

2

No little pleasure to Velloso gave
So fair a subject watch and ward to ’guile,
For as dure warfare made him dour and brave,
So gentled Love his breast by soft’ening wile.
Such is the cunning of this Cupid-knave,
So Art with Nature can he reconcile,
While mortal hearts with blandness it endowereth,
Lovers with double pow’er his will empowereth.

3

“Recount” (quoth he), “recount of Love, fair Sir!
And of the wondrous chances Love befell,
Still his sharp arrows this sad bosom stir
That may not hurt of open wound dispel.”
With him agreed each watchful mariner,
That all and ev’ery, then and there, should tell
Their tales of Love, and how the ventures farèd:—
Thiswise its watch to keep the crew preparèd.

4

Then quoth Le’onardo: “Here let no man wot
From me to gather fables known of yore:
Whoso would quote the tears of alien lot
Himself exempted hath no tears in store.
Sith Love with magick eye-glance mortals smote
Those dearest en’emies mine smote none so sore
’Mid men as me; nor Pyramus nor him
Who from Abydos Helle’s stream did swim.

5

“Fortune, who vaunteth o’er the world her might
Already drave me far from Fatherland,
Where I long time had lived, sufficient quite
To lose a blessing which I held in hand.
Yes, free I lived; yet nought astounds my sprite
Save that my freedom I could not command,
But changed for prison, since mine every thought,
Would I or nould I, boon of Love besought.”

Canto VI (after Stanza 81).

“Thou Guard divine, who dost with Angels dwell,
And of the Starry Pole hast seigniory;
Thou who didst bring Thy people Israèl
Through the burst waters of the blushing sea:
If from more risks than what t’ Aeneas fell
Or Ithican Ulysses sav’edst thou me,
Passing Apollo’s largely bounded path
Through rage of Aeolus and Tethys’ wrath.”

Canto VI (after Stanza 94).

Look ye, how following fast on fierce despair
We win the weal that seemed beyond our range;
Thus ever dogging happy days sans care
Comes hateful Sorrow with her certain change.
Whoso would win such lore, such secret bare,
How Chance shall aye Security estrange,
I wot, his wisdom would no blessing gain,
But breed a madness in his brooding brain.

2

I have short answer for the wights who say
That fickle Fortune deals in living lies;
That God hath made for pillar of His sway
A goddess ranging aye ’twixt fall and rise.
Importunate opinion men obey
That Man, whose nature with the Angels vies,
For whom his God such goodness wrought, is rulèd
By blindfold chances, and by luck befoolèd.

3

Who saith that Good or Ill be reason why,
The lowly up, the lofty downward, go;
What shall he say me se’eing the low rise high?
What shall he say me se’eing the high fall low?
If some should say “we’re born predestined,” I
Find it an asp’erous reason so to trow;
If darkly bound by bond of Destiny,
What boots a Sinner or a Saint I be?

4

Such dreadful storm the Portingalls tormented,
All were assurèd life was surely lost;
Sudden it passèd and to them presented
Venus the guerdon which they yearned for most.
Meanwhile Cabral whose wreck and wrack distented
The list of losses on that portless coast,
Saves his life gladly, and at once he loses ’t
Because what men call Chance or Dest’iny choses ’t.

5

An he must lose his life in one short hour,
To save the span before what could avail?
We ask why Fortune’s all prevailing pow’er
Upon the heels of ill sent nought of weal?
Well said the Sage, so famed for el’egant lore,
Simonides, who from his safe portail
Beheld his rev’elling friends within the hall
Crusht by the fragments of the fallen wall:—

6

“Oh, force of Fortune grievous, sore to dree,
That hast so many in one moment slain!
Say for what greater bane hast savèd me
Whom thou hast savèd from this present bane?
Certès, the wrath of Heav’en right well I see:
No harm sufficeth for his rage insane:
Nor ill he workèd but the will he had
Eftsoons of working something worse than bad.”

7

Right well I wot that many shall be found
With subtle reasons Faith to re-assure;
Many by Second Causes shall expound
High matters sound sure judgment doth depure.
To all I pledge myself, I could respond
Did art of scribe such mighty theme endure:
I but respond that long Experience
Oft shows your Science lacking common Sense.

Manuscript No. II

Canto VIII (after Stanza 32).

1

“This the foundation-stone sublimely laid
Of the Braganza House, illustrious strain,
Which in estate and grandeur all outweigh’d
Whatever vaunts the high Hispanian reign.
Seest thou him, who with the stout Armade
Cutteth th’ Hesperian sea, forthwith to gain
His brave objective; wends this stout pretender
Azamor town to fight and gar surrender?

2

“ ’Tis ducal Gemes, ’heriting from his sires
Of old nobility a name memorious,
Who does this mighty deed; and ’s high desires
Fulfilled, to Portugale returns victorious.
This time a valour which the world admires
Leaveth the Moorman in such fear inglorious,
Who to the Present is nowise relievèd
Of the cold burden in the Past conceivèd.

3

“And, if the famous Duke forbore as wont
Catholick conquests farther still to bear,
Unto Marocco’s mures and Terudant,
And other thousand thorpes the Haven near;
Deem not his constant soul of spirit scant,
Or wanting energy or slow to dare;
’Twas that his loyalty to cross declinèd
The certain limits which his King assignèd.”

Canto VIII

“In such unfairest odds and chance of fray
One of our soldiers was begirt by foes;
But he, by valour more than mail, makes way
And of true warrior-heart fair ’surance shows;
Slain the near charger with his sabre-sway
Its rider’s head upon the plain he throws;—
Brave sworder-feat!—and, pace by pace, he leaveth
Arear the foeman whom such exploit grieveth.”

Canto X (after Stanza 72).

“Shalt see, in fine, conspire all India, ’drest
To bellick apparatus; peoples rush
Cháúl, Maláca, Goa-town t’ invest,
At once such different sites to seize and crush.
But see, now Cháúl City sorely prest,
The seas with em’inent billows flies to brush
Castro, in haste his Portingalls to save
When only God in Mercy’s aid they crave.

2

“Se’est thou yon Paynim King so fain of fight
Burn, overrun, beleaguer, firm persist
In throwing forces which the land affright
Against a little squad that loveth Christ?
But bear that gen’erous Pundonor in sight,
Ne siege ne battle e’er before hath wist;
See how the sold’iery flying posts secure,
Pass to the post of peril dire and dure.

Canto VIII (after Stanza 36).

“In such unfairest odds and chance of fray
One of our soldiers was begirt by foes;
But he, by valour more than mail, makes way
And of true warrior-heart fair ’surance shows;
Slain the near charger with his sabre-sway
Its rider’s head upon the plain he throws;—
Brave sworder-feat!—and, pace by pace, he leaveth
Arear the foeman whom such exploit grieveth.”

3

“There shall Ataide, most for prudence known,
Strong in the ghostly comfort of the Lord,
Where Time and Need demand such force be shown,
With more than human valour aid afford.
Until its salvage object shall disown
With grievous losses yon vile Pagan horde,
Who crusht in thousand cruel fights shall rue
The war, and hurry for a truce to sue.

4

“While here so happeth on the coast that glows
Of Asia and Am’erica sombre cold,
There not the less in Europe bellicose,
And Barb’ary’s wild uncultivated wold,
Shall show thy Race, Elysian, valorous
Its worth and with a freezing fear enfold
The seething Zone, that sees one conquest won
Pass to three other and ne’er pause till done.

5

“Barriga, brave of braves, they here shall sight,
Guide of Zafim,[281] in war of prime account,
Who finds no man-at-arms to foil his might,
O’errun the Mauritanian plain and mount.
But see how th’ Infidels, by luck of fight
And doom disastrous, in the very brunt
Make him and his Bellona’s battle-prize
For in such chances Valour hopeless lies.

6

“But past the perils of this imm’inent chance,
See how he snatcheth while to durance led
From grasp of Moorish foe the beamy lance,
And lays with single lunge its lancer dead.
Then with strong arm the weapon swung askance,
He saves his friends the while his foes have fled:
Thus all triumphant wend his men their way
Whither their lot was sad captivity.

7

“Lo! here is he by snare once more beset,
And in the darkness of vile stable lain,
Loaded with iron fetters of such weight,
From off the floor he mote not rise again.
But see the heart with gen’erous fire irate,
Tear up the stake that showed a bloody stain,
And brain the haughty Moor who had not fear’d
Foul hand to fasten on his honoured beard?

8

“Yet further see yon faithless Hagarene,
By the commandment of his Inf’idel King,
Visit the daring deed with scourge so keen
That strips from ribs his robes with stripes that sting.
Yet the brave Baron scorns one word, nor e’en
An ‘Ah!’ a murmur, may his tortures wring:
To Portugale the ragged vesture goes
Wherewith to raise a ransom for the foes.

9

“Behold yon Aguer Headland tane, and lost
By fault of tardy succouring soldiery:
And see’st thou great Carvalho ’mid the host
Hostile, like baited bull the ring o’erfly?
Hear him ’mid thirty Moorish corpses boast
Whirling his broadsword, crying:—‘Since I die
Let dead atone for this mine òbscure doom,
These carrion deadlings form my fittest tomb!’

10

“See how when both his legs a passing ball
In pieces dasht and shanks from trunk had mown;
On arms and knees he doth his best to crawl
And fight with force and valour never known:
Round and about the field evanish all
Hagar’s hard children who no pity own;
And with their shafts and javelins far they deal,
The death they dare not by a nearer steel.”

Canto X (after Stanza 73).

“With sim’ilar labours, Gestes so great, so new
Of valour never viewed, nor reached by thought,
To Honour shall ye rise so high, so true,
To excellences Heaven’s will hath wrought
’Mid worlds of men for you and only you,
While Phoebus warms what salty billows moat:
Rare boons be these which rarely doled we find
To man, and only in you men conjoin’d.

2

“Religion first, the Truths sublime reveal’d
In earthly garb of pious holy Zeal;
Fain to Divine Obedience self to yield
And all imbibèd with its works of weal.
Thus men fare swimming to th’ Elysian field;
And thus in Life and Death shall ever deal
Mortals, who strain to win the princely prize
Which high religious Monarchy affies.

3

“Loyalty second, that makes great and grand
Above all others, hearts of noble strain;
Whereby a certain likeness mortals fand
To Choirs immortal in the Heav’enly Reign.
For this be known o’er farthest sea and land
The passing merits of the Lusitan;
Ne’er to his Maker nor sworn King forsworn,
Nor holds such public Faith to public scorn.

4

“Valour next cometh, which of yore did greet,
In olden Lusus, men who sang and wrote;
And which your Portingalls with greater feat
Certify veridic withouten doubt:
Affording novel theme to modern writ,
With their high exploits of memorious note;
And, vanquishing o’er the world the most renown’d,
By fewer vanquisht they shall ne’er be found.

5

“Conquest shall prove the fourth, which in the power
Of only Portugale full-forced resideth;
Since in the higher Hemisphere and lower
O’er Earth’s four quarters she alone abideth:
The four great Nations only serve to show her
What high mysterious Hope her conquests guideth;
That Christian, Moorman, Turk, and Gentile all,
Joinèd in single law shall feel her thrall.

6

“Discov’ery comes the fifth, which of a truth
To none save Lusus’ children doth belong;
Who have explorèd all from North to South
Where suns be short-lived and where days be long.
Now by uncertain ways, unused, uncouth,
From Ponent Lèvantward, in daring strong,
She wends to circle Earth by shortest tract:[282]
A feat which never was till now a fact.

7

“I pass in silence o’er the Piety
And courteous ways that mark the Lusian breast;
Temperance, Holy Faith, Zeal, Charity,
With other gifts as easy to attest.
For ’tis a not’able point of verity,
Moral Philosophy’s own rule and hest,
No single virtue e’er hath Man array’d
When all the others do not arm and aid.

8

“But these, the first foundation and the base
Of those renownèd five transcendencies,
Whereon they rest and rise by Nature’s grace,
And whence they borrow fair dependencies.
Here I neglect; for stoop I not to trace
That meaner matter which the tendence is
Of human nature in the gen’eral view:—
Only I tell what dwells in only you.

9

“Natheless expect not to run clear and pure,
The course uneven of your Race’s story:
Such the condition of our state obscure,
Of human life-tide fragile, transitory:
Death and Destruction, travail sore and dure
Shall mingle water in your wine of glory;
Yet ne’er shall force of Fortune, nor of Fate
Degrade your gifts, debase your high estate.

10

“Shall dawn the Day o’er either Hemisphere
By you explored, and conquerèd in fight,
Where battle, slaughter, prison-doom strike fear
In all the peoples subject to your might:
The twain of mightiest empires which is peer
In Spain beneath one sceptre shall unite;
Owning for cap’ital, Ladye of the Land,
The goodly City hither sends your band.[283]

11

“And now, o’er earth establisht, Race renown’d
Whom God in Cath’olick bosom hath conservèd,
Redeemed from horrid pains of Hell profound,
For hosts of damnèd Heathenry reservèd;
Dower’d with the losses of Lusbel[284] immund,
Lusbel, by vile and vulgar spirits servèd;
Since all Earth’s glories ye have learnt to gain,
’Ware lest ye lose the glory sovereign.”

Canto X (after Stanza 141).

“Hence shall he wend[285] his way, and end the light
Of Life, when landed on that fatal Isle:
Nor less his vent’urous Fleet shall wing her flight
Returning homeward from such miracle;
The far-famed ship ‘Victória’ men shall sight
Anchored in safest waters by Sevile,
When she had girdled Ocean-plain profound
And circled Earth in one continuous round.”